<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Loyal poems and satyrs upon the times since the beginning of the Salamanca plot written by several hands ; collected by M.T.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13558572</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13558572</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100279</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100279)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 803:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Loyal poems and satyrs upon the times since the beginning of the Salamanca plot written by several hands ; collected by M.T.</title>
                  <author>Taubman, Matthew, d. 1690?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Mat. Taubman.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Rye House Plot, 1683 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100279:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100279:1"/>
            <p>Loyal Poems AND SATYRS Upon the TIMES, Since the beginning of the <hi>Salamanca Plot.</hi> Written by ſeveral Hands.</p>
            <p>Collected by <hi>M. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Achitophel.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Plots true or falſe are neceſſary things</l>
               <l>To ſet up Common-Wealths, and Ruin Kings.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Smith</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Ruſſel-Street</hi> near <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100279:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100279:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Illuſtrious, moſt Honourable, &amp; moſt Loyal, THE LORDS and GENTLEMEN OF THE Loyal Club, At the <hi>Dog</hi> in <hi>Drury-Lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honourable, and moſt Loyal.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Collection of LOYAL POEMS reſcu'd from the Flames (when our Illium was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a ſecond time on Fire) preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an humble Offering at your Feet. It is the Poets Loyalty and Religion, aſſerting thoſe Rights with their Pens, which you have avouch'd to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with your Swords; The Defence of which was the firſt Foundation of this Illuſtrious Society. A moſt Noble Inſtitution, and deſtin'd to as glorious ends, When Factious Caballs began to prevail, and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion under the diſguiſe of Liberty began to invade on
<pb facs="tcp:100279:3"/>the Prerogative, then was't the Royal Party began to meet with generous Reſolution, and ſtand up as one Man for the Intereſt of the Crown and Government. When <hi>Abſolom</hi> had Conſpir'd with <hi>Achitophel</hi> againſt the envy'd Life and Peaceful Reign of Injur'd <hi>David,</hi> what leſs could engage in his Defence than the Princes and Chiefs of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> This was that Royal Aſſembly which like you kept the Aſpiring Rebells in awe, and the Monarch againſt all their Conſpiracies ſafe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Throne. Where then can theſe Innocent Loyal Truths rather fly for Protection, than to You the moſt Eminent Patrons of Truth and Loyalty?</p>
            <p>I fear it will be counted Arogance in me to devote ſo mean a Trifle to the whole Body Politick, the leaſt Member of which is worthy of a far Richer Oblation, but our whole Artillery being level'd againſt the Factions, what <hi>Hercules</hi> Arm can guard me againſt the Multitude? Againſt the Imps of Rebellion, there is no Power to invoke, but the Sons of Loyalty, nor a ſpell againſt the Witchcraft of the Murmuring Cabals, but the Muſical Charms of the ROYAL CL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>B. That Club ſo nobly founded, and ſo amicably carry'd on with unanimity of Heart and Voice for the long Life and Preſervation of his Majeſty and Loyal Brother in the Lawful Succeſſion againſt all Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>I dare not venture after the manner of Dedications to enter on Encomium, or Launce out into the boundleſs praiſe of ſo many Illuſtrious and Eminent Heroes, the meaneſt of whom is a Theme ſufficient for the moſt Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Pen; but being threatned before on the like
<pb facs="tcp:100279:3"/>occaſion (for my Collection of Loyal Songs Dedicated to his R. Highneſs) I only implore your gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and acceptance, that under that Influence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guarded from all the Treacherous Aſſaults of my Enemies, Whigs and Trimmers, I may walk abroad in ſafety under the Character of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours Moſt Obedient, and Moſt Devoted Humble Servant, <hi>Mat. Taubman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:100279:4"/>
            <head>THE Loyal Club.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HAil, <hi>Royal Synod!</hi> Sons of Loyalty:</l>
               <l>That <hi>Parliament</hi> whoſe <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Tongues</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree:</l>
               <l>With one conſent the <hi>Loyal Health</hi> goes round,</l>
               <l>And Univerſal Harmony is found:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Crowns</hi> Defence, the Beauty of the <hi>Field,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Peoples Safe-guard,</hi> and the <hi>Prince's Shield:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Pride</hi> o'th' <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Camp,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Sterling Ore</hi> that bears the <hi>Royal Stamp:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Touch-ſtone</hi> where no <hi>Counterfeit</hi> can paſs,</l>
               <l>But ſoon diſcovers all its <hi>ſecret Braſs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Trimmer</hi> and <hi>Whig,</hi> like <hi>Copper</hi> fac'd with <hi>Tin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Currant</hi> without, and <hi>Counterfeit</hi> within;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Bitt</hi> and <hi>Bridle</hi> of the <hi>Factious Bands,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That checks their ſtubborn Necks, and binds their Hands:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Rebels Dread</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> that gives them <hi>Law;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Rabbles Curb,</hi> that keeps the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in awe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whiliſt every night You your bright beams diſplay,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Factions,</hi> like <hi>groſs Vapours,</hi> waſte away.</l>
               <l>YOU, like the <hi>Stars,</hi> fix'd conſtant to your <hi>Sphere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>CHARLES his Wain</hi> pay Homage all the year;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:100279:4"/>
               <l>Whil'ſt <hi>Whig-Cabals,</hi> like <hi>Exhalations</hi> drawn</l>
               <l>From all the poys'nous <hi>Treaſon-Sinks</hi> in Town,</l>
               <l>From their aſpiring <hi>Heights</hi> come tumbling down;</l>
               <l>The groſſer <hi>Bubbles</hi> mounting up too far,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Light'ning</hi> fall, ſhot from an angry <hi>Star.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>Whig</hi> nor <hi>Trimmer</hi> can inhabit there;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They</hi>'re <hi>Exhalations</hi> cannot reach <hi>Your Sphere.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Wills i'th' Wiſp</hi> that lead Men from the Road,</l>
               <l>To ſee a Sun more bright, revile their God:</l>
               <l>The Sun which gave them Being they diſ-own,</l>
               <l>And fall to Earth, who cannot mount his Throne.</l>
               <l>When e're that <hi>Fiery-Comet</hi> does appear</l>
               <l>Within the Center of our <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Fate-portending <hi>Tail</hi> does ſtill pronounce,</l>
               <l>The fall of Kingdoms and the date of Crowns.</l>
               <l>That Monſtrous Tyrant with his <hi>Gorgon</hi> face,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe looks are Death, this late had been our Caſe,</l>
               <l>Had not the LOYAL CLUB retriev'd our Fate,</l>
               <l>And ſtood the <hi>Atlas</hi> of the <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Throne</hi> Heaven guard, and HIM that ſits thereon,</l>
               <l>And YOU, next Heaven, the <hi>Pillars</hi> of that Throne;</l>
               <l>May <hi>Loyalty</hi> with Friendſhip link for ever,</l>
               <l>No Tyrants force that <hi>Gordian Knot</hi> diſſever.</l>
               <l>May never <hi>Diſcord</hi> in this CLUB be found,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Ecchoing Huzza</hi>'s from th' <hi>Skies</hi> rebound,</l>
               <l>And ev'ry Glaſs with <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Health be crown'd.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:100279:5"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE Poets Addreſs to the King.</hi> 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Excellency of Monarchy. a Panegyrick.</hi> 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>On his Majeſties Recovery at</hi> Winſor. 7</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Succeſſion.</hi> 10</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Paradox againſt Liberty, Writen by the Lords, during their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in the</hi> Tower. 13</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The laſt Speech of Sr.</hi> Edmundbury Godfrye's <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>On the Death of the Protestant</hi> Joyner. 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Innocence <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nveil'd; or, a Poem on the Acquittal of the Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> Scrogs. 28</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Advice to the Painter's Adviſer.</hi> 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Hypocritical Chriſtian: or the Conventicling Citizen.</hi> 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>On the Loyal Apprentices Feaſt.</hi> 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>On old Doctor</hi> Wild's <hi>new Poem to his old Friend upon the new Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scanda! Proof, or an Heroick Poem on the Renowned Champions of the good old Cauſe, Impudent</hi> Dick Janeway, <hi>and the reſt of the Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tribe.</hi> 48</item>
               <item>Fitz—Harris <hi>his Farwell to the World, or a Traytors Juſt Reward.</hi> 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Meal Tubb Plot.</hi> 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Dialogue between the Ghoſts of the two laſt Parliaments at their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview Fuimur Troes</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>Ghoſt's Advice.</hi> 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nitimur in Vetitum</hi> Oxford <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> 60</item>
               <item>Weſtminſter <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> 61</item>
               <item>Tom Think <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> 74</item>
               <item>Sejanus, <hi>or the Popular Favourite.</hi> 70</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Whig Caball.</hi> 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Presbyterian Club.</hi> 77</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The true Presbyterian without Diſguiſe.</hi> 80</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Diſſenter.</hi> 87</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Sollicitous Citizen.</hi> 90</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iter Boreale.</hi> 94</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Mad-mens Hoſpital, or Presbyterian Itch</hi> 96</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>State Caſes put to</hi> Jack Presbyter. 99</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Geneva <hi>Litany.</hi> 102</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Norwich <hi>Litany.</hi> 105</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Loyall Litany.</hi> 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The laſt will and Teſtament of</hi> Anthony <hi>King of</hi> Poland. 111</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Codecil to the Former Will.</hi> 115</item>
               <item>Shaftsburys <hi>farewell, or the Aſſociation.</hi> 120</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Recovery.</hi> 123</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>On the Kings Deliverance at</hi> Newmarket. 127</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100279:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Poets Addreſs</hi> TO THE KING.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THO Scribling Factions are ſo ſawcy grown,</l>
               <l>To dart curſt Libels at your Sacred Throne,</l>
               <l>To ſtrive to pre-depoſe your Royal Heirs,</l>
               <l>And ſeek your Life who frankly gave them theirs,</l>
               <l>Yet (Mighty Sir) the Poets are your own,</l>
               <l>Their Lives and Pens (for Fortunes they have none)</l>
               <l>Reaſon, and Wit are faithful to their Prince,</l>
               <l>Nay he that Writes againſt you can't Write Senſe,</l>
               <l>The Sacred <hi>Nine</hi> Elected you Supreme,</l>
               <l>And Swore Allegiance to your Diadem;</l>
               <l>And all the Jobbers of the Rhiming Crew</l>
               <l>Are Rebels e'en to them when ſo to You.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th' Old Loyal Bloud when your kind Beams with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</l>
               <l>Unmurmuring Slept till they return'd anew;</l>
               <l>Then (like the Luſt of Plants) its Automs ſtrong</l>
               <l>To deck th' old Branches, &amp; to ſhoot forth young.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100279:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> was an Autumn to our Lays,</l>
               <l>But th' <hi>Oxford</hi> Nipping Spring had kill'd our Bays,</l>
               <l>Had not your Mercy and Diſſolving Skill</l>
               <l>Stopt both their Doing, and our Suffering Ill.</l>
               <l>Had we th' Heſperian Fruit, you ſhou'd not pull,</l>
               <l>We'd freely drop you a whole Checquer full,</l>
               <l>(But equal Heaven has given it to the Dull.)</l>
               <l>Wit by Camelion Nouriſhment conceives,</l>
               <l>And was Decreed only to put forth Leaves.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hail (Sacred Sir) altho we have no Banks</l>
               <l>Yet we can pay (what none can give You) thanks</l>
               <l>Thanks for the Numerous Bleſſings which you ſhed</l>
               <l>Like the Impartial Sun on every Head.</l>
               <l>Thanks for the Factious Deluge you put by,</l>
               <l>And thanks for th' humble ſtoop to tell us why</l>
               <l>But thanks above all thinking for your Care</l>
               <l>To ſtop that Tap which wou'd have drown'd your Heir</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Illuſtrious <hi>James</hi> thou cou'dſt not bear ſuch thing</l>
               <l>Wert thou not Son and Brother to ſuch Kings;</l>
               <l>How cou'd we think from Juſtice thou ſhou'dſt fly</l>
               <l>A Land which does it to their King deny?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sh'riffs of late ſuch Naturaliſts are grown</l>
               <l>They'l turn no ſtreams back to the Fountain, Throne</l>
               <l>And thoſe grand Jews that <hi>Ignoramus</hi> bring</l>
               <l>For <hi>Barabbas</hi> wou'd Crucifie their King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100279:6"/>
               <l>The <hi>Poliſh</hi> Prince is Charm'd, he ſcorns weak Buff,</l>
               <l>His Conſcience of Impenitrable ſtuff</l>
               <l>Arms the ſmall Patriot, Plot, and Witneſs Proof;</l>
               <l>'Tis ſuch a Knot as wants the <hi>Gordian</hi> Knife,</l>
               <l>For ſome Conſpire his Death, and ſome his Life,</l>
               <l>And Nineteen Unbelievers Damn to Save</l>
               <l>That Head ſo lately Deſtin'd to a Grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once more Hail Sacred Monarch, may kind Stars</l>
               <l>Proſper your Peace, and Guard you in your Wars.</l>
               <l>Let God ariſe, who your Avenger is,</l>
               <l>And Scatter both Your Enemies and His;</l>
               <l>May Heav'n attend your Councils and Diſpoſe</l>
               <l>Succeſs to all that's Yours except your Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long may you Rule this Iſland with your Nod,</l>
               <l>And let the ſtubborn feel your angry Rod,</l>
               <l>Exceed your Father, and be like Your God.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100279:7"/>
            <head>The Excellency of MONARCHY. <hi>A Panegyrick,</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>IF wanting wings one may aſcend the Skys,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phaebus</hi> view without an Eagles Eyes,</l>
               <l>Then rouſe up, (Muſe) from thy Lethargick ſtrains.</l>
               <l>And having firſt invok'd the God of brains,</l>
               <l>Let the grand Subject of thy Meaſures be,</l>
               <l>No rule to <hi>England</hi> like a Monarchy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>It is the Image of that Domination,</l>
               <l>By which <hi>Jehova</hi> rules the whole Creation,</l>
               <l>Angels nor Saints do in his Kingdom ſhare,</l>
               <l>God is ſole Monarch, they but Subjects are,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Laws are ſuch as when they did Rebell,</l>
               <l>Sequeſter'd not, but ſent 'em ſtraight to Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>As old as that paternal Soveraignty,</l>
               <l>God plac'd in <hi>Adam,</hi> Rul'd his People by,</l>
               <l>Diſown'd by none, but them whoſe minds aſpire,</l>
               <l>And Envy One ſhou'd have what All deſire,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100279:7"/>
               <l>For be't a Few or Many we live under,</l>
               <l>Such ſhall Repine, ſtill whilſt not of the Number.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>The Ancients did a Monarchy prefer,</l>
               <l>Made all their Gods Submit to <hi>Jvpiter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And (where Affairs, and Nations firſt began)</l>
               <l>Princes Decrees were th' only Laws of Man.</l>
               <l>Experience will avow it where ther's Any,</l>
               <l>One Honeſt Man is ſooner found then Many.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>The Rational Soul performs a Princes Part,</l>
               <l>She rules the Body by Monarchick Art,</l>
               <l>Poor Cranes and little Bees with ſhivering Wings,</l>
               <l>Obſerve their Leaders and obey their Kings.</l>
               <l>Nature her ſelf diſdains a crowded Throne,</l>
               <l>The Body's Monſtrous, has more Heads then One.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>A Monarchy's that Politick ſimple State,</l>
               <l>Conſiſts in Unity (Inſeprate,</l>
               <l>Pure and Intire) A Government that ſtands,</l>
               <l>When others fall, touch'd but with Levelling hands.</l>
               <l>So natural and with ſuch skill Endu'd,</l>
               <l>It makes one Body of a Multitude.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>In order wherein later things Depend,</l>
               <l>On former, that's moſt perfect doth Attend</l>
               <l>On Unity: But this can never be,</l>
               <l>The Pop'lar ſtate nor <hi>Ariſtocraſy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For where, or All, or Many bear the ſway,</l>
               <l>Such Order to Confuſion leads the Way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100279:8"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>A Monarchy more quickly doth attain</l>
               <l>The end propoſ'd, for tis the ſingle Brain</l>
               <l>That ripens Councel, and Concealeth beſt</l>
               <l>Princely deſigns, 'tis deeds proclaim em bleſt.</l>
               <l>Whilſt numerous Heads are rarely of one Mind,</l>
               <l>Slow in their Motion, louder then the Wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>Treaſon nor Fear ſo ſuddenly divides</l>
               <l>Th' united ſtrength that in a Crown reſides:</l>
               <l>Sedition proſpers not, it ſeldom here,</l>
               <l>Reſults the Object of a Prince's fear.</l>
               <l>Then when an Empire <hi>Rome</hi> was nere ſo ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Nor Triumph'd under other Rule ſo long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>A Monarchy abates thoſe Feveriſh fits,</l>
               <l>Of Emulation, a free ſtate begets;</l>
               <l>A Prince cannot his Reins ſo quickly ſlack,</l>
               <l>Or throw his burthen on anothers back:</l>
               <l>But where ſo many Rulers have Command,</l>
               <l>The works Transfer'd, and toſt from Hand to Hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>The People or the Nobles to Debate</l>
               <l>The deep Concernments of a troubled ſtate,</l>
               <l>Set Times and Places have aſſign'd them, they</l>
               <l>Firſt Meet, and then Adjourn from Day to Day.</l>
               <l>Whereas a Monarch who by Natures one,</l>
               <l>Deliberat's allways, never's off his Throne.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100279:8"/>
            <head>On His <hi>Majeſties Recovery</hi> AT WINDSOR.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>THanks High and Mighty one by whom Kings Reign,</l>
               <l>We now return unto our ſelves again,</l>
               <l>The Head affected cou'd the Members all</l>
               <l>Lye otherwiſe then Apoplectical?</l>
               <l>So when a Spring Head has not paſſage clear,</l>
               <l>The Brooks ſubſide, and Gaſping Fiſh appear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>WINDSOR</hi> whoſe lofty Top Mounts to the Sky,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>WINDSOR</hi> that Writers do ſo Magnifie?</l>
               <l>How had thy name ſneak'd under ground and fail'd</l>
               <l>Had the Blood-thirſty-Traytor PLOT prevail'd?</l>
               <l>Or had ſo good a Prince by Nature dy'd,</l>
               <l>Nature and Thou (as guilty) had been Try'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>In thee too long for ſhame without a Tomb.</l>
               <l>The beſt of Kings lay after Martyrdom,</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100279:9"/>
               <l>Regardleſly full Thirty Years were ſpent,</l>
               <l>'Twas well his Vertues ſtood his Monument,</l>
               <l>Whence let Contrivers do well or amiſs,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>MO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SOL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> never had the like to His.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>His Sacred Urn diſturb'd who cou'd have heard,</l>
               <l>Without Convulſive Fits what good Men fear'd?</l>
               <l>The Perfume of whoſe Aſhes clear'd the Air,</l>
               <l>More then <hi>Arabian</hi> Spices cou'd by far,</l>
               <l>So that the Paroxiſm had Remedy,</l>
               <l>Not from dull Phiſick, but by Sympathy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Ask the Phyſician what an Ague means,</l>
               <l>He'l talk of Ebollition in the Veins,</l>
               <l>Ferment and Circulation ſtopt, and Chat,</l>
               <l>What Baker knows, and Brewer from his Fat,</l>
               <l>Take him aſide and ſmile him in the Face,</l>
               <l>Indeed quoth he, an Agu's our Diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>And ſo it had been with a Witneſs ſure,</l>
               <l>Had Providence not found a Soveraign Cure,</l>
               <l>That Providence that ſlumbers not nor ſleeps,</l>
               <l>But his Anoynted ſtill in Safety keeps,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafeing Combinations to Reveal,</l>
               <l>When the Foundation's laid as deep as Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>Whether the Breathing of a Vain gave eaſe,</l>
               <l>And did the Preternatural Heat appeaſe,</l>
               <l>In Royal Blood (whoſe Spirits are ſo fine,</l>
               <l>They of themſelves might to give eaſe incline)</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100279:9"/>
               <l>We argue not, but I dare promiſe it,</l>
               <l>'Twas not the Jeſuits Powder checkd the fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>Summon Apothecaries, let them tell</l>
               <l>How oft our Oaken Bark for it they ſell,</l>
               <l>And this as well as that has prov'd a ſpell.</l>
               <l>Sacred to <hi>Jove,</hi> how cou'd her Boughs do leſs,</l>
               <l>Then yield a MONARCH ſhelter in diſtreſs?</l>
               <l>For which the Powers above we ever bleſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>There lyes our Fort, our Rock of firm Defence,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt Forreign and Domeſtick Violence,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſignal Demonſtrations have been given,</l>
               <l>Of Preſervation (Maugre ſpite) from Heaven,</l>
               <l>Prove <hi>CHARLES</hi> on Earth Immortal whoſe Remove</l>
               <l>May it be late, then let him Reign above.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>(Welcome Great Sir) to your Majeſtick Seat,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Whitehall</hi> Royal and your Chair of State,</l>
               <l>From whence let <hi>Tamaſis</hi> the Tydings ſend,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Tyber</hi> that our Tears are at an End,</l>
               <l>Then let the Conſiſtory meet again,</l>
               <l>Fret, and lay Cap aſide to cool the Brain.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100279:10"/>
            <head>THE SUCCESSION.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE precious Gem call'd Loyalty grows ſcarce,</l>
               <l>The Saints pretending, turns it into Farce,</l>
               <l>Whilſt <hi>Englands</hi> great Prerogative does grow</l>
               <l>Into Contempt by the Tumultuous Foe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſubtile ſecret Hypocritick gins,</l>
               <l>Wou'd turn the Frame of Nature off its pins</l>
               <l>A Painted Zeal muſt back what they Decree,</l>
               <l>And while the Cheat pretends to Loyalty,</l>
               <l>Heaven muſt be mock'd t' uphold their Treachery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bluſh then Diſloyal Mortals, let your ſhame</l>
               <l>All wild Attempts againſt your Reaſon Tame,</l>
               <l>Nor think your ſelves who are but Subjects, Kings,</l>
               <l>You know Religion teaches better things,</l>
               <l>Late reeling times ſufficiently have ſhown</l>
               <l>The Effects of Maſquerade Religion,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Charles</hi> the Great whoſe Memory ſhall Live,</l>
               <l>Cou'd not their Loyal Principles Survive,</l>
               <l>And thoſe who dare oppoſe Succeſſion</l>
               <l>Wou'd play the ſame Game over with the Son,</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100279:10"/>
               <l>This Speaks your truſt, the VVounds continue green</l>
               <l>Since that Bleſt Martyr was the Bloudy Scene</l>
               <l>Of their Impieties; This Land was wrack'd,</l>
               <l>Its Bowels Torn, Natures chief Fabrick Crack'd,</l>
               <l>Into Confuſion hurld, till in the End</l>
               <l>(As each thing does unto its Center tend,)</l>
               <l>The Clouds diſpers'd, and drove away Deſpair</l>
               <l>VVhen in the Throne appear'd the much wrong'd Heir</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhom Heaven preſerve, and may he ever be</l>
               <l>Secure from all pretending Loyalty,</l>
               <l>Princes are Gods Anoynted and the Crown,</l>
               <l>None can detain but Heavens great Prince alone,</l>
               <l>When Natures Law hath been Impeach'd ſuch things</l>
               <l>Are wrought by Pow'r Divine, the King of Kings,</l>
               <l>By that great Pow'r they Rule, and by no leſs,</l>
               <l>And he who only rais'd them can depreſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All Officers whether of Sword or Gown</l>
               <l>Are ſworn t'uphold the Rights of <hi>Englands</hi> Crown</l>
               <l>The Commons too before they Voice can claim</l>
               <l>Are duly Sworn ith' Houſe to Right the ſame,</l>
               <l>How can we Judg of this but as a Plot</l>
               <l>When ſuch a Solemn Oath can be forgot?</l>
               <l>It's a high Crime to let a Papiſt Reign,</l>
               <l>But Perjury wee'l Piouſly maintain,</l>
               <l>For a great Vertue when ſelf-intereſt</l>
               <l>In Whiſpers tells us all goes for the Beſt,</l>
               <l>That Monſter Faction evermore did range</l>
               <l>In theſe three Kingdoms to promote a Change,</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100279:11"/>
               <l>Which being upheld by Frenzy, Pride and Scorn,</l>
               <l>Of Monarcy, 'tis that's the wounding Thorn,</l>
               <l>To publick Peace, and makes the greateſt Scars</l>
               <l>That fills Mens Mouths with Armys, Bloud and Wars,</l>
               <l>'Tis that Depoſes Princes, blackens Fame</l>
               <l>Whitens the <hi>Negro,</hi> makes the ſound Man Lame,</l>
               <l>A Prince oth' the Bloud is a Regardleſs thing</l>
               <l>And if we durſt wee'd tell you ſo's a KING,</l>
               <l>Vertues bright Luſtre can't her ſelf protect</l>
               <l>From baſe Ingratitude and Diſreſpect,</l>
               <l>It once hath been admir'd in that great Prince</l>
               <l>And ſtill may't be his Glorious Defence,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Tongue of everyſenſeleſs Brute</l>
               <l>That dare Succeſſion to the Crown Diſpute.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100279:11"/>
            <head>A PARADOX <hi>Againſt Liberty,</hi> Written by the Lords, during their Impriſonment in the Tower.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Priſon, or the Iſle, are much the ſame;</l>
               <l>They onely differ in Conceit and Name.</l>
               <l>As Art the firſt, Nature Immures the laſt;</l>
               <l>Onely i'th' larger Mold her Figure's caſt.</l>
               <l>All Iſlanders are in a Priſon pent,</l>
               <l>And none at large, not thoſe o'th' Continent.</l>
               <l>Each Mariner's a Priſoner in his Bark.</l>
               <l>The living World was priſon'd in the Ark.</l>
               <l>And though it be abroad adays; the Light</l>
               <l>Still lodges in the Priſon of black Night.</l>
               <l>The Sea it ſelf, is to its bounds confin'd,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Aeolus</hi> in Caves ſhuts up the wind:</l>
               <l>Nothing in nature has ſuch vaſt Extent,</l>
               <l>But is impriſon'd in its Element.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100279:12"/>
               <l>The Fiſh in watry Dungeons are inclos'd;</l>
               <l>Men, Beaſts, and Birds, to Earth and Ayr diſpos'd.</l>
               <l>If to enlarge their narrow bounds, they ſtrive,</l>
               <l>The fatal freedom rarely they ſurvive.</l>
               <l>And as with them, we hope with Us 'twill be,</l>
               <l>When from their Priſons took, Death ſets them free,</l>
               <l>Man can no more a native freedome boaſt;</l>
               <l>That Jewel ne're was found, ſince firſt 'twas loſt.</l>
               <l>'Twas then tranſported to the <hi>Stygian</hi> Coaſt.</l>
               <l>But ſtill there's ſomething which we do eſteem,</l>
               <l>Onely becauſe 'tis like the poliſht Gem,</l>
               <l>And this we Feedome call; its credit grows</l>
               <l>From a falſe ſtamp, the guilded outſide ſhows:</l>
               <l>Which avaritious Man attempts to get,</l>
               <l>Cheated and ruin'd with the Counterfeit.</l>
               <l>Like Children, Soapy-Bubbles they purſue,</l>
               <l>And the ſantaſtick Viſion, take for true;</l>
               <l>But whilſt they think bright forms they do enmbrace</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixion</hi>-like, they find a cloud i'th' place.</l>
               <l>Conſent of Crowds, exceeding credit brings,</l>
               <l>And ſeems to ſlamp Truths Image on falſe thing</l>
               <l>Not what's a real good, but what does ſeem,</l>
               <l>Still ſhares the blind and popular eſteem.</l>
               <l>Whilſt Senſe and ſancy over-rule their choice,</l>
               <l>And Reaſon in th' Election has no voice.</l>
               <l>But Souls in vain have Reaſons Attribute,</l>
               <l>If to the Rule, they cannot Senſe ſubmit.</l>
               <l>Hence the Heriock mind make; no complaint,</l>
               <l>But freedom does Enjoy, even in reſtraint.</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100279:12"/>
               <l>When Chains and Fetters do his Body bind,</l>
               <l>He then appears more free, and leſs confin'd.</l>
               <l>Diſcord and Care, which do diſtract him here,</l>
               <l>In durance take their leave and come not there.</l>
               <l>Falfe Friends and Flatt'rers, then, take laſt adieu,</l>
               <l>Who often ſwore how faithful and how true,</l>
               <l>Things their diſhoneſt boſoms never knew.</l>
               <l>Theſe, like the Swallows, in cold weather flye;</l>
               <l>A Summers fortune onely draws them nigh.</l>
               <l>Elatt'rers a ſort of fatal Suckers be,</l>
               <l>Which draw the Sap 'till they deſtroy the Tree.</l>
               <l>Fair Vertue to their Obticks when they bring,</l>
               <l>Seems a deform'd and antiquated thing.</l>
               <l>Vice they commend, whilſt Vertue is deſpis'd;</l>
               <l>The blackeſt by theſe Negroes moſt are pris'd.</l>
               <l>Theſe ſlaves to Vice, do hug ſo hard and long,</l>
               <l>Till like the o'refond Ape, they kill their Young.</l>
               <l>Ambition in the Mind's a Feveriſh Thirſt,</l>
               <l>Which is by drinking dryer than at Firſt;</l>
               <l>And theſe will feed the humour till it burſt.</l>
               <l>When Paraſites the Arbiters are made,</l>
               <l>They'l place the Garland on a Beadlam's head.</l>
               <l>Riot, Exces, and Pleaſure car' the Day,</l>
               <l>And Luſt (the worſt of Tyrants) bears the ſway,</l>
               <l>At whoſe black Throne they blind Allegiance pay.</l>
               <l>Moroſe and dull they do account the Grave;</l>
               <l>And the Meek-man, fit only for a Slave:</l>
               <l>The Humble of a Nature poor and baſe;</l>
               <l>The Chaſt, ſprung from a dull inſipid Race;</l>
               <l>And Temperance, a Gallant's cheif diſgrace.</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100279:13"/>
               <l>In Vertues garb, the great Mans Vice they dreſs,</l>
               <l>Giving it Names which ſound of Worthineſs.</l>
               <l>They call his Pride the Grandeur of his mind,</l>
               <l>And for his luſt the Name they have deſign'd</l>
               <l>Is a complaiſant Ayr, that makes men kind.</l>
               <l>Profaneneſs is his Wit; and his Exceſs</l>
               <l>By a Gay janty Humour they expreſs;</l>
               <l>All his Debauches too muſt be no leſs.</l>
               <l>Thus they lap ruin up, and guild our Crimes;</l>
               <l>But Vice deſtroys, like <hi>Ivy,</hi> where it climbs.</l>
               <l>In us the dangrous ſtate th' Ambitious ſee</l>
               <l>Of Greatneſs, Avarice, and Flatterie.</l>
               <l>Gifts, Honour, Office, Greatneſs, Grace of Kings,</l>
               <l>Raiſe the Ambitious upon treach'rous wings.</l>
               <l>Till from the mighty heights they giddy grow,</l>
               <l>And fall into the Ruin lyes below.</l>
               <l>If the firſt fail, which do ſupport our ſtate,</l>
               <l>The laſt our Fall ſerve to percipitate.</l>
               <l>This with too dear Experience we have bought,</l>
               <l>And learnt a Leſſon, which too late was taught.</l>
               <l>Proſperity's a Drug, that muſt be ta'ne</l>
               <l>Corrected, (<hi>Opium</hi> like) or elſe 'tis bane.</l>
               <l>A more <hi>Lethargick</hi> quality's in her,</l>
               <l>Than ever yet in <hi>Opium</hi> did appear.</l>
               <l>her fatal Poyſon to the Mind ſhe ſends,</l>
               <l>And uncorrect, in ſure deſtruction ends.</l>
               <l>Whilſt in the way her guilded ſnares ſhe lays,</l>
               <l>Eaſie and credulous Man ſhe ſoon betrays;</l>
               <l>Who ſees her Roſes and her Lilies here,</l>
               <l>But her concealed Snakes doth never fear.</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100279:13"/>
               <l>Proſperity's repaſts puff up the Mind</l>
               <l>With unſubſtantial and unwholeſome wind.</l>
               <l>'Tis a <hi>Hault-Gouſt</hi> which <hi>Epicures</hi> do uſe,</l>
               <l>And choicer Viands ſqueamiſhly refuſe.</l>
               <l>But when Affliction moulds your dayly bread,</l>
               <l>'Tis then the ſtaff of Life with which ſhe's fed.</l>
               <l>Affliction (like the river <hi>Nile</hi>) beſtows</l>
               <l>Her fruitful bleſſings whereſoe'er ſhe flows:</l>
               <l>And if when ſhe withdraws, ſtrange Serpents riſe,</l>
               <l>Not in her ſtreams, but in the Soyl, it lyes.</l>
               <l>Which (like the great <hi>Apollo</hi>) ſhe ſtrikes dead,</l>
               <l>By the ſame Influence they firſt were bred,</l>
               <l>If ſhe return, and ſhew her hidden head.</l>
               <l>Great Minds (like the victorious palms) are wont</l>
               <l>Under the Weights of Fortune more to mount.</l>
               <l>Strongly ſuppreſt, and hurl'd upon the ground,</l>
               <l>Fill'd with ſublimer thoughts they more rebound.</l>
               <l>Still careleſs whether Fortune ſmile or frown,</l>
               <l>Whether ſhe give, or take away a Crown.</l>
               <l>Our Walls are Tyded, and by that we know</l>
               <l>She always ebbs, when ſhe doth leave to flow,</l>
               <l>And conſtant in Inconſtancy does grow.</l>
               <l>Make an attacque all Injuries that can,</l>
               <l>They fall like Waves beneath a riſing Swan.</l>
               <l>Freed and ſecur'd from all diſcordant Care,</l>
               <l>Here we our heads above the billows bear,</l>
               <l>Till from our ſhoulders they tranſplanted are.</l>
               <l>And from their ſummits, with dum gapes proclaim,</l>
               <l>Of a Quincumvirat the trait'rous ſhame,</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100279:14"/>
               <l>But during all this Storm, we ſtill do find</l>
               <l>An Anchor and a Haven in our Mind,</l>
               <l>Not beaten now, though then expos'd to th' Wind.</l>
               <l>As Nightingals, our boſom we expoſe,</l>
               <l>And ſing, environ'd with the ſharpeſt woes.</l>
               <l>Degraded from vain Honour, here we grow</l>
               <l>More great and high, as Trees by lopping do.</l>
               <l>Honour's like froth in each Man's glaſs of Beer;</l>
               <l>'Tis leaſt of uſe, though topmoſt it appear.</l>
               <l>The common Vouchee for ill acts ſhe's grown;</l>
               <l>It and Religion all our Miſchifs own.</l>
               <l>She raigns in Youth with an unruly heat,</l>
               <l>And in her falſer Mirror ſhews them Great,</l>
               <l>Till Age and Time convince them of the Cheat.</l>
               <l>Raſh heads approve what ſober Men deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>And the fantaſtict Garb offends the Wiſe;</l>
               <l>She rarely now is ſeen, but in Diguiſe.</l>
               <l>True Honour and plain Honeſty's the ſame;</l>
               <l>From various Dwellings, comes the various Name:</l>
               <l>For whilſt ſhe gay in Courts, ſhe's Honour there,</l>
               <l>But Honeſty with us in Durance here.</l>
               <l>In differing States, moſt things have difference:</l>
               <l>What pleas'd this day, the next offends the Prince.</l>
               <l>The Proſperous loath what the Afflicted love;</l>
               <l>Priſoners abhor, what free, they did approve.</l>
               <l>And ſtill there's power in each Man choice, to make</l>
               <l>Himſelf content, if he can wiſely take,</l>
               <l>And think his own (though hard) a happy Stake.</l>
               <l>In ev'ry ſtate does ſome Contentment dwell,</l>
               <l>And here we ſind a Palace in a Cell.</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100279:14"/>
               <l>Good is good ev'ry where, and ev'ry thing,</l>
               <l>And good can of it ſelf no Evil bring.</l>
               <l>All good's a raye of the firſt Light alone;</l>
               <l>When Ill approaches, only that's our own.</l>
               <l>Vertue's not gain'd by ſpending of our days</l>
               <l>In pleaſure, Princes Courts, or from their Rays.</l>
               <l>At Vertue's Coaſt by Travel we arrive,</l>
               <l>And ſo by Travel Vertue's kept alive.</l>
               <l>She dwindles if ſhe want due Exerciſe;</l>
               <l>But us'd, grows brighter, and ſtill multiplies.</l>
               <l>Vertue increaſes, Snow-ball-like, rowl'd on:</l>
               <l>A lazy Vertue's next of kin to None.</l>
               <l>Pris'ners indeed they be, that do lay by</l>
               <l>At once their Fredom and their Induſtry.</l>
               <l>If Men turn Drones within theſe hony'd Hyves,</l>
               <l>It lyes i'th' Pris'ner's heart, and not his Gyves.</l>
               <l>The good grows better here, the bad grows worſe;</l>
               <l>The Spur that makes this go, does jade that Horſe.</l>
               <l>Hence the great'ſt part are male-content and ſad,</l>
               <l>Since that the Good are fewer than the bad.</l>
               <l>A Bliſs that ſprings from penetential joy,</l>
               <l>Is the Minds balſome in each ſharp Annoy;</l>
               <l>Fools only their own Comforts do deſtroy.</l>
               <l>To this Retrement we can freely go;</l>
               <l>'Tis the great'ſt pace of Majeſty below:</l>
               <l>Or ſtirring out imports the World to know.</l>
               <l>The Goaler's Centinel to guard our Doors,</l>
               <l>And Caſtles are contain'd i'th' narrow Floors.</l>
               <l>More happy and more ſafe, ſecur'd from Foes,</l>
               <l>Than thoſe whom Troops of Enemies encloſe.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100279:15"/>
               <l>Much more as Priſ'ners, our high bliſs we boaſt,</l>
               <l>Being ſecur'd from ſuch a mighty Hoaſt</l>
               <l>Gf deadly Foes, ſo fierce with wrath and might,</l>
               <l>Our ſelves ſo feeble, and unfit to fight</l>
               <l>'Gainſt the black band of vicious and Profane,</l>
               <l>Who Thouſands do undo in each Campain.</l>
               <l>In the Aſſault, we ſeldome brook the Field.</l>
               <l>But flye like Hares, or elſe like Cowards yield.</l>
               <l>Yet this the World eſteems an hard eſtate,</l>
               <l>And Us, who feel it, count unfortunate.</l>
               <l>Shew then, Philoſophy! the ſtate wherein</l>
               <l>Such Safety, and ſo much Content is ſeen.</l>
               <l>Wherein leſs rugged or ſteep hind'rance lyes,</l>
               <l>T'obſtruct the Path unto Perfection's prize.</l>
               <l>The uſeful Rod's only bound up for this,</l>
               <l>To whip and laſh the Childiſh on to Bliſs;</l>
               <l>Who ſullenly refuſe the Rod to kiſs,</l>
               <l>And ſo the Bleſſing in the Whipping miſs.</l>
               <l>Some, like the Whale, only deſign'd to play</l>
               <l>In fruteleſs pleaſures, drive the flying day;</l>
               <l>As Boys with Clackers drive the Lent away.</l>
               <l>Whilſt here, we ſtop the hours of time, that flyes,</l>
               <l>With Contemplation's nobler Exerciſe.</l>
               <l>Maurge all Goals, think we e're long muſt dye,</l>
               <l>And then enjoy an endleſs Liberty;</l>
               <l>Death will redeem from long Captivity.</l>
               <l>Man's Life's a Piece ſpun of a various Thred;</l>
               <l>In ſome 'tis fine, in ſome a courſer Web.</l>
               <l>The Threads acroſs, th' Occurrences of Fate,</l>
               <l>Cut early from the Loom by Death or late.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100279:15"/>
               <l>The Dread of Kings, Death, does not us diſmay;</l>
               <l>To Dye's leſs than be Tantalis'd each day.</l>
               <l>What Man complains, with Wearineſs oppreſt,</l>
               <l>That Night is come, the only Time to Reſt?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The laſt SPEECH OF Sr. <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi>'s Ghoſt.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LOok up? Baſe Croaking Zealots of the Age,</l>
               <l>Before your Frenzy Wits, fall into rage;</l>
               <l>Look here? Who Vindicates the Royal Stage.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s brave Spirit, doth this day appear,</l>
               <l>Tremble ye now for Anger, or for Fear.</l>
               <l>His worthy Ghoſt, that courted Sacred good,</l>
               <l>Has paſt the dangers, of the <hi>Stygian Flood;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Left the <hi>Elizian Shades,</hi> by ſtrict commands,</l>
               <l>To ſee once more how this poor Cuntrey ſtands.</l>
               <l>But to our ſhame his grived Soul doth find,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Lunatick Zeal)</hi> with us hath Been too kind,</l>
               <l>And ſtruck his Loving Fellow Subjects Blind.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100279:16"/>
               <l>He fears our Diſobedience to a Prince,</l>
               <l>Whom Heaven protected, (he can the World con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</l>
               <l>From Zealous Rage; and Traytors hands long ſince.</l>
               <l>He ſees and fears, that in-bread Wars are coming,</l>
               <l>By Zealous Prayer created, Preach'd by cunning,</l>
               <l>Holy Long-winded, Fervent, Piows, Men</l>
               <l>Who ſeem as innocent as the prety <hi>Wren;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But if well tryd, we eaſily may find,</l>
               <l>They unto none, but to themſelves are kind;</l>
               <l>Envy all happineſs, but what's their own,</l>
               <l>Have humble outſides, inwardly o're-grown,</l>
               <l>With Pride, Ambition, snd Self-Intereſt;</l>
               <l>Longing with Crounes themſelves for to Inveſt,</l>
               <l>For what is <hi>Monarchy</hi> to them that ſay,</l>
               <l>They are all <hi>Monarch's,</hi> that Zealoufly can Pray</l>
               <l>He ſees foul threatnings, and inteſtine Thunder,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Plagues</hi> of Eating Swords, <hi>Domeſtick Plunder</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Foretels the Fathers ſtriking of his Suns,</l>
               <l>Who without Mercy, on their <hi>Old Sire</hi> runs;</l>
               <l>Sees the Sons baſe Revenge upon the Father,</l>
               <l>Who never leave, till all lye dead together;</l>
               <l>Friend killing Friend, a Brother Fights a Brother</l>
               <l>And ſpares his own Blood leſs then any other.</l>
               <l>A wake, a wake, I ſay awake be times,</l>
               <l>Before your Sovls, feed on ſuch Helliſh Crimes;</l>
               <l>Let your own reaſon, cleat your blinded Eyes,</l>
               <l>Let ſad experience, baniſh ſuch Tragedies;</l>
               <l>And as you older are, ſtill grow more wiſe.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100279:16"/>
               <l>Beware thoſe <hi>Monſters,</hi> that have taught your Zeals,</l>
               <l>Firſt to Bethrone your Prince (whom God an heals,)</l>
               <l>Then brings Deſtruction, to your Publick Weals,</l>
               <l>For doubtleſs ſuch baſe Principles as theſe,</l>
               <l>Cannot, but muſt the Heavenly Power Diſpleaſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s fore-grived-Ghoſt, weeps Bloody Tears,</l>
               <l>Seeing you drawn by jealoufies and Fears,</l>
               <l>To act thoſe things, which Murdring ſorrow bears.</l>
               <l>Is it ſo longe ſince, that you have forgot,</l>
               <l>Can you ſo ſoon waſh out that Royal Spots,</l>
               <l>Of Sacred Innocent Blood, bring back to mind,</l>
               <l>Murdring the <hi>Sire,</hi> then to the Son be kind,</l>
               <l>And ſay again your Zeal had made you blind.</l>
               <l>Let not <hi>Religions Cloak,</hi> your Bodies cover,</l>
               <l>And under That Both Prince and Countrey Smo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</l>
               <l>To make your ſelves, more hateful, and leſs good</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his <hi>Rebelliovs. Brood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You as a parelel to them I bring,</l>
               <l>Both ſtriving (with this Difference in the thing,)</l>
               <l>They 'gain their Heavenly—,</l>
               <l>But you, both 'gainſt, your Heaven and Earthly King.</l>
               <l>But yet a King ſo good. ſo ſweet, ſo great.</l>
               <l>Makes all your joys and happineſs Compleat.</l>
               <l>Them onely are excepted, that you ſee</l>
               <l>Fain would be <hi>Monarch</hi>'s, Kings as well as He.</l>
               <l>Let not your Loving <hi>Godfrey</hi> longer weep,</l>
               <l>But let his weary Ghoſt retire to ſleep;</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100279:17"/>
               <l>Who never can have reſt, unleſs he find,</l>
               <l>Your ſouls more Loyal to your Prince more kind;</l>
               <l>Endeavouring ſtill to immitate thoſe Quires,</l>
               <l>That with their Harps, and Hearts, and Sacred Lyres,</l>
               <l>Sing to their Heavenly King, who can alone,</l>
               <l>Set whom he Pleaſes on an Earthly Throne.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>ON THE DEATH Of the <hi>Proteſtant Joyner.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>BRave <hi>Colledg</hi> is Hang'd, the Chief of our hopes,</l>
               <l>For pulling down Biſhops and making New Popes,</l>
               <l>Our dear Brother Property crawls on the Ground,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Poland,</hi> K— <hi>Anthony</hi> ne're will be Crown'd:</l>
               <l>For now they'r reſolv'd, that <hi>Harts</hi> ſhall be Trump,</l>
               <l>And the Prentiſes Swear, they will Burn the Old Rump.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100279:17"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Brave <hi>Colledge,</hi> both Champion and Carver of Laws,</l>
               <l>Who dyed undaunted, and ſtuck to the Cauſe;</l>
               <l>What miſchief might thou to the Godly have done</l>
               <l>Had thy dareing Soul, dreaded the World to come?</l>
               <l>And all thy dear Party to danger expos'd.</l>
               <l>If thou to the World, had thy ſecrets diſclos'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>But now thou art Hang'd, and that fear is paſt,</l>
               <l>Were all that's in queſtion as ſafe in the Neſt,</l>
               <l>Then we ſome new means, might conſult or contrive,</l>
               <l>To drive on our purpoſe, to proſper or thrive:</l>
               <l>But the Popiſh PLOT, has now quite loſt i'ts Name,</l>
               <l>And none thy bright Blunderbuſh dare to maintain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>What K—but Great <hi>Colledge,</hi> could er'e make a Pope</l>
               <l>Tho' he was or'e rul'd by the end of the Rope?</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Colledge,</hi> was certainly <hi>Jure Divino,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When the Tripple Crown, on the Popes Heap did <hi>Shino.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He burnt him to aſhes, for paſtime like <hi>Nero</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then ſtraight made a new one, ſuch Power had our <hi>Here.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Colledge,</hi> muſt certainly dye a good Martyr,</l>
               <l>Being Knight of the Halter, and above the Garter;</l>
               <l>Our dear Brother States-man, tho' bred in a Saw-pit,</l>
               <l>Had Internal <hi>Genious,</hi> enough to or ethrow Wit:</l>
               <l>He fram'd a new Moddle, to limit the K—,</l>
               <l>In hopes Crown and Scepter, might truckle to him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100279:18"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Great, <hi>Brittain,</hi> ne're bred ſuch a Brother as <hi>Colledge,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He made Seven Popes, in his Time on our knowledg;</l>
               <l>Our Signals of Crimes, he put in the Popes Armes</l>
               <l>Which prudent Contrivance, our Function Alarms.</l>
               <l>With threats in Petition, Kings Power to reſtrain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet Towſer</hi> and <hi>Broomſtaff,</hi> rides Admiral again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Hanibals</hi> Conqueſt, nor <hi>Olivers</hi> Noſe,</l>
               <l>Could with ſuch ſmall Slaughter, ſubdue ſuch great Foes,</l>
               <l>As he in this three years, with the help of our Party,</l>
               <l>Hath check't our three Kingdoms and <hi>Magna Carta.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Head of our Church, and the Head of our Cauſe,</l>
               <l>He would have maintain'd them by Perjury and Blows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>He now may becall'd, a third Saviour oth' Nation,</l>
               <l>To ſave his dear Church he Renounced Salvation;</l>
               <l>Like Famous <hi>Cargile,</hi> he dy'd for King Jeſus,</l>
               <l>Defying Church Idols; enough to amaze us:</l>
               <l>He ty'd up together, both his and our Crimes,</l>
               <l>And dy'd like a Devil, to damp our Deſignes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>Our cauſe toth' Carrecter-men, we muſt refer</l>
               <l>To <hi>Shadwell,</hi> and <hi>Settle,</hi> to <hi>Curtis,</hi> and <hi>Carr.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To know who Succeeds, our Late Captain the Joyner,</l>
               <l>He muſt be an Artiſt, ſome Carver, or Coyner,</l>
               <l>To make our Solemnity, and ſome New Popes,</l>
               <l>On which our dependency, hangs and our hopes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100279:18"/>
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>But when the time comes, that the Pope muſt be burn'd</l>
               <l>Ifear we ſhall finde that the Tide is much turn'd?</l>
               <l>For the <hi>Tory</hi> Party, hath got ſo much ground,</l>
               <l>To Head a Rebellion there's none will be found;</l>
               <l>For now they'r Reſolved that <hi>Harts</hi> ſhall be Trump;</l>
               <l>And the Prentices Swear, they'l burn the Old Rump.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>Such a confuſed Monſter, they ſwear they'l Compoſe</l>
               <l>Of all the Diſſenters, that are the Kings Foes;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>Biter,</hi> the <hi>Pendant,</hi> and <hi>Quaker,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From which they will draw ſuch a prodigious Creature:</l>
               <l>More Diabolical Invective far,</l>
               <l>Then all Popes Solemnity's at <hi>Temple-Barr.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>Our Common-Councel lets Summon together,</l>
               <l>To Pannel pack't Jury's, Let's mak't our endeavour,</l>
               <l>For an <hi>Habeus Corpus,</hi> Inſiſts on our Power;</l>
               <l>To fetch our Great Patriots out of the <hi>Tower;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then we'le Diſpute the Caſe, for Reformation,</l>
               <l>And make the Provd <hi>Torys</hi> Reſign us the Nation.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100279:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>INNOCENCE UNVEIL'D:</hi> OR, A POEM On the Acquittal of the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>SCROGS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <lg>
               <l>IMperious <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and his <hi>Oaten</hi> Friend,</l>
               <l>Will now begin to buckle, or to bend:</l>
               <l>Now I do plainly ſee that they are Fools,</l>
               <l>They find it dang'rous meddling with Edge-Tools</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſtice</hi> is ſharp when 'tis too much abus'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſtice</hi> unjuſtly lately was accus'd:</l>
               <l>And now what follows, Scourges of the Law,</l>
               <l>To keep ſuch bold-fac'd Fellows all in awe.</l>
               <l>Your Innocence (unleſs I miſs my mark)</l>
               <l>Will make their Evidence look dull and dark.</l>
               <l>Had they but found you Guilty, I dare ſwing</l>
               <l>If they had let alone our Gracious King.</l>
               <l>Their Heads were very high, their Hearts too ſtout,</l>
               <l>Now give their Pride and Confidence a rout.</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100279:19"/>
               <l>The <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> is there All in All,</l>
               <l>And while they ſtand, the Coxcombs cannot fall.</l>
               <l>This is their ſtrong conceit; they do not fear:</l>
               <l>But ev'ry man that has an ear to hear,</l>
               <l>Shall ſhortly hear that they have ſpoil'd their ſport</l>
               <l>By nothing more, than by this falſe Report.</l>
               <l>Thoſe Scriblers <hi>Harris, Smith,</hi> and <hi>Care,</hi> will quake,</l>
               <l>For their Foundation doth begin to ſhake:</l>
               <l>The firſt and ſecond Saviour both look pale,</l>
               <l>To ſee their Gall and Malice doth ſo fall:</l>
               <l>The Rubbiſh is remov'd, Knaves muſt fly hence,</l>
               <l>For who can ſtand againſt our Innocence!</l>
               <l>The <hi>Chief</hi> in <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſhines in's proper place,</l>
               <l>Whilſt Envy lies obſcur'd with great diſgrace.</l>
               <l>Plot on, thou puny Levite, but beware</l>
               <l>(Both Thou, the Captain <hi>Harris, Smith,</hi> and <hi>Care,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of him you aim'd to catch within your Snare.</l>
               <l>His great Integrity is fully known,</l>
               <l>And well approv'd by him that wears the Crown;</l>
               <l>Is't a light thing to tread our <hi>Juſtice</hi> down?</l>
               <l>Might <hi>Juſtice</hi> once be trodden under feet,</l>
               <l>Then ev'ry Knave would ſtrive for <hi>CHARLES</hi> his Seat:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſtice</hi> is not ſo weak as you ſuppoſe;</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Smith</hi> may ſooner take the Devil by th' Noſe,</l>
               <l>Than think his Libels or your Oaths can taint</l>
               <l>That that's the Badge of every Earthly Saint.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Injuſtice</hi> is your Juſtice, I'me affraid,</l>
               <l>But yet by Juſtice you ſhall all be paid?</l>
               <l>You have had Rope enough too much I doubt,</l>
               <l>Indeed I wonder that your Necks are out.</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:100279:20"/>
               <l>You are not Hang'd, but choak'd up in your Throats,</l>
               <l>Now who'l believe the Rev'rend Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or the Heroick Captain? <hi>Commons</hi> may</l>
               <l>Not when they find your Truth is gone aſtray:</l>
               <l>My <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> Story will be told,</l>
               <l>And 'twill appear that you have been too bold,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> both at once you've ſold.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>ADVICE TO THE <hi>Painters Adviſer,</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WE <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Lions</hi> by their <hi>Voices</hi> know,</l>
               <l>For by their <hi>Notes</hi> themſelves all Creatures ſhow;</l>
               <l>Yet here's a <hi>Thing</hi> I know not what to call,</l>
               <l>He <hi>roars</hi> and <hi>Barks;</hi> what's <hi>Good</hi> he curſes all.</l>
               <l>No <hi>Monſter</hi> that e're yet from <hi>Africk</hi> came,</l>
               <l>But what would ſtart at thy prodigious <hi>Fame;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet we thy Name nor <hi>Pedigree</hi> can tell,</l>
               <l>Thou dar'ſt Blaſpheme beyond the Mouths of Hell.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I call thee, <hi>Monſter</hi> or <hi>baſe Fiend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That canſt daub <hi>Paper</hi> to ſo baſe an end?</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100279:20"/>
               <l>Unmouth that <hi>Tongue,</hi> maugre its double <hi>Pale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Fit <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to tell the <hi>Devils Tale</hi>)</l>
               <l>Which dar'd blaſpheme that <hi>Sacred Majeſty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The voice of <hi>Angels</hi> joy'd to Deifie.</l>
               <l>Foul Traitor, to beſpatter ſuch a King</l>
               <l>With th' Aſpiſh Poiſon of thy ſlandering,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ev'ry Action (if the Truth we ſcan)</l>
               <l>Speaks as much <hi>God,</hi> as his Foes find him <hi>Man?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Prince</hi> ſo tender of his <hi>Subjects</hi> Good,</l>
               <l>As would redeem the meaneſt with his <hi>Blood:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heavens Joy, Earths Pride;</hi> when After-age ſhall tell</l>
               <l>His Worth and Parts, 'twill want a Parrellel.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> their <hi>Heroes Punies</hi> call,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Charles the Great</hi> I'm ſure outdoes them all.</l>
               <l>Curſt <hi>Caitiff,</hi> thy <hi>ſharp Arrow, bitter word,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Gaul'd more than <hi>Europ</hi>'s many edged <hi>Sword.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ye <hi>Heavens</hi> look to't, he that attempts ſo high</l>
               <l>As <hi>Vice-God Charles,</hi> threats <hi>Gignatomachy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So he that ſtabb'd fam'd <hi>Millain</hi>'s Duke of yore,</l>
               <l>By Practice at his <hi>Picture</hi> did no more.</l>
               <l>But (Oh! the <hi>Devil</hi>) ſee the Serpent flies</l>
               <l>To his firſt courſe, he doubles his <hi>Advice</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To a poor <hi>Painter,</hi> to draw this and that,</l>
               <l>And <hi>draws himſelf</hi> into the Lord knows what.</l>
               <l>Even ſo thoſe <hi>Brats of ſin</hi> we bluſh to own,</l>
               <l>We bring to <hi>others doors,</hi> and lay them down.</l>
               <l>But <hi>(pox upon his Picture)</hi> to be ſhort,</l>
               <l>The wary <hi>White could</hi> have no <hi>colour</hi> for't;</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100279:21"/>
               <l>Elſe <hi>Hell</hi> had paid the Wages of th' abuſe,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Quidlibit audendi</hi>'s no excuſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kings failings</hi> (if th' are any) ought not lie</l>
               <l>An open <hi>Proſpect</hi> for the <hi>Vulgar Eye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He that drew <hi>Alexander</hi>'s ſcarry Face,</l>
               <l>Diſcreetly put his <hi>Finger</hi> on the place:</l>
               <l>But where's the <hi>Arteſt</hi> that can frame a Line,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Shadow</hi> or <hi>Eclipſe</hi> the <hi>Glorious Shine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of CHARLES'S <hi>Ray?</hi> what <hi>Eagle-eye</hi> can gaze</l>
               <l>On ſo much <hi>Sun,</hi> or fully ſuch a <hi>Blaze.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> i'th' <hi>Abſtract,</hi> whoſe each <hi>Glance</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Would ſtrike <hi>Preſumption</hi> out of Countenance;</l>
               <l>Much leſs can any draw his <hi>Treaſur'd Mind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To every Noble Virtuous <hi>Mood</hi> inclin'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nblemiſh'd</hi> as the <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> leſs clear</l>
               <l>In that firſt <hi>Shine</hi> which <hi>Summer'd</hi> all the <hi>Year:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our <hi>Painters</hi> well knew this, who e're read o're</l>
               <l>A <hi>Face</hi> more puzling <hi>Art,</hi> a <hi>Mind</hi> much more.</l>
               <l>Then, <hi>Devil do thy worſt,</hi> with thy <hi>Advice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> and his Court are 'bove thy <hi>Calumnies.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Dignities</hi> approach the Skies,</l>
               <l>Like Ships the more the Waves do under riſe.</l>
               <l>But 'tis not each <hi>Gods Fate</hi> alone, elſe why</l>
               <l>Do <hi>Miſcreants</hi> ſlight the <hi>Angels</hi> Miniſtry?</l>
               <l>Ours is but little lower, one remove,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vicegerent</hi> to the <hi>King of Kings</hi> above.</l>
               <l>The beſt are ſtill the moſt malign'd with wrong,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue</hi>'s no fence againſt a <hi>ſpiteful Tongue;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100279:21"/>
               <l>Is th' Object of his <hi>prophanation.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tho pure as new fall'n <hi>Snow,</hi> free from offence,</l>
               <l>As blameleſs Truth, and white as <hi>Innocence.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His breath blaſts thoſe, whoſe breath perfuming <hi>Air,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Makes all (ſave that) as ſweet as they are fair,</l>
               <l>Unbitter'd bitterneſs it ſelf of all,</l>
               <l>Earth's Heavenly few, the moſt <hi>Angelicall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Vice</hi> be dam'd, thou art like one of thoſe,</l>
               <l>Who giddi'd in a Ship at Sea, ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>The <hi>Continent</hi> doth move as well as they,</l>
               <l>All tread awry to thoſe whoſe <hi>Feet</hi> are ſplay.</l>
               <l>If (though our <hi>thoughts</hi> are free) we muſt not think</l>
               <l>Ill of the King; he that ſhall black his Ink,</l>
               <l>And pale his Paper with words, ſtartles more,</l>
               <l>Than, <hi>Lord, have mercy,</hi> chalk'd upon the door,</l>
               <l>To traduce <hi>Princes</hi> in the ſhapes of ſin,</l>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Painters</hi> chooſe to draw the <hi>Devil</hi> in;</l>
               <l>Theſe are the <hi>marks o'th' Beaſts,</hi> who caſts an eye</l>
               <l>On thoſe (as on a <hi>Baſilisk</hi>) muſt die.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Mecha Pilgrims</hi> at their Prophets Tomb,</l>
               <l>Need nothing elſe to make them blind or dumb.</l>
               <l>Here now my Muſe would ſit as Judg at laſt,</l>
               <l>And Sentence paſs on every Sentence paſt;</l>
               <l>But he's not worth the while, Avant, be gone;</l>
               <l>Yet firſt attend thy <hi>Benediction:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou that darſt own, and doſt deſire no Name,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But what is Regiſtred to endleſs ſhame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Live long in all the</hi> Plagues <hi>this World affords;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And if thou wilt repent and eat thy words</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100279:22"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>To choak thee; or, to give the Devil's due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Hangman <hi>draw thee, and thy</hi> Painter <hi>too.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>THE <hi>HYPOCRITICAL CHRISTIAN:</hi> OR THE Conventicling Citizen.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WEll! for a careful foreſight, ſober wit,</l>
               <l>Give me a <hi>Godly,</hi> zealous, <hi>Wiggiſh Cit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He twice a <hi>Week</hi> to <hi>Conventicle</hi> walks,</l>
               <l>Where Bawling, Canting <hi>Preacher</hi> Nonſenſe talks.</l>
               <l>He ſqueamiſh <hi>Fool</hi> for <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divine</l>
               <l>Nere cares; becauſe he cannot Sob, and Whine.</l>
               <l>He likes a <hi>Tubſter</hi> with his down caſt Face,</l>
               <l>His Comic Poſtures, and his damn'd Grimace.</l>
               <l>But hates the Rev'rend <hi>Clergy</hi> of the Town,</l>
               <l>Diſdains with Pride a <hi>Pulpiteer</hi> in Gown.</l>
               <l>And every <hi>Parſon</hi> Dr. <hi>Crape</hi> he'l call;</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Lad</hi> of late at Merchant-<hi>Taylors</hi> Hall.</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſneaking looks his <hi>Principles</hi> betray'd.</l>
               <l>It was a ſly, ſtarv'd Whig in Maſquerade,</l>
               <l>A ſtingy perjur'd, faithleſs Renegade.</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100279:22"/>
               <l>The Godly <hi>Puppet</hi> came (he ſaid) to ſee,</l>
               <l>And know the Humour of the Company.</l>
               <l>But the Glut'nous <hi>Aſs</hi> he was ſo neſty,</l>
               <l>Hew'd down the Walls of the <hi>Ven'ſon</hi> Paſty.</l>
               <l>To come to's roſt; Alas! the <hi>Tarts</hi> and Pyes,</l>
               <l>To's Oſtrich-ſtomack fell a Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>His Appetite was keen for all's pretences,</l>
               <l>He pleas'd his Eye, and Banqu'tted his Senſes.</l>
               <l>Then all the generous Gueſts traduces,</l>
               <l>With ſturring, dirty, pit'ful abuſes.</l>
               <l>Becauſe they drank a Loyal Health or two,</l>
               <l>He calls them <hi>Popiſh, Toriſh</hi> drunken Crew.</l>
               <l>A parcel of mean ſordid <hi>Lads</hi> there were,</l>
               <l>Who he was certain near eat <hi>Buck</hi> before.</l>
               <l>For ſuch abuſes let the <hi>Lad</hi> beware,</l>
               <l>And ſo let pimping, Whiggiſh <hi>Harry Care.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who's Tugging daily to Promote the <hi>Cauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To T'wart all Juſtice, and make Null the <hi>Laws.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>One <hi>Ignoramus</hi>-man, (ſays he) at leaſt,</l>
               <l>Is able purchaſe all that were at Feaſt.</l>
               <l>All their Eſtates in equal Ballance lai'd,</l>
               <l>By one <hi>Whig-Jury-man's</hi> would be out-weigh'd.</l>
               <l>Faith! <hi>Harry</hi>'s very generous; he prates</l>
               <l>As tho he really knew all mens Eſtates.</l>
               <l>Poor Mr. <hi>Chriſtian's</hi> dead, and th' Dukes Grace,</l>
               <l>May give to <hi>Harry</hi> his old Stewards Place.</l>
               <l>For he's a Godly, Honeſt Man, and true,</l>
               <l>And do's deſerve his Place, and Pill'ry too.</l>
               <l>His too hot Zeal for <hi>Teckley</hi> Reformation,</l>
               <l>In broaching Falſhoods, t'embroil the Nation;</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100279:23"/>
               <l>His Venting this, and contradicting that,</l>
               <l>Shew him more Fool, or Knave, than pillar'd <hi>Nat:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The greateſt Truths that publiſhed can be,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Hodge;</hi> are Story's and damn'd Ribaldry,</l>
               <l>If it with his and <hi>Gotham</hi>'s diſagree,</l>
               <l>The Dukes young Daughter could not live, 'twas ſaid</l>
               <l>'Twas ſo infirm a Child, and ſince 'tis dead.</l>
               <l>The Serenading Crew, for all their ſqueaking,</l>
               <l>Were Thieves, and did intend Houſe-breaking.</l>
               <l>Contriv'd with's Grace, a black and diſmall War,</l>
               <l>To batter him with Fiddles and Gitter,</l>
               <l>The Inſtrument of Death, a ſmall <hi>Rechorder,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And Fiddle Stick, and Pipe to do th' Murder.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Chicheſter</hi> Informer took a Pot,</l>
               <l>Too much of Brandy; and his Brains were hot,</l>
               <l>Broke Windows, was a ſwearing drunken Sot.</l>
               <l>H' had wild Freaks, ungovernable Paſſions,</l>
               <l>And dy'd (like Biſhop's Horſe) of the Faſhions.</l>
               <l>The fine Prelatic Jade will ſure be Sainted,</l>
               <l>Yes, yes: If <hi>Baxters</hi> book of Saint's reprinted.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Curtiſs, Care</hi> with mighty <hi>Polander,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall have their Names in Whiggiſh Calender.</l>
               <l>And all who carry on the work o'th' Laird.</l>
               <l>Shall have a good and bountifull Reward.</l>
               <l>In this large Catalogue of Fools and Knaves,</l>
               <l>Come Leaden Conſtables with Wooden Staves.</l>
               <l>With Solemn Oaths they gravely can diſpence,</l>
               <l>They have a ſwinging well ſtretcht Conſcience.</l>
               <l>Who take up the Office out of mighty Zeal,</l>
               <l>To ſupport their Brethren o'th' <hi>Common Weal.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:100279:23"/>
               <l>They to th' Brother-hood ſend holy Greetings,</l>
               <l>Acquaint them how they'l come moleſt th' <hi>Meetings.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then hey! the Godly Flock's diſpers'd and gone,</l>
               <l>And all (like young Fledg'd Birds) are quickly Flown.</l>
               <l>The Preacher then with's Congregation,</l>
               <l>Give thanks for this great Preſervation,</l>
               <l>And Orders that th' Thanks of the <hi>Houſe</hi> be ſent,</l>
               <l>To Godly <hi>Conſtable</hi> for's good intent.</l>
               <l>O! what will not Men do, if this they dare,</l>
               <l>To Affront Juſtice? And themſelves Forſwear</l>
               <l>To Oblige a few, and ſuch a Faction pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Who in this Government were ne're at eaſe.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Officer</hi> (though gravely Sworn) Cologues,</l>
               <l>Call's <hi>Hilton</hi> Fool, and all th' <hi>Informers</hi> Rogues.</l>
               <l>Though he hath <hi>Warrants</hi> with him, that's all one,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of <hi>Laws,</hi> he Executeth none.</l>
               <l>'Tis ſtrange, ſuch <hi>Meetings</hi> cannot ſilenc'd be,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Preacher</hi> bawls ſo much for <hi>Liberty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And boldly talks of <hi>Subjects Property.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh! Horrid Inſolence! can Juſtice ſleep?</l>
               <l>Not ſee ſuch Vermin into Corners creep?</l>
               <l>Seduce poor <hi>Women,</hi> and on <hi>Cit</hi> impoſe,</l>
               <l>Draw him through <hi>Bogs</hi> of <hi>Error</hi> by the Noſe.</l>
               <l>Tell him of Plots, and great <hi>Deſigns,</hi> forſooth</l>
               <l>All which the Cred'lous <hi>Cit</hi> ſucks in for Truth,</l>
               <l>That ſev'ral <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were up and down,</l>
               <l>In cloſe <hi>Cabals,</hi> for to enſlave the Town.</l>
               <l>It was, not long ago at <hi>Lor'ners</hi>-Hall,</l>
               <l>That Youngſter did for <hi>Magna Charta</hi> Bawl.</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100279:24"/>
               <l>And (like <hi>Hugh Peters</hi>) with new ſtrange Alarms,</l>
               <l>Bid 'm beware, ſtand ſtifly to their Arms.</l>
               <l>To quit themſelves like Men; be Strong and Stout,</l>
               <l>Secure their Perſons, and the <hi>Tories</hi> Rout.</l>
               <l>What? loſe the Priv'ledge of Chuſing <hi>Shrieves,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Rich</hi> will prove two deadly Thieves.</l>
               <l>They'l rob you of your <hi>Jury</hi>'s here at home,</l>
               <l>And make you fall ſad Victims unto <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then ſtill oppoſe the Polls of Sir <hi>John More,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He hugs that Witch, the <hi>Babylonic</hi> Whore,</l>
               <l>Will ne're your Native Liberty's reſtore.</l>
               <l>Be ready too, your <hi>Charter</hi> to ſecure,</l>
               <l>Who thoſe damn'd <hi>Que-Warranto</hi>'s can't endure?</l>
               <l>You ſee that <hi>Oxford</hi> ſtoutly doth Defie,</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Writs;</hi> and will protect their <hi>Liberty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ne're truſt their <hi>Charter</hi> in the Hands of <hi>King's,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who'd bauk their <hi>Priv'ledge,</hi> and clip their <hi>Wings.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then ſtand it out Boyes ſtill, and ſtill be Famous,</l>
               <l>(Like <hi>Oxford</hi> Towns-Men) for old <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But I'm inform'd of late that Whiggiſh Town</l>
               <l>Is Alter'd ſtrangely; and is Loyal grown,</l>
               <l>An Impudent Reſiſtance do's diſown.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Charter</hi> they'l Reſign for all the bawling,</l>
               <l>Of Fooliſh <hi>Wright,</hi> and ſelf-conceited <hi>Pawling.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To oppoſe the <hi>Loyaliſts</hi> the <hi>Whigs</hi> don't dare,</l>
               <l>The Youngſters laugh at dull <hi>Machine</hi> the <hi>Mayor.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus Honeſty, I hope, in vogue may be,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Cit</hi> may find his long loſt <hi>Loyalty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And baul no more for Bugbear <hi>Property.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:100279:24"/>
               <l>May names of Parties and Diſtinctions ceaſe,</l>
               <l>May <hi>Faction</hi> fall, and <hi>Loyalty</hi> increaſe,</l>
               <l>To Stabliſh here an Univerſal Peace.</l>
               <l>May <hi>Cit</hi> to <hi>Church</hi> devoutly go and Pray,</l>
               <l>And ne're diſpiſe a Godly-Homily.</l>
               <l>Ne're Meet thus in Un-hallowed <hi>Barns</hi> and <hi>Sty</hi>'s,</l>
               <l>And blindly Offer their Fools Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>Leave <hi>Cit,</hi> thoſe <hi>Synagogues,</hi> and do Conform,</l>
               <l>Into the <hi>Churches</hi> Breaſt at laſt Return.</l>
               <l>Caſt off (for Shame) the Factious Crew; you know</l>
               <l>How they Prophanely impudent do grow.</l>
               <l>An Am'rous Brother late ſo kind and tender,</l>
               <l>Did there with Siſter Publickly <hi>Engender.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Preacher</hi> ſaw the <hi>Godly Act</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saw the <hi>Lewd Couple</hi> Zealouſly <hi>Embrace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He nodded, Frown'd, and gravely did Reprove,</l>
               <l>Their wicked Satyr's way, of Brutal Love.</l>
               <l>Hence forth he'l have a Smarter Rod in Pickle,</l>
               <l>For ſuch <hi>Debaucher's</hi> of's dear Conventicle.</l>
               <l>From ſuch Vile <hi>Cells</hi> as from Contagion ſlee,</l>
               <l>Such Deeds were never ſeen in <hi>Monaſt'ry.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beleive it (to th' Eternal ſhame of <hi>Meetings</hi>)</l>
               <l>Nor in our <hi>Churches</hi> are ſuch Carnal Greetings.</l>
               <l>Then pri'thee Diſaffected <hi>Cit</hi> Comply,</l>
               <l>With Law; and thou'lt enjoy thy <hi>Liberty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Securely live beneath thy <hi>Vine</hi> at eaſe.</l>
               <l>Thy Credit and thy Fortune will encreaſe.</l>
               <l>Be Loyal, and Defend the Kings Juſt Right,</l>
               <l>Ne're read a Factious Pamphlet with delight.</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100279:25"/>
               <l>Ne're ſeed on <hi>Horſe</hi> fleſh; nor read vain Diſcourſes,</l>
               <l>'Twixt <hi>Charing-Croſs</hi> and your <hi>Wool-Church-Horſes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ne're have a Vitious thought 'gainſt Majeſty,</l>
               <l>But let all Treaſon Talkers ſilenc'd be,</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Vermin</hi> that do girn at <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oppoſe their barking; and let the <hi>World</hi> know</l>
               <l>You can be honeſt, if you would be ſo.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Comet</hi> that appear'd did ſure portend,</l>
               <l>That all your Factions here will have an end,</l>
               <l>And Zealous Conventiclers will amend.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the <hi>Loyal Apprentices</hi> FEAST.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe buiſy Town grew ſtill, and <hi>Trait'rous Whigs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had lately chang'd their <hi>Looks</hi> &amp; <hi>Periwigs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leſt Envy's Face behind, and Sniv'ling Cant,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hectors</hi> turn'd, with <hi>Loyaliſts</hi> to Rant.</l>
               <l>I know not which it was, whether They thought</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Conventicling Whores</hi> might there be brought</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100279:25"/>
               <l>By <hi>ſtrict Devotion</hi> to meet a <hi>BROTHER;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or whether 'twas they Scented out ſome other</l>
               <l>Warm Zealous <hi>Game,</hi> as <hi>Paſty, Pudding-Pie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not Superſtitious now, if <hi>WHIG</hi> be by.</l>
               <l>But ſomthing 'twas made <hi>Godly'ſt Men o'th'Nation</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Back-ſlide a little now for Recreation;</l>
               <l>And here's a <hi>Penitential Pſalm</hi> of One</l>
               <l>That tells his <hi>BRETHREN</hi> what Himſelf has done</l>
               <l>At <hi>LOTAL-FEAST</hi> in <hi>MERCHNT-TAYLORS-HALL</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Mongſt <hi>Coxcomb-Lords,</hi> and Worſhippers of <hi>BAAL;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whither <hi>Fooliſh KING,</hi> and <hi>PRINCES</hi> too had ſent</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fat B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CKS,</hi> in Sacrifice to IDOLS meant.</l>
               <l>Yet 'mongſt ſuch Fools a <hi>WHIG</hi> can Eat and Drink,</l>
               <l>Whilſt H'one thing Speaks, and doth another Think.</l>
               <l>He in Deceit can mannage cunning ſlight;</l>
               <l>Not ſo the <hi>Tories,</hi> they muſt be downright,</l>
               <l>And naturally are ſo to all Mens ſight.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Whigs</hi> with Reſervation Speak and Write,</l>
               <l>And far out-do the greateſt <hi>Jeſuite.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Well; Fools we muſt be then, the <hi>Whigs</hi> will have</l>
               <l>For their dear ſelves the other Sir-name, <hi>Knave.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then let them hav't, well give the Devil's due,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whig</hi> earns it better than <hi>Papiſt, Turk,</hi> or <hi>Jew:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis but re-counting in <hi>PHANATICK</hi> ſtrain</l>
               <l>The fouleſt Crimes, and then they're <hi>SAINT</hi> again.</l>
               <l>A <hi>FALLEN STAR</hi> to day, perhaps to morrow</l>
               <l>May ſhine like <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CIFER,</hi> and from him borrow</l>
               <l>A brand or two of his Infernal <hi>LIGHT,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>T'intoxicate poor people in the <hi>Night.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100279:26"/>
               <l>New <hi>Lights,</hi> and new <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> they bring,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dark-Lanthorn-Counſels</hi> how to 'buſe the <hi>King;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Make every thing <hi>Ridiculous</hi> appear,</l>
               <l>That pleaſes <hi>HIM,</hi> or any <hi>LOYAL PEER.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>ROYAL FAM'LY</hi>'s but a <hi>Popiſh Crew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Doctor Crape-Gowns</hi> are all <hi>Papiſts</hi> too;</l>
               <l>A puny Pray'rs the beſt thing they can tell ye,</l>
               <l>Whileſt their <hi>Devotion</hi>'s fix'd upon their <hi>Belly:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Loyal ADDRESSES,</hi> and <hi>ABHORRENCES,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Quoth <hi>Turn-Coat Whig</hi>) are ſottiſh <hi>Flatteries;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>KING</hi> delights in <hi>Paraſites,</hi> we ſee,</l>
               <l>And none but <hi>Fools</hi> can in His Favour be;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſſolving Parliaments</hi> deſerves <hi>Damnation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For keeping <hi>Publick Juſtice</hi> from the Nation;</l>
               <l>And th' <hi>Godly Perſecuted.</hi> 'Laſs! 'tis worſe</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Tyranny,</hi> or <hi>Arbitrary Force.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Popery</hi> is come already! Where be we?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſtand faſt in <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>See how the <hi>Loval Beagles</hi> of the Town</l>
               <l>Flock from their Shops, t'adore the Idol CROWN.</l>
               <l>Thoſe filly Curs, that ſometimes us'd to help's,</l>
               <l>And foll'w our keen <hi>Rebellious Bloud-hound Whelps,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They're now declaring for the ROYAL CAUSE,</l>
               <l>Think KINGLY BLOUD too Sacred for our Jaws.</l>
               <l>Help now or never, <hi>Baxter, Curtis, Care,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And all <hi>True Patriots</hi> of our <hi>Holy War;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>COVRT</hi> can't be more odious made,</l>
               <l>Strike now; ſtrike home, or all our PLOT's betraid.</l>
               <l>Thus far the <hi>Whigs;</hi> For here the <hi>True Sence</hi> lies</l>
               <l>Of all their <hi>Libels, Rhithmes,</hi> and <hi>Forgeries;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100279:26"/>
               <l>And yet they're <hi>LOYAL</hi> ſtill; But ye muſt know</l>
               <l>'Tis with a <hi>Mental Reſervation</hi> though,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Brother Poet</hi> has at laſt confeſt;</l>
               <l>Who, if he'd hid <hi>This Truth,</hi> had ſpoil'd his <hi>Jeſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ay, we've experienc'd well what <hi>LOYALTY</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since <hi>Forty One,</hi> his <hi>Brethren</hi> brood and he</l>
               <l>Are like to ſhew; which makes us think, and ſay,</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Nick</hi>'s as <hi>True,</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> too, as <hi>They.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But YOU, <hi>Brave Loyal YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THS</hi> (that <hi>Fools</hi> &amp; <hi>Fops</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are nick-nam'd by the <hi>Rebel-Rout</hi>) Your ſhops</l>
               <l>Shall be Protected, by the Sov'reign Charms</l>
               <l>Of <hi>CHARLES</hi> and <hi>YORK,</hi> and their <hi>Victorious Arms;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With Heav'ns aſſiſtance, win Your ſelves Renown,</l>
               <l>Redeem the Credit of this <hi>Ancient Town;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Say, LONDON'S 'PRENTICES have done the thing,</l>
               <l>Joyn'd <hi>Zeal to GOD</hi> with <hi>Duty to the KING.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100279:27"/>
            <head>ON <hi>Old Doctor Wild</hi>'s New POEM TO HIS <hi>Old Friend,</hi> upon the <hi>New PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THus 'tis to ſtand Condemn'd by rigorous Fate</l>
               <l>To the vile <hi>Plague</hi> of a <hi>Poetick Pate:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Itch of Rhyming</hi> where it once does ſeize,</l>
               <l>Becomes a more <hi>Incurable</hi> Diſeaſe</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Pox</hi> or <hi>Scurvey:</hi> Harder 'tis to rout</l>
               <l>WILD's <hi>Scribling humour,</hi> than to Charm his <hi>Gout</hi>
               </l>
               <l>An <hi>Old Man's twice a Child,</hi> I heard folks ſay,</l>
               <l>But never <hi>more,</hi> than when he would ſeem <hi>Gay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And does with <hi>Jingling Hobby-horſes</hi> play:</l>
               <l>When ſprightly <hi>Fancy's</hi> gone, the <hi>doting Bungler</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mounts the brisk <hi>Muſe,</hi> but proves an errant <hi>Fumble</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Gets only <hi>Puling Verſe,</hi> languid and thin,</l>
               <l>Not to be call'd a <hi>Birth,</hi> but <hi>Souterkin.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:100279:27"/>
               <l>Sorry dull <hi>Puns,</hi> and Nauſeating <hi>Quibbles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Worſe than old <hi>Crab-i'th-wood,</hi> or <hi>Belman</hi> Scribbles.</l>
               <l>Juſt ſo <hi>Sir Limber-ham</hi> that ſcarce can crawl,</l>
               <l>Will on his <hi>Venus,</hi> and his <hi>Cupids</hi> call;</l>
               <l>And drains <hi>Five hundred Pieces</hi> from his Purſe</l>
               <l>To keep a <hi>Miſs,</hi> when more he wants a <hi>Nurſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But tell me <hi>Reverend Songſter!</hi> was it fit</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Doctorſhip</hi> ſhould thus the <hi>Pulpit</hi> quit,</l>
               <l>To Revel in ſuch <hi>Babyloniſh Wit?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy very Friends when they thy Poem ſcan,</l>
               <l>Say only—<hi>He's a Towardly old Man.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though thou forgot'ſt thy <hi>Calling, Age, Degree,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This <hi>Subject</hi> ſure ſhould curb thy <hi>Levity</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To treat of PARLIAMENTS at ſuch a rate,</l>
               <l>In <hi>fulſom Metaphors</hi> of <hi>Billings-gate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Before th' <hi>Auguſt Illuſtrious Senate</hi> come,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight <hi>turn up,</hi> (ſans ſhame,) thy <hi>Aged Bum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deſerves a <hi>Laſh</hi> from the <hi>Black Rod</hi> at leaſt</l>
               <l>To make th' <hi>Old Baby</hi> ſmart for the lewd Jeſt,</l>
               <l>Amongſt ſo many <hi>Olds</hi> as thou doſt trace,</l>
               <l>'Tis ſtrange the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> obtain'd no place.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Poor Diſſenter</hi> bravely might <hi>Aſcend</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into a Pulpit from the Tables end,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Hold forth</hi> Godly Sonnets to his Friend.</l>
               <l>We all are <hi>Joy'd</hi> at preſent <hi>Face of Things,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thank both <hi>Heav'ns kind Influence, and the Kings,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ROMES <hi>Vultures,</hi> nor the <hi>Gallick Cocks</hi> we fear,</l>
               <l>Safe in our watchful <hi>Eagles</hi> Royal Care:</l>
               <l>Yet love not to <hi>run mad,</hi> and <hi>Dance the Hay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>ſtung</hi> (like thee) With a <hi>Tarantula:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:100279:28"/>
               <l>VVho e're thy <hi>greazie Tale</hi> of <hi>Pork</hi> does view,</l>
               <l>Suſpects thee for the <hi>By-blow</hi> of a <hi>Jew.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Grandam</hi> when ſhe <hi>burnt th'old Stock,</hi> was cruel,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Bees</hi> but <hi>Waſps</hi> deſerve to be made Fewel:</l>
               <l>Good <hi>Houſewives</hi> do not think her Method <hi>ſafe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Drive</hi> is better than to <hi>Burn</hi> by half;</l>
               <l>But theſe <hi>Wild Sallies</hi> do too plainly ſhow,</l>
               <l>Thou doſt but <hi>Cackle</hi> when thou thoughtſt to <hi>Crow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Treating of Richeſt <hi>Robes of State,</hi> and <hi>Ermin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou juſt like ſome <hi>Pot-Poets</hi> Cozen German</l>
               <l>Bethinks thee of th'own <hi>thred-bare Cloaths &amp; Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then cry'ſt to <hi>Longlane with them-New put on;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sweet Sir! 'tis <hi>timely</hi> thought of, may't be done.</l>
               <l>But beſt make haſte e're <hi>Ketches Wardrobe's gone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thinkſt thou (VVILD as thou art!) ſuch <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage</hi> meet</l>
               <l>T'approach the Soveraign <hi>Legiſlative Seat?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pardon <hi>Great Senate!</hi> that his Phrenſy drew</l>
               <l>Me to the <hi>Rudeneſs</hi> here of naming You.</l>
               <l>The <hi>haughtieſt Subjects</hi> tremble when they come</l>
               <l>To your <hi>Juſt Barr,</hi> and dread th'<hi>Impartial Doom.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fair <hi>Copy</hi> of Heavens Policy! the ſame</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Idaea</hi> that rules the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Frame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhere <hi>Nobles,</hi> as the <hi>Fixed Stars</hi> do ſhine</l>
               <l>In Honours Firmament; And Rays Divine</l>
               <l>From <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> of the Church are ſpread,</l>
               <l>To ſtrike both <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> dead.</l>
               <l>Next, <hi>Sages of the Law,</hi> as <hi>Planets</hi> trace</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Circuits,</hi> to enliven in each place</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:100279:28"/>
               <l>Thoſe needful ACTS which here are fram'd, and deal</l>
               <l>Diſtributive <hi>Juſtice</hi> for the Publick weal.</l>
               <l>Then COMMONS as full <hi>Conſtellations,</hi> joyn,</l>
               <l>And their <hi>Wiſe Councels</hi> ſolemnly Combine,</l>
               <l>VVhilſt <hi>Sacred Majeſty</hi> incircled round</l>
               <l>VVith Native Glory, as the <hi>Sun,</hi> is found</l>
               <l>Beaming his <hi>Acts of Grace</hi> ſo free and bright,</l>
               <l>That all from <hi>Him</hi> borrow both <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Light.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Healing Aſſembly!</hi> whenſoe're you meet,</l>
               <l>The Peoples <hi>Choice,</hi> and the KINGS <hi>Wiſhes</hi> greet:</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Liberties,</hi> His <hi>Honour,</hi> You mantain,</l>
               <l>O let them ne'r be <hi>Differenc'd</hi> again!</l>
               <l>In his own <hi>proper Orb</hi> let each <hi>Star</hi> move,</l>
               <l>Not Joſtling thoſe <hi>Below,</hi> nor them <hi>Above.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let no <hi>Falſe Fires</hi> their <hi>dazling Beams</hi> diſplay,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>upſtart Meteors</hi> interrupt your way:</l>
               <l>All Your <hi>Debates</hi> lot <hi>Moderation</hi> Calm,</l>
               <l>And Your <hi>Reſults</hi> become the Nations <hi>Balm.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>little Foxes</hi> that the Land Defile,</l>
               <l>And ſeek our <hi>Vine</hi> and <hi>Tender Grapes</hi> to ſpoil,</l>
               <l>Unkennel them; and let ROMES <hi>Conclave</hi> ſee,</l>
               <l>In vain they PLOT, whilſt You our <hi>Guardians</hi> be.</l>
               <l>May <hi>Heaven</hi> all Your <hi>Conſultations</hi> Bleſs,</l>
               <l>And all <hi>Good Men</hi> pray for your wiſht Succeſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But our</hi> Old Buiſie Rhymer <hi>we ſhall loſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who</hi> Hawks and Kites, and blind Buzzards <hi>purſues,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil at laſt like a</hi> Bewildred <hi>Jolt-head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Muſe has all her</hi> Borrowed Feathers <hi>moulted.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Age makes all</hi> ſtoop—<hi>How faſt the</hi> Man deſcends?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Commences</hi> Doctor, <hi>and</hi> Poor Robin, <hi>Ends.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:100279:29"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SCANDAL PROOF,</hi> OR AN Heroick Poem On the Renowned Champions of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> Inpudent <hi>Dick Janeway,</hi> and the reſt of the Factious Tribe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>COme on ye Scribling <hi>Rebels</hi> of the Age,</l>
               <l>Come on I ſay, advance upon the Stage;</l>
               <l>Arm'd with <hi>Phanatick</hi> Malice, Zeal and Rage.</l>
               <l>Diſplay your Merits to the Publick View,</l>
               <l>Tell'em'tis You'r their Champion, none but You</l>
               <l>Dare Counter-Plot the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plotting Crew,</l>
               <l>Faith 'twas great pity there was not a Tryal</l>
               <l>Between that pack of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who did deny all,</l>
               <l>And You <hi>Phanatick</hi> Scriblers who Belly-all:</l>
               <l>I mean that Zealous Sanctified Gang,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comus,</hi> and <hi>Hal</hi>-Old <hi>Elephant,</hi> and <hi>Lang</hi>-</l>
               <l>(who precious Saints) no doubt in time may Hang.</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:100279:29"/>
               <l>And make as Fine a Show, as <hi>Whitebread</hi> did</l>
               <l>VVith th' other precious four whoſe Souls are fled</l>
               <l>Into another World; yet 'twas unkind</l>
               <l>To leave ſuch Holy Brethren thus behind,</l>
               <l>Without Directions, where their Friends to find.</l>
               <l>Alas poor Harmleſs Devils, what a Pother</l>
               <l>They make to Troop ſo haſty after th'other:</l>
               <l>Who dy'd great Rogues, yet ne'r deny'd their Trade</l>
               <l>As you do, who their Miſtery Invade,</l>
               <l>Proving your ſelves <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in Maſquerade.</l>
               <l>I Laugh to ſee how you'd the World deceive,</l>
               <l>If they would all your Lying Tricks believe;</l>
               <l>As how you'rth' only Men, that ſtand i'th' Gap,</l>
               <l>There to repel th' approaching Thunder-Clap</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Popery,</hi> which Threatens all the Nation,</l>
               <l>With no leſs than a Total Inundation;</l>
               <l>Unleſs prevented by your Reformation.</l>
               <l>This is a precious hopefull Age, no doubt,</l>
               <l>When ſuch an Impious, Daring Rebel Rout;</l>
               <l>Such Wretched Tools as You ſhall undertake</l>
               <l>A Reformation in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet 'tis but what we muſt expect from You,</l>
               <l>Who in plain Terms, (to give the Devil his due)</l>
               <l>Pretend to Love the King, but hate him too.</l>
               <l>Among the reſt of this <hi>Phanatick</hi> Knot</l>
               <l>Of Factious <hi>Whigs,</hi> Faith I had quite forgot</l>
               <l>To mention that Fgregious Raſcal <hi>Dick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That Wondrous Lying Son of Damn'd <hi>Old Nick:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Impartial Rakehell whoſe Romantick Skill</l>
               <l>Excells the other Lying Knights o' th' Quill:</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:100279:30"/>
               <l>So like a <hi>Janus,</hi> does <hi>Dick Janeway</hi> look,</l>
               <l>We ſee his Double Face in every Book;</l>
               <l>In which wee'r Weekly Plagu'd with's Impudence,</l>
               <l>Offenſive to all Loyal men of Senſe,</l>
               <l>Who hate both <hi>Dick,</hi> and's Damn'd Impertinence.</l>
               <l>Well then, go on thou Curſed Rogue in Grain,</l>
               <l>Proceed to Write in thy own Lying Strain.</l>
               <l>'Tis Meritorious; thou deſerv'ſt Applauſe,</l>
               <l>By Propping up the Sinking Damn'd <hi>Old Cauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which not prevented, Ruins the King &amp; Laws:</l>
               <l>Go tell th'awaken'd World, (but 'tis in vain)</l>
               <l>You Love (alas you Lye) Great <hi>Charles</hi> his Raign:</l>
               <l>How canſt thou Love the King, or can your Brood</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Whigs,</hi> when <hi>Treaſon</hi> Taints your Soul &amp; Blood,</l>
               <l>Ye Damn'd Antipodes to all that's good.</l>
               <l>But Thou amongſt the reſt art ſuch a Fool,</l>
               <l>Poor Silly Rogue! They uſe thee for a Tool:</l>
               <l>A certain neceſſary Implement,</l>
               <l>To Print and own the Lyes that they Invent;</l>
               <l>A Foppiſh Brazen Fool, that's led Aſtray</l>
               <l>By every Cunning <hi>Whig</hi> that ſhews the way:</l>
               <l>With what Officious <hi>Care</hi> thou Plagu'ſt thy Brains,</l>
               <l>To get the Name of Villain for thy pains;</l>
               <l>Like that Inglorious Rogue that ſet on Flame</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple; which to the Villains ſhame</l>
               <l>He only did, to gain a Carſed Fame:</l>
               <l>Such is thy Curſed <hi>Care</hi> thou damned Fop,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Pate more ſit for Scullens Broom, or Mop;</l>
               <l>Merits the Glorious Name of buſie Sot,</l>
               <l>And (Calves-Head-like) deſerves to go to Pot.</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:100279:30"/>
               <l>Thou Dull Inſipid <hi>Coxcomb,</hi> worſe then Beaſt,</l>
               <l>What Guts and Garbidge hath thy Brains poſſeſt;</l>
               <l>To make thy Scribling Whelpſhip ſo Uncivil,</l>
               <l>So unlike man, and ſo much like the Devil:</l>
               <l>Sure thou'rt the Spawn of ſome Ill Natur'd <hi>Gipſy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Got in a Barn, perhaps where each was <hi>Tipſy;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hatcht up with th' noiſe of Tory, Rory, Randy,</l>
               <l>The pure effects of Ale, and Beer, and Brandy;</l>
               <l>And ever ſince thou'ſt been the Devils Imp,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diffenters</hi> Bully, and <hi>Phanaticks</hi> Pimp:</l>
               <l>A perfect Staulking Horſe unto all thoſe,</l>
               <l>That Hate the King, and Love the Kingdoms Foes:</l>
               <l>A Drudging Journy-man, a Slave to th' <hi>Pope,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Next Heir in Law to the <hi>Heer Van Ketch</hi> his Rope;</l>
               <l>One whom the Devil, for his Excellent Work</l>
               <l>Is more beholding to, then <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Turk.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mayſt thou at length receive thy Merits Due,</l>
               <l>As Ample as the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plotting Crew;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Janeway,</hi> fare thee well, until I ſee</l>
               <l>Thy Rogueſhip made <hi>St. Dick</hi> at <hi>Tyburn Tree.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:100279:31"/>
            <head>Fitz-Harris HIS Farwell to the WORLD, OR A TRAYTORS <hi>Juſt Reward.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>FArwell great Villain, and unpittied Lie,</l>
               <l>Inſtead of Tears drawn from a tender Eye;</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand Traytors like <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Unhuman Monſter, to the World ingrate,</l>
               <l>An Enemy to the King, the Church and State;</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou been ſtarv'd, 't had been too kind a Fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Crimes were horrid, infamous and baſe.</l>
               <l>Deſerves a total extinct of his Race;</l>
               <l>Baniſh his Name unto ſome diſmal place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What's worſe than injuring Sacred Majeſtie?</l>
               <l>For which he ſuftered on the fatal Tree;</l>
               <l>May all men ſuffer for ſuch Loyalty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:100279:31"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> may then be glad, with Triumph ſing,</l>
               <l>When all her Foes are vaniſht with a ſtring;</l>
               <l>The Golden Age from <hi>Halcion</hi>-days will ſpring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe Wolves that Plot Proteſtant Lambs to Gull,</l>
               <l>May Heaven obſtruct the Engines of their Scull;</l>
               <l>Give them of <hi>Tyburn,</hi> Lord, their Belly full.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hot-headed Youths have been ſeduc'd of late,</l>
               <l>Beyond their Wits, talk of the Affairs of State;</l>
               <l>Obedience learn to avoid <hi>Fitz-Harris</hi> Fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe publick Libellers with Zeal and heat,</l>
               <l>With ſome unheard of Novels dayly Treat;</l>
               <l>If they write falſly, tie them from their Meat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell th' Ambitious, they Fools ſtrive in vain,</l>
               <l>To undermine a Crown, King <hi>Charles</hi> will Reign:</l>
               <l>To be true and honeſt, is the ſafeſt Gain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I hope to ſee Juſtice at <hi>Tyburn</hi> done,</l>
               <l>If ſo, ſome hundreds may have Cauſe to run;</l>
               <l>Give them what they deſerve, their Thread is ſpun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bid proud petitioners, good Advice approve,</l>
               <l>Make an Addreſs and in one Body move;</l>
               <l>With all humility t' gain their Prince's Love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I'de ſooner loſe a Limb, from th' Monument fly,</l>
               <l>Endure the worſt of Torments till I dye;</l>
               <l>Then willingly deſerve my Kings diſpleaſing Eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100279:32"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>London,</hi> on thee all ſlouriſhing joys deſcend,</l>
               <l>Heaven's bleſs the Government, and Governors to the end;</l>
               <l>Unanimous to agree, your Soveraign to defend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Man that burnt <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple down,</l>
               <l>Did it on purpoſe a Villain to be Crown'd;</l>
               <l>Mongſt Rogues (Damn'd Rogues) he got Renown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How many thouſands are there in the Nation,</l>
               <l>Meer Knaves, but Saints, in private Congregation;</l>
               <l>Loves Monarchy, with mental Reſervation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Gods rebuke the Error of the Age,</l>
               <l>Let moderation Tumultuous men aſſwage;</l>
               <l>But hang all thoſe againſt their King engage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let all diſſenting Brothers Love the King.</l>
               <l>To the Church Unite, 'tis a goodly thing;</l>
               <l>With Brethren to agree, and with <hi>Te Deum</hi> ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heaven's bleſs his Majeſty, with Plenty, Joy and Peace.</l>
               <l>To all that love the King Heavens give increaſe;</l>
               <l>Confound his Foes to pray I nere will ceaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non eſt Lex juſtior ulla</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quam Necis Artifficis, Arte perire ſua.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:100279:32"/>
            <head>THE MEAL TUBB PLOT.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GOod <hi>Heraclitus</hi> lets have no quarrel,</l>
               <l>Sing you of the Tap, i'll ſing of the Barrel,</l>
               <l>And neither laugh nor cry for the Lawrel.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Body can deny.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Fig for your Tap or your Cork. Do but bring here</l>
               <l>A barrel of empty Reports, <hi>(Mr. Singer)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You ſhall ſee we can broach them with a wet <hi>Finger.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I'll not meddle with Barrels of Ale and Bear,</l>
               <l>For ſhould they work again, we may fear</l>
               <l>Too quick a return o'th' <hi>Platonick</hi> Tear.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Pox of your Barrels full of <hi>French,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis a ſort of an ominous Bloody Drench,</l>
               <l>And full of diſpute as an Oyſter Wench.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:100279:33"/>
               <l>Give me that Miraculous Laſting Joke,</l>
               <l>O'th Barrel of Meal, that Blinded the Folk,</l>
               <l>Fill'd every Mans Mouth and yet every Man ſpoke</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It made more noiſe and was more hot,</l>
               <l>Than all thoſe Barrels I had forgot,</l>
               <l>That had their heads in the <hi>Gunpowder</hi>-Plot,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some ſay it was the very ſame.</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Byter John</hi> the firſt of the Name,</l>
               <l>Vented ſuch ſtore of Smoak and Flame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I think indeed they hit the Nail,</l>
               <l>For's Notes were found within the Meal,</l>
               <l>Wherewith the Diſcoverer wip'd his Tayl.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Regulus</hi> (but for the ſpoiling the Leaven)</l>
               <l>The Barrel full of Spikes had driven,</l>
               <l>And rowl'd the Rogue downward to Heaven.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which no Bedy can deny.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:100279:33"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE <hi>Between the Ghoſts of the two laſt Parliaments at their Interview <hi>Fuimur Troes</hi> Weſtminſter Ghoſt</hi>'s <hi>Advice.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom deepeſt Dungeon of Eternal Night,</l>
               <l>The Seats of Horror, Sorrow, Pains and Spight,</l>
               <l>I have been ſent to tell your tender Youth</l>
               <l>A Seaſonable and Important Truth!</l>
               <l>I feel, (but oh too late) that no Diſeaſe</l>
               <l>Is like a Surfeit of Luxurious Eaſe;</l>
               <l>And of all other the moſt tempting things</l>
               <l>Are too much Wealth, and too Indulgent Kings.</l>
               <l>None ever was Superlitively ill</l>
               <l>But by Degrees with Induſtry and Skill</l>
               <l>And ſome whoſe meaning hath at firſt been fair,</l>
               <l>Grow Knaves by uſe, and Rebells by Deſpair;</l>
               <l>My time is paſt, and yours will ſoon begin</l>
               <l>Keep the firſt Bloſſoms from the blaſt of Sin,</l>
               <l>And by the Fate of my Tumultuous ways</l>
               <l>Preſerve your ſelf, and bring Serener days,</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:100279:34"/>
               <l>The buſy ſubtile Serpents of the Law</l>
               <l>Did firſt my mind from Due obedience draw,</l>
               <l>While I did limits to the King preſcribe</l>
               <l>And look for Oracles that canting Tribe,</l>
               <l>I chang'd true Freedom for the name of Free</l>
               <l>And grew Seditious for Variety;</l>
               <l>All that oppos'd me were to be accus'd</l>
               <l>And by the Law Illegally abus'd.</l>
               <l>The Robe was ſummon'd M—d in the head,</l>
               <l>In Legall Minder none ſo deeply read:</l>
               <l>I brought him to the Barr where once he ſtood</l>
               <l>Stain'd with the (yet unexpiated) Blood</l>
               <l>Of the Brave <hi>Strafford</hi> when three Kingdoms rung</l>
               <l>With his Accumulated Hackney Tongue:</l>
               <l>Priſoners and Witneſſes were waiting by:</l>
               <l>Theſe had been taught to Swear, and thoſe to die</l>
               <l>And to expect their Arbitrary Fates</l>
               <l>Some for ill faces ſome for good Effates:</l>
               <l>To fright the people, and alarm the Town,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bedlo,</hi> and <hi>Oates</hi> Employ'd the Reverend Gown.</l>
               <l>But while the Trebble Mitre bore the blame</l>
               <l>The Nings Three Crowns were their Rebellious Aim.</l>
               <l>I ſeem'd and did but ſeem to fear the Guards,</l>
               <l>And took for mine the B—and the—W.—</l>
               <l>Antimonarchick Hereticks of State,</l>
               <l>Immortall Atheiſts, Rich and Reprobate:</l>
               <l>But above all I got a little Guide</l>
               <l>Who every Foard of Villany had try'd;</l>
               <l>None knew ſo well the Old pernicious way</l>
               <l>To Ruin Subjects, and make Rings obey,</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:100279:34"/>
               <l>And my ſmall <hi>Jehu</hi> at a furious Rate</l>
               <l>VVas driving <hi>Eighty</hi> back to <hi>Fourty Eight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This the King knew and was reſolv'd to bear</l>
               <l>But I miſtook his patience for his fear:</l>
               <l>All that this happy Iſland cou'd afford</l>
               <l>VVas ſacrific'd to my Voluptuous board.</l>
               <l>In his whole Paradiſe one only Tree</l>
               <l>He had Excepted by a ſtrict Decree,</l>
               <l>A Sacred Tree which Royall fruit did bear,</l>
               <l>Yet it in pieces I conſpir'd to tear,</l>
               <l>Beware my Child! Divinity is there.</l>
               <l>This ſo out did all I had done before</l>
               <l>I cou'd attempt, and He Endure no more.</l>
               <l>My unprepar'd and unrepenting Breath</l>
               <l>VVas ſnatch'd away by the ſwift hand of Death,</l>
               <l>And I with all my Sins about me hurld</l>
               <l>Toth' utter Darkneſs of the Lower VVorld;</l>
               <l>A Dreadfull place which you too ſoon will fee</l>
               <l>If you believe Seducers, more then me.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:100279:35"/>
            <head>Nitimur in Vetitum <hi>Oxford Ghoſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>HAil great prophetick ſpirit; who cou'd ſee</l>
               <l>Through the dark glaſs of ripening time what we</l>
               <l>Too true have found and now too late complain</l>
               <l>That thou great Spirit ſhoud'ſt foretell in vain,</l>
               <l>Full well and Faithfully did'ſt thou adviſe,</l>
               <l>Had we been modeſtly and timely wiſe.</l>
               <l>Free may you rang'e ſaid'ſt thou through every Field</l>
               <l>And what elſe more Luxurious Gardens yield</l>
               <l>Is thine; what e're may pleaſe what e're delight</l>
               <l>The weakeſt ſtomach niceſt appetite;</l>
               <l>Of all the plenty of ſo Vaſt a ſtore</l>
               <l>One thing forbidden is one, and no more,</l>
               <l>By late and ſad Experience of what's paſt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Probatum eſt ipſe Dixit:</hi> Do not taſt!</l>
               <l>Swift Ruins there, and ſure Deſtruction,</l>
               <l>How great a Truth had it in time been known.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:100279:35"/>
            <head>WESTMINSTER GHOST.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VAin empty nothing that were lately all,</l>
               <l>How juſt, and how unpitty'd is thy Fall!</l>
               <l>Well worthy of the Horrours of this place</l>
               <l>That wou'd no warning take by my diſgrace;</l>
               <l>Glutted with Plenty, ſurfeited with Peace,</l>
               <l>Weary of Bleſſings, ſick of to much eaſe,</l>
               <l>Mad, reſtleſs Troublers of our <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who wou'd not quiet be when things went well;</l>
               <l>Of ſeverel baſe deſignes, meer manag'd Tools,</l>
               <l>Raſh, unadvis'd, incorrigible Fools;</l>
               <l>Brisk Hotſpurs inconſideratly bold</l>
               <l>By much too violent, and too hot to hold;</l>
               <l>Zeal flew as if 't had been to run a Race,</l>
               <l>Duty and reaſon cou'd not keep it's pace:</l>
               <l>Inſenſible, Regardleſs of my Fate</l>
               <l>Dull <hi>Phrygian</hi> Sages, wiſe when 'tis too late;</l>
               <l>You liv'd and then you had an eaſy way</l>
               <l>To have provided 'gainſt the Evill day</l>
               <l>Who wou'd not then be timely wiſe? forbear</l>
               <l>Your vain unreaſonable ſorrows here;</l>
               <l>Frailty (for men are frail) may err one time</l>
               <l>But malice only can repeat the crime.</l>
               <l>Unthinking Senate fed with empty words</l>
               <l>Of Patriot Lawyers and proteſting Lords:</l>
               <l>Abus'd by popular and miſtaken friends;</l>
               <l>Serv'd a dull Property for baſe hidden ends</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:100279:36"/>
               <l>Liberty, Property, Religion,</l>
               <l>Sweet names and ſo is <hi>Reformation.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rank ſign of ſickly and diſtemper'd times</l>
               <l>When faireſt names diſguiſe the fouleſt crimes.</l>
               <l>The cry of liberty helpeth Ambition,</l>
               <l>And ſtrait-lac'd Conſcience quite choaks up Religion</l>
               <l>Of publick Int'reſt you had no concern;</l>
               <l>But damn'd a Proverb, ne're too late to learn,</l>
               <l>By no experience taught, miſcarriage tam'd</l>
               <l>Nor by ſad Inſtance of my Fate reclaim'd.</l>
               <l>What prejudice and private Ends ill us'd,</l>
               <l>Falſe zeal and like Religion ill excus'd:</l>
               <l>Who (ſtiff neck'd) rather wou'd my Fate repeat</l>
               <l>Than by new meaſures be ſecurely great:</l>
               <l>No freedom of debate was left for you</l>
               <l>When all was mov'd and manag'd by a few.</l>
               <l>Your leading <hi>M. J.—s</hi> and <hi>W—ton</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if all wiſdom were in them alone:</l>
               <l>A Houſe of Commons crumbled into three,</l>
               <l>Slaves in effect, and in appearance Free.</l>
               <l>What ail'd the Pilot ſlept he at the head?</l>
               <l>Or was your Judgment by your wills miſled?</l>
               <l>What evill ſpirits Influence did prevail</l>
               <l>That you who might at large ſecurely Sail</l>
               <l>In ſull Sea, and from all dangers free</l>
               <l>Wou'd run upon that ſhelf that ruin'd me?</l>
               <l>Theſe ſure and ſad effects I well foreſaw,</l>
               <l>Theſe reall ills which ſeeming good wou'd draw;</l>
               <l>From theſe ſad conſequences to diſſwade</l>
               <l>I was ſent forth, and gladly I obey'd:</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:100279:36"/>
               <l>I told you then what now too true I find,</l>
               <l>Where zeal flys out, and duty leaves behind,</l>
               <l>Tis wiſdoms ſhame and Policies defect</l>
               <l>For ſtill like cauſes will have like Effect.</l>
               <l>I ſought by wondrous Truth the point to gain,</l>
               <l>Urg'd many Reaſons, but urg'd all in Vain:</l>
               <l>None were of force againſt the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Counſell was thrown away, Fool that I was.</l>
               <l>Where men with Law and Prophets wou'd not live</l>
               <l>To think a meſſage from the Dead ſhou'd thrive.</l>
               <l>Spight of my foreſight, and my dear bought Skill</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſſandra</hi> I, you faithleſs <hi>Pans</hi> are ſtill.</l>
               <l>Your boundleſs paſſion did no meaſures keep,</l>
               <l>VVell might you break your Neck with ſuch a leap:</l>
               <l>Men may at Diſtance over about Kings</l>
               <l>And by your Influence move Earthly things</l>
               <l>But when thoſe Bounds they wou'd Exceed, and fly</l>
               <l>Too neer the Sun ſcorch'd they drop down, and dy,</l>
               <l>What an Occaſion loſt you to improve</l>
               <l>The Princes Favour and the Peoples Love?</l>
               <l>This when conſidering Poſterity</l>
               <l>Shall think upon, they'l hate your Memory;</l>
               <l>And as once antient <hi>Rome,</hi> they in their turn</l>
               <l>With you had never dy'd, or ne're been Born;</l>
               <l>Shou'd your Suceſſors tread your ſteps, they then,</l>
               <l>Tho they were Gods, like us, ſhall dye as men.</l>
               <l>Oh! may the next, (for ſure a next will be)</l>
               <l>Avoid the Rock that ruin'd you and me:</l>
               <l>Deeply affected with a juſt Concern</l>
               <l>At your ſad Fate ſelf-preſervation learn;</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:100279:37"/>
               <l>And merit by avoiding needleſs fears</l>
               <l>By moderat Councills, and praiſe worthy cares,</l>
               <l>A Monarchs bleſſing, and Three Kingdoms Prayer.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Tom, Thins Ghoſt</head>
            <l>IN dead of night when the pale Moon</l>
            <l>Had got to th' Nocturnall Noon</l>
            <l>Betwixt her Light, and what was lent</l>
            <l>From twinkling Candle almoſt ſpent,</l>
            <l>As I lay ſlumbering on my Bed</l>
            <l>I ſaw methought a man was dead,</l>
            <l>Gravely he ſtalk't and ſtood and ſtar'd</l>
            <l>While I lay trembling and was Scarr'd</l>
            <l>Dumb for a while at laſt I broke</l>
            <l>Silence and to the Phantoſm ſpoke,</l>
            <l>Art thou ſaid I that man of Sin</l>
            <l>Or Ghoſt of <hi>Thomas</hi> late Squire <hi>T.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He ſoon reply'd with Accents hollow</l>
            <l>In words conform to theſe that follow.</l>
            <l>From the <hi>Tartarean</hi> ſhades below</l>
            <l>That neither Bounds nor bottom know</l>
            <l>Where a new life, the Curſed gain,</l>
            <l>Throw conſtant Torments, Endles pain,</l>
            <l>I by permiſſion come to tell</l>
            <l>What Goverment there is in Hell,</l>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:100279:37"/>
            <l>Becauſe I know thou wert a Tory</l>
            <l>To thee I choſe t' impart my ſtory,</l>
            <l>For thou wil't Joyfully reveal</l>
            <l>What, Whiggs that long for, Common-weal</l>
            <l>Like <hi>Spartan</hi> Boyes, wou'd ſtill conceal.</l>
            <l>Attend then and my Narrative</l>
            <l>Communicate to all alive,</l>
            <l>I am the Soul of one of thoſe</l>
            <l>That both the <hi>K</hi>— and Law oppoſe</l>
            <l>And Itch' with Conſcientious Scurvey</l>
            <l>To turn the Kingdom topſey Turvey,</l>
            <l>Rogues that preſume themſelves appointed</l>
            <l>To contradict the Lords Anointed,</l>
            <l>Thoſe that wou'd murder an Addreſſor</l>
            <l>And cut the Legs of true Succeſſor.</l>
            <l>And make him look in piteous Caſe</l>
            <l>As <hi>Withrington</hi> in Chivy Chaſe,</l>
            <l>Nay cut his Throte and in his place</l>
            <l>Set <hi>Perking</hi> up of Extract baſe,</l>
            <l>Who has no more pretence to Rule</l>
            <l>This Land, than any other Fool,</l>
            <l>But may make out Il'e Swear as ſoon</l>
            <l>A Title to the World ith' Moon,</l>
            <l>I was I ſay of that Caball</l>
            <l>Till I was murder'd in the Mall;</l>
            <l>You've heard I know of that Barbarity</l>
            <l>Hatefull beyond all Bonds of Charity.</l>
            <l>Proceed we then with our Relation</l>
            <l>Of Action in th' Infernal Nation,</l>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:100279:38"/>
            <l>Aſſiſt me ſteed of <hi>Phaebus</hi> Legion</l>
            <l>VVhilſt I deſcribe the dolefull Region,</l>
            <l>One Monarch in that VVorld controuls</l>
            <l>VVith flameing Scepter, tortur'd Souls,</l>
            <l>And Captive, tho he be in Chains,</l>
            <l>Yet abſolute Emperour he Reigns.</l>
            <l>No Factions there diſturb the State</l>
            <l>VVhich is preſerv'd by ſteady fate,</l>
            <l>Unalterable Laws they have</l>
            <l>VVhich the Almighty God-head gave,</l>
            <l>And to their Prince ev'n on his Foes</l>
            <l>A ſtrict Obedience does Impoſe.</l>
            <l>That Prince is Lucifer, whoſe power</l>
            <l>The Subject Ghoſts adore Each hour,</l>
            <l>VVho to advance their mighty King</l>
            <l>In Blaſphemies, his praiſes ſing</l>
            <l>Devoutly ſwearing there's no odds</l>
            <l>Betwix this Grandeur and the Gods,</l>
            <l>Theſe tho' they ſuffer 'tis in Vain</l>
            <l>Amid'ſt their Torments to complain,</l>
            <l>If he but nod from burning Throne</l>
            <l>There's not a Soul that dares to groan,</l>
            <l>For Hell admitts of no Petition</l>
            <l>To redreſs Grievance of condition,</l>
            <l>Nor do Tumultuous Crowds appear</l>
            <l>VVith bold Remonſtrances of Fear,</l>
            <l>Nor Spirit Murmer at oppreſſion</l>
            <l>Nor prate of right or wrong Succeſſion,</l>
            <l>Their King Immortall, Oh! 'mong you,</l>
            <l>That <hi>Charles</hi> the Second were ſo too.</l>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:100279:38"/>
            <l>I love him now, and tho' a Devil</l>
            <l>Am much more honeſt grown and Civil,</l>
            <l>For having ta'ne a Drachm of Styx</l>
            <l>I have forgot my VVhiggiſh Tricks</l>
            <l>Next to the Prince there are that ſtand</l>
            <l>Awfully waiting his Command</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Belzebub, Moloch, Aſhteroth, Baal,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>Dagon,</hi> who before their fall</l>
            <l>Tho' not condemn'd t' Eternall Night</l>
            <l>VVhere <hi>Seraphins</hi> and ſons of Light.</l>
            <l>Thoſe curſed Peers when e're he will</l>
            <l>If he intends great woe or Ill</l>
            <l>To ſons of Earth he quickly can</l>
            <l>Summon into his Dark divan,</l>
            <l>Not to give Counſell, but to do</l>
            <l>VVhat his Dire Dictates Prompts him to.</l>
            <l>You have like him, one Noble Peer</l>
            <l>VVho wou'd do mighty Service there</l>
            <l>VVou'd he were there in ſtead of me</l>
            <l>To ſhew his Squinting Policy.</l>
            <l>He 'tis I mean that looks at once</l>
            <l>Like <hi>Cerberus</hi> from tipple Sconce</l>
            <l>But that his Eyes wou'd faſcinate</l>
            <l>And give a deſtiny to Fate;</l>
            <l>For he I fear wou'd break the Law</l>
            <l>By which this world is kept in awe,</l>
            <l>Since it is here his chiefeſt Care</l>
            <l>To break all Laws that Penall are,</l>
            <l>He wou'd go nigh ev'n in this ſtation</l>
            <l>To make a new <hi>Aſſociation.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:100279:39"/>
            <l>But if he did, Oh! There are Judges,</l>
            <l>In ſtead of Scarlet Cloth with Budges</l>
            <l>Not ſuch as theſe in which we trade</l>
            <l>But Robes of Solid Darkneſs made,</l>
            <l>They'd firk his Toby for take this</l>
            <l>For fatal truth, (and ſo it is)</l>
            <l>In the proceedings againſt furies</l>
            <l>There are no <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Juries,</l>
            <l>Plain Evidence is there believ'd</l>
            <l>And no convicted Soul repriev'd.</l>
            <l>No Mainprize there allow'd nor Bail</l>
            <l>But doomn'd to an Eternal Jayl,</l>
            <l>The reſtleſs Priſoners howl, and cry</l>
            <l>Whilſt they in burning Shackles fry,</l>
            <l>Yet in my Conſcience hee'd Endeavour</l>
            <l>Eev'n to deceive the great Deceiver,</l>
            <l>Or wou'd pretend to Court for Miſtreſs</l>
            <l>The fatalleſt oth' Fatal Siſters,</l>
            <l>And wou'd ſo wheedle her that ſhee</l>
            <l>Shou'd cut the thread of Monarchy,</l>
            <l>So wou'd he his dear wiſh obtain</l>
            <l>And put an end to <hi>Charles</hi> his Reign,</l>
            <l>Nor wou'd he value his Damnation</l>
            <l>To keep great <hi>James</hi> from Kingly Station,</l>
            <l>Here upon Earth he has a Pug</l>
            <l>Which he like Devil &amp; Witch does hug,</l>
            <l>For he ne're found his words were true in</l>
            <l>Any one thing but his own Ruin,</l>
            <l>He <hi>Whilom</hi> told the Yonker he</l>
            <l>Shou'd ſway the Britiſh Monarchy,</l>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:100279:39"/>
            <l>Of a known Baſtard grown a Prince</l>
            <l>But poor deluded <hi>Perkin</hi> ſince,</l>
            <l>From fancy'd Honour is degraded</l>
            <l>And all his Flowerde-lyſſes faded.</l>
            <l>But I degreſs from my Deſign</l>
            <l>While things on Earth, and Hell I joyn,</l>
            <l>Suffer me then to repreſent</l>
            <l>The Methods of our Parliament.</l>
            <l>VVhen <hi>Lucifer</hi> to utmoſt borders</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Erebus</hi> ſends out his Orders,</l>
            <l>His Officers make no delay</l>
            <l>But the great Summons ſoon obey,</l>
            <l>Unanimouſly they all Elect,</l>
            <l>Not ſuch as ſay they will protect,</l>
            <l>The Common Peoples Liberty</l>
            <l>From their dread Soveraigns Tyranny,</l>
            <l>For none his boundleſs Power Queſtions</l>
            <l>Or make undutiful Suggeſtions.</l>
            <l>But ſuch they are as when th' aſſemble</l>
            <l>Before his Footſtool bow and tremble,</l>
            <l>They come with ſteadfaſt Reſolutions</l>
            <l>To aſſert the fatal Conſtitutions,</l>
            <l>Nor do they once Capitulate</l>
            <l>Or grumble to maintain the State</l>
            <l>All that they have to him they owe</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mammon</hi> beſides is his they know,</l>
            <l>There is no Sawcy well clad Clown</l>
            <l>That claims the uſe of what's his own,</l>
            <l>Nor can from Helliſh mouth ſuch ſin come</l>
            <l>As to deny him his own Income.</l>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:100279:40"/>
            <l>There no Abhorror on their Knees,</l>
            <l>Pay <hi>Topham</hi>'s Arbitrary Fees.</l>
            <l>Nor bawling Lawyers Speakers make</l>
            <l>Which only with the Vulgar take.</l>
            <l>But hark! I hear the Midnight Bell,</l>
            <l>And that rings my Departing Knel.</l>
            <l>What I have ſaid pray con it or'e,</l>
            <l>Next time we meet Ile tell thee more.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Sejanus, OR THE <hi>Popular Favourite</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IS this thy Glory now? Is this thy Pride</l>
               <l>Of ſticking to the Saints and Godly ſide?</l>
               <l>Religious Bugbear words that fright from hence,</l>
               <l>From Subjects, all their Loyalty to Prince,</l>
               <l>Make black Rebellion ſeem white Innocence.</l>
               <l>Entitle Heaven to the Vileſt Crimes,</l>
               <l>Make Deity, like Rabble, blame the Times.</l>
               <l>Mad Zealots! ſo Atheiſtically Civil,</l>
               <l>Blſapheme the Gods to Complement the Devil.</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:100279:40"/>
               <l>The mightieſt of theſe inſpir'd Saints is come,</l>
               <l>To Crown himſelf with fancy'd Marterdom.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Geneva</hi> Whig that ſtill crys out at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But raiſes ſtill Domeſtick Broyls at home.</l>
               <l>How quietly Great <hi>Charles</hi> might end his Reign</l>
               <l>Which all in troubles the Dear Prince began,</l>
               <l>Now vext by Ghoſt mere ſhadow of a Man.</l>
               <l>The cunning Hypocrite that ſtill can Spy</l>
               <l>The ſmalleſt more in his kind Princes Eye,</l>
               <l>By Zeal and Nature made ſo double blind,</l>
               <l>That in his own the Beam he cannot find:</l>
               <l>Some ſay but one vaſt Luminary ſtands,</l>
               <l>In's furrow'd Brow, and watches all the Land.</l>
               <l>But ſunk into it's hole, crept out of ſight,</l>
               <l>As if it were afraid to ſee the Light.</l>
               <l>His Scull's too narrow Circle can't contain,</l>
               <l>His Towring thought and vaſt Gigantick Brain.</l>
               <l>Blinded again with hopes of Reformation,</l>
               <l>Poor little <hi>Polyphemus</hi> of the Nation.</l>
               <l>That mighty Monſter brav'd the riſing Flood,</l>
               <l>And this can wade throw a whole Sea of Blood.</l>
               <l>How hath this wretched Iſle been chang'd and curſt</l>
               <l>Since thou were't born in't, and it knew thee firſt.</l>
               <l>How did its tributary Rivers pay</l>
               <l>A bloudy dreadful Homage to the Sea!</l>
               <l>Whilſt on the purple Ocean thou didſt ride,</l>
               <l>And tack about with every Wind and Tide.</l>
               <l>This floating Bark he now again would Steer,</l>
               <l>Ah! treacherous Pilot! and falſe Mariner.</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:100279:41"/>
               <l>The Kingdoms yet ſcarce mended Hulk to ſave,</l>
               <l>Wou'd launch again into the Purple Wave.</l>
               <l>Religious Bully that can cheat a Nation,</l>
               <l>And make it periſh working out Salvation.</l>
               <l>Three Kingdoms he o're looks, and ſoon can Count,</l>
               <l>The Tories all from <hi>Barwick</hi> to the Mount.</l>
               <l>Sifts Cittys, Shires, to know what Each afford,</l>
               <l>Calls this tantivy, that proteſting Lord.</l>
               <l>Sees what grave Noddle's for Caballing fit,</l>
               <l>And who are Bromigems of Sence and Wit.</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Ovids</hi> Muſe from hence may take her flights,</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Argus</hi> only had an hundred lights.</l>
               <l>This little Monſtrous Corps is Eye all o're,</l>
               <l>And the whole Body ſees at every pore.</l>
               <l>Sees hatching thoughts meer Embrio of a Plot,</l>
               <l>Nay ſees it oft before it be begot:</l>
               <l>If well corrected for his Inſolence,</l>
               <l>The little Spannil fawns upon his Prince.</l>
               <l>But once eſcap'd the Ax, or fatal loops,</l>
               <l>Straight to the dull anthinking Rable ſtoops,</l>
               <l>Puft up with the vain blaſt of Vulgar Breath</l>
               <l>The ſmall State Urchins hurry to their Death,</l>
               <l>So the kind Air with an officious blaſt</l>
               <l>Toſſes poor Bubbles to the Clouds at laſt,</l>
               <l>Dances the little Globe about the Sky;</l>
               <l>Then breaks the glittering Ball it fan'd ſo high,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Romes</hi> fair darling once that govern'd all</l>
               <l>With the Inconſtant Rout did ſtand or fall:</l>
               <l>Th' obliged Camp their General did Crown,</l>
               <l>Then dragg'd his ragged Carcaſe throw the Town.</l>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:100279:41"/>
               <l>Weak Tools! that think they may ſecurely flee</l>
               <l>On the looſe Wings of wild Inconſtancy,</l>
               <l>Or on its Metaphor the Mobile.</l>
               <l>Diſguſted by the Rout this cunning wight</l>
               <l>Runs cringing to his Injur'd Monarch ſtraight,</l>
               <l>Whoſe goodneſs is too ready to forgive</l>
               <l>Faulty alone in ſuffering him to live.</l>
               <l>Advanc'd to follow Mace, and wear a Gown</l>
               <l>The <hi>Tony</hi> then ſaw Mutineers in Town,</l>
               <l>But now they all True Proteſtants are grown.</l>
               <l>Whilſt he unto it's Chambers can reſort</l>
               <l>There's naught alas! of Popery at Court,</l>
               <l>Clap the Prophetick Soul but in the Tower</l>
               <l>It ſtraight divines of Arbitrary Power,</l>
               <l>Nor leaves the Rout, and then as ſoon as able</l>
               <l>Leaves his good Prince juſt as he left the Rabble.</l>
               <l>This buſy Noddle of the Factious Crew</l>
               <l>(The Badg of upſtart Whigs muſt ſtill be new)</l>
               <l>With his green bob in his new Senate ſits</l>
               <l>And round him all thoſe Livery Men of Wits,</l>
               <l>Some raiſe a name, and ſome inſert a Clauſe</l>
               <l>Order their Bills themſelves and Vote 'em Laws,</l>
               <l>With awful care ſome Scriblers Penning be</l>
               <l>A Speech for Siſter <hi>Scotlands</hi> Liberty,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt <hi>Lotherdales</hi> unbounded Tyranny.</l>
               <l>There a Young Scribe is coppying out a Cant</l>
               <l>Next Morn for to be ſpoke in Parliament,</l>
               <l>Upſtarts an Hector, Swears upon a Book,</l>
               <l>Gad you ſhall ſee we will Exclude the Duke,</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:100279:42"/>
               <l>Then brings a Bill 'gainſt Arbitrary Pow'r</l>
               <l>And that will ſend a Member to the Tower,</l>
               <l>One Votes him to be cenſured on his Knees,</l>
               <l>This cries diſcharge, that let him pay his Fees,</l>
               <l>And in the little Club you fairly ſee</l>
               <l>Of the great Senate an Epitome.</l>
               <l>Our ſad Diſtracted <hi>Albion</hi> gaz'd around</l>
               <l>She ſaw no Foe, but ſtill ſhe felt a wound,</l>
               <l>The bleeding Dear thus trembling ſtands at bay,</l>
               <l>But can't find where the cloſe hid Archer lay.</l>
               <l>As on the winding Banks, and watery Maze</l>
               <l>Where fam'd <hi>Meander</hi> cuts her crooked ways,</l>
               <l>The loſt diſtracted Traveller doth gaze.</l>
               <l>At laſt kind Fate or Providence doth bring</l>
               <l>The poor Deſpairing Soul unto the Spring,</l>
               <l>So ſome kind Angel, genius of this Iſle</l>
               <l>VVhere peace alaſs! with thee cou'd never ſmile,</l>
               <l>Hath taught us now to make her flouriſh ſtill</l>
               <l>Shew'n us the hidden ſource of all her Ill,</l>
               <l>Reaſon the Plummet, with the Line ſhall be</l>
               <l>Both ſtretch'd to Fathom, and to meaſure thee,</l>
               <l>Lead throw the Labyrinth of all thy tricks</l>
               <l>All the wild Mazes of thy Politicks.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:100279:42"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Whig Caball.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>TH' ſullen night worn threadbare when I lay</l>
               <l>Expecting the Approach of Early Day:</l>
               <l>Such Loyal thoughts did in my Boſom rage.</l>
               <l>As drew my Curſes on this Factious Age:</l>
               <l>With tears I mourn'd our ſinking Countrys Fate,</l>
               <l>And ſhadow'd glory of the Royal State.</l>
               <l>Till ſlumbering at the laſt a glimmering Light,</l>
               <l>Methought was ſhown to my Myſterious Sight.</l>
               <l>When I deſcry'd a Treaſonous damn'd Caball,</l>
               <l>Hells mounting Engines that wou'd ſink us all,</l>
               <l>And riſe upon our King and Countrys fall.</l>
               <l>Dark were their Looks and knowingly I ſaw</l>
               <l>Villains they were and ſuch as fled the Law:</l>
               <l>Printers, and thoſe who had abuſ'd the times,</l>
               <l>Religion was their Cloak to hide their Crimes,</l>
               <l>Envious as Eiends, like Hells Divan they ſate,</l>
               <l>What wou'd Hell more? to ruin Church and State.</l>
               <l>So vile as theſe it never cou'd appear,</l>
               <l>Had the great <hi>Whigland Lucifer</hi> been there.</l>
               <l>When in an abrupt Voice I heard one Cry,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi>'s Idoll <hi>York</hi> ſhan't gorge our Liberty.</l>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:100279:43"/>
               <l>Rowz up my friends, our Ruin's more then fear'd</l>
               <l>Their Bulls do roar ſo lowd we can't be heard.</l>
               <l>With that he paus'd—then ſaid with much Diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>What ſhall we do? the Tyde of our Succeſs</l>
               <l>Now ſeems to Ebb, nor can we hope for leſs.</l>
               <l>For even thoſe will now believe no more</l>
               <l>Our ſhams who judg'd them Miracles before.</l>
               <l>Intereſt's our hook, and Freedom is the Bait,</l>
               <l>Bondage but nam'd, you'l ſee Rebellion Straight.</l>
               <l>Each weak pretence deceives the Eaſy Crowd,</l>
               <l>With them 'tis Law what is by us allow'd,</l>
               <l>But ſhallow are our Plots to ſearching Eyes,</l>
               <l>They ſee what Miſcheifs at the Bottom Lyes.</l>
               <l>Our Sh'riffs and Juryes for their ends applauſe,</l>
               <l>With Ignormaus Riots prop our Cauſe,</l>
               <l>They doubt of peace from thoſe that break the Laws.</l>
               <l>There our Deſignes are Deſp'rat and ſo croſt,</l>
               <l>Bold the Attempt muſt be to gain what's loſt.</l>
               <l>Zealous Rebellion muſt ſecure us all,</l>
               <l>We cannot fail while we pretend a Call.</l>
               <l>With that like Fiends they Vaniſh'd, and I woke,</l>
               <l>Whilſt all amaz'd and troubled thus I ſpoke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O wretched Land! how prov'd thy cureing vain?</l>
               <l>Sign thy old wound is breaking out again.</l>
               <l>The whole's Endanger'd by th' Infected part,</l>
               <l>But Heav'n inſtruct our great Phyſitians Art.</l>
               <l>Theres one way left to heal this deſp'rat Wound,</l>
               <l>Out off the Rotten for to ſave the Sound.</l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:100279:43"/>
               <l>Were there no Cauſe for this now needful blow,</l>
               <l>Religious peace then throwgh the Land wou'd Flow</l>
               <l>So <hi>Jehu Sion</hi> purg'd, and faith did grow.</l>
               <l>But let's unite with pious Joy to ſing,</l>
               <l>Health to the beſt—to <hi>Englands</hi> gracious King.</l>
               <l>Bleſt may he bee, his Queen and Royall Bed,</l>
               <l>And bleſs great <hi>James</hi> whilſt all their Foes ly Dead</l>
               <l>So we at laſt ſhall bruiſe the Serpents Head.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>THE <hi>Preſbyterian Club,</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS 'tother day <hi>Dick, Harry, Tom,</hi> and I,</l>
               <l>At th' Tavern ſate in wine and mirth rais'd high</l>
               <l>As round the Boord the Chearful Brimmer went,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Charles</hi> his health was drunk with one Conſent</l>
               <l>The Duke of <hi>Tork</hi>'s by Birthright next Enſu'd,</l>
               <l>Confuſion to all thoſe who wou'd Exclude.</l>
               <l>Thus went the Claret round till up the ſtairs,</l>
               <l>The Drawer came laden with Stools and Chairs.</l>
               <l>His Burthen thrice he did renew when I</l>
               <l>(To ſatisfy my Curioſity,</l>
               <l>Asking the Reaſon of his <hi>Task,</hi>) was told</l>
               <l>The Saints to night a Canventicle hold</l>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:100279:44"/>
               <l>The Room was large, well ſtor'd with Chairs &amp; Stools,</l>
               <l>Pitty 'twas to be fill'd anon with Fools,</l>
               <l>We Torys big with Expectation wait</l>
               <l>As well to ſee 'em as to hear 'em prate,</l>
               <l>When uſher'd up in long proceſſion came</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baxter</hi> with many more too long to name;</l>
               <l>Their looks, their dreſs, was ſuch you wou'd have thought</l>
               <l>They really had practis'd what they taught,</l>
               <l>VVith ſtarch lawn Band, and hats right gravely ſet</l>
               <l>Had you but ſeen 'em, you had thought they'd met</l>
               <l>There to ſet up a thorow Reformation</l>
               <l>VVhen 'twas it ſeems only for Recreation,</l>
               <l>Now round the Table all in Order ſate</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baxter</hi> at th' upper end as chief in State,</l>
               <l>For Pride is to th' Elect as natural</l>
               <l>As to the Devil 'twas before his fall,</l>
               <l>Mean while the Brethren drink till warm with wine</l>
               <l>They all to Treaſonable talk encline,</l>
               <l>And in each glaſs the Kings Deſtruction vow</l>
               <l>The King nere more their Enemy than now.</l>
               <l>Thus ſtill the Zealous glaſs went round, whom one</l>
               <l>VVith lift up hands and gogling Eyes begun,</l>
               <l>I thought him by his Bawling <hi>Farringdon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Half drunk to make a Godly ſpeech, and cry</l>
               <l>Oh Lord!</l>
               <l>When will thou put an end to Tyranny?</l>
               <l>When wilt thou free us from our Tyrants hands</l>
               <l>And ſettle on us all the Biſhops Lands?</l>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:100279:44"/>
               <l>For tho Lawn Sleeves and Gowns are an offence</l>
               <l>We with the Churches Livings cou'd diſpence,</l>
               <l>Nay verily I think I cou'd ſubmit</l>
               <l>To any thing, but Popery, to get,</l>
               <l>The Dioceſs of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> I ſay,</l>
               <l>I wou'd the Churches liveing were our prey,</l>
               <l>Nay I pray dayly God wou'd make 'em ſo</l>
               <l>For I have little elſe with Prayer to do,</l>
               <l>And tho the K. (good Man) be vainly lead</l>
               <l>Ith' crooked path of Wickedneſs to tread,</l>
               <l>'Tis Charity to wiſh the Tyrant Dead.</l>
               <l>Wou'd he were mounting, nay I wiſh he were</l>
               <l>Already crown'd in his Triumphant Chair,</l>
               <l>That he from thence might ſee us act below</l>
               <l>Deeds that our once Lov'd <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſhall outdo,</l>
               <l>Such deeds as even his Ghoſt ſhall fear to ſee</l>
               <l>While Satan trembles at our Tyranny,</l>
               <l>Leaſt coming thither we their Peace deſtroy</l>
               <l>And with inteſtin VVars his Relms annoy,</l>
               <l>Leaſt we by force ſhou'd their old Laws repeal</l>
               <l>And ſpight of Empire for a Common-weal,</l>
               <l>Thus ſpake the Reverend Pimp with ſober hum</l>
               <l>They as amazement had 'em all ſtruct dumb,</l>
               <l>Did ſilently applaud the ſpeech, whilſt he</l>
               <l>As in Arrears did ſwallow Brimmers three.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now the hour of ten drew nigh, 'twas time</l>
               <l>To part, leaſt ſtaying prove a Godly crime,</l>
               <l>Then being drunk, for all of 'em were ſo,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>B—r</hi> himſelf cou'd not uprightly go,</l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:100279:45"/>
               <l>Tho' he had much the odds of all the reſt</l>
               <l>Who in's ſheeps Cloathing fed a greedy Beaſt,</l>
               <l>Making the Scripture Prophecy prove good</l>
               <l>Which ne're till now was rightly underſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus they, (and time it was) the houſe Depart</l>
               <l>For I their Abſence wiſh'd with all my heart,</l>
               <l>Thus do the Saints ſolace themſelves, and thus</l>
               <l>They act thoſe Crimes which they abhor in us.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>THE <hi>True Presbyterian <hi>Without Diſguiſe</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Presbyter is ſuch a Monſtrous thing</l>
               <l>That Loves Democraſy and hates a King,</l>
               <l>For Royal Iſſue never making Prayers</l>
               <l>Since Kingdoms as he thinks ſhou'd have no Heirs,</l>
               <l>But ſtand Elective, that the holy Crew</l>
               <l>May (when their Zeal tranſports them) chuſe a new,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And is ſo ſtrongly grounded in belief</l>
               <l>That Antichriſt his coming will be brief,</l>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:100279:45"/>
               <l>As he dares ſwear (if he dares ſwear at all)</l>
               <l>The Quakers are ordain'd to make him fall,</l>
               <l>From whence he grows impatient, and he ſays</l>
               <l>The wiſeſt Counſels are but fond Delays,</l>
               <l>To hold him lingring in deluded hope,</l>
               <l>Elſe long e're this he had ſubdu'd the Pope.</l>
               <l>A Presbyter is he whoſe heart doth hate</l>
               <l>The Man (how good ſo e're) advance'd in State,</l>
               <l>And finding his Diſeaſe a Leproſy</l>
               <l>Doth Judg that all in Courts <hi>Geheſi</hi>'s be;</l>
               <l>Whiſt he himſelf in Bribery is loſt</l>
               <l>And lyes for gain unto the holy Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>When tho' in ſhew he ſeems a grave <hi>Tobias</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He is within a very <hi>Ananias,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The lay-prophane name (Lord) he hates, and ſays</l>
               <l>It is th' approaching ſign of the laſt days,</l>
               <l>For Church-men to be ſtiled ſo, nay more,</l>
               <l>'Tis Uſher to the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Whore,</l>
               <l>The Biſhops Habits with the Tip and Rochets</l>
               <l>Beget in him ſuch fancies and ſuch Crochets,</l>
               <l>That he believes it is a thing as Evil</l>
               <l>To look on them as to behold the Devil,</l>
               <l>And for the Government Epiſcopal</l>
               <l>That he condemns to be the worſt of all,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the primeſt times did ſuffer no man</l>
               <l>To' exalt himſelf, for all was held in Common,</l>
               <l>Yet 'tis moſt ſtrange when he is moſt Zeal-ſick</l>
               <l>Nothing can cure him but a Biſhoprick,</l>
               <l>Where once Inveſted proves without all ſcope</l>
               <l>Inſulting boundleſs more than any Pope,</l>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:100279:46"/>
               <l>A Presbyter is he that's never known</l>
               <l>To think on others good beſides his own,</l>
               <l>And all his Doctrine is of hope and Faith,</l>
               <l>For Charity, 'tis Popery he ſaith:</l>
               <l>And is not only ſilent in good works,</l>
               <l>But in his practice too Reſembles Turks.</l>
               <l>The Churches Ornaments, the Ring of Bells</l>
               <l>(Can he get Power) 'tis ten to one he ſells,</l>
               <l>For his well tuned Ears cannot abide</l>
               <l>A Jangling noiſe, but when his Neighbours chide</l>
               <l>A Presbyter is he that never Prays</l>
               <l>But all the World muſt hear him what he ſays;</l>
               <l>And in that faſhion too, that all may ſee</l>
               <l>He is an open Modern Phariſee.</l>
               <l>The Name of Sabbath ſtill he keeps, 'tis true,</l>
               <l>But ſo he is leſs Chriſtian more a Jew,</l>
               <l>Nor ſettled form of Prayer his Zeal will keep</l>
               <l>But Preacheth all his purer Flock aſleep,</l>
               <l>To ſtudy what to ſay, were for to doubt</l>
               <l>Of a preſumed Grace to hold him out.</l>
               <l>And to be learn'd is too too human thought,</l>
               <l>Th' Apoſtles all he ſays were men untaught,</l>
               <l>And thus he proves it for the beſt to be</l>
               <l>A ſimple Teacher of Divinity.</l>
               <l>The Reverence which Ceremony brings</l>
               <l>Into the Sacred Church his Conſcience ſtings,</l>
               <l>Which is ſo void of Grace and ſo ill bent,</l>
               <l>That kneel he will not at the Sacrament,</l>
               <l>But ſits more like a Judg then like a Sinner,</l>
               <l>And takes it juſt as he recieves his Dinner.</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:100279:46"/>
               <l>Thus do his ſaucy poſtures ſpeak his Sin,</l>
               <l>For as without ſuch is his heart within.</l>
               <l>A Presbyter is he who doth defame</l>
               <l>Thoſe Reverend Anceſtors from whence he came,</l>
               <l>And like a graceleſs Child above all other</l>
               <l>Denies Reſpect unto the Church his Mother,</l>
               <l>His Choſen Proteſtants he ſcorns, as men</l>
               <l>Not ſav'd, becauſe they are not Brethren,</l>
               <l>And leſt his Doctrine ſhou'd be counted new,</l>
               <l>He wears an ancient Beard to make it true.</l>
               <l>A Presbyter is he who thinks his Place</l>
               <l>At every Table is to ſay the Grace,</l>
               <l>When the good Man or when his Child hath paid</l>
               <l>And thanks to God for King and Realm hath ſaid,</l>
               <l>He then ſtarts up and thinks himſelf a Debtor</l>
               <l>Till he doth cry (I pray you thank God better,)</l>
               <l>When long he prays for every living thing</l>
               <l>But for the Catholick Church, and for the King.</l>
               <l>A Presbyter is he wou'd wondrous fain</l>
               <l>Be call'd Diſciple by the holy Train,</l>
               <l>Which to be worthy of, hee'l ſtray and Err</l>
               <l>Ten Miles to hear a ſilenc'd Miniſter:</l>
               <l>He loves a Veſper Sermon, hates a Mattin,</l>
               <l>And he deteſts the Fathers nam'd in Latin,</l>
               <l>And as he <hi>Fryday, Sunday</hi> makes in Dyet,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the King and Canons do deny it,</l>
               <l>The ſelf ſame nature makes him to repair</l>
               <l>To week day Lectures, more then Sunday Prayer,</l>
               <l>And as the Man muſt needs in all things Err</l>
               <l>He ſtarves his Parſon, crams his Lecturer,</l>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:100279:47"/>
               <l>A Presbyter is he whoſe heart is bent</l>
               <l>To croſs the Kings deſigns in Parliament.</l>
               <l>Where whilſt the place of Burgeſs he doth bear,</l>
               <l>He thinks he owes but ſmall Allegiance there,</l>
               <l>But ſtands at Diſtance at ſome higher thing,</l>
               <l>Like a <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> or a kind of King.</l>
               <l>Then as in Errant times bold Knights were wont</l>
               <l>To ſeek out Monſters, and Adventures hunt,</l>
               <l>So with his Wit and Valour he doth try,</l>
               <l>How the Prerogative he may defy.</l>
               <l>Thus he attempts and firſt he fain wou'd know,</l>
               <l>If that the Soveraign Power be new, or no:</l>
               <l>Or if it were not fitter Kings ſhould be</l>
               <l>Confin'd unto a limitted Degree.</l>
               <l>And for his part like a <hi>Plebeian</hi> ſtate,</l>
               <l>Where th' poor Mechanicks freely may debate</l>
               <l>All matters at their pleaſure, not confin'd</l>
               <l>To this, or that, but as they cauſe do find;</l>
               <l>When tho' that every Voice againſt him go,</l>
               <l>Hee'l ſlay the Gyant with his Single, No.</l>
               <l>He in his Heart, tho' at a poor Expence,</l>
               <l>Abhors a gift that's call'd Benevolence.</l>
               <l>For as his Mind, ſo is his Bounty bent,</l>
               <l>And ſtill unto the King Malevolent.</l>
               <l>He is the Stateſman, juſt enough, preciſe,</l>
               <l>The neareſt Government to Scandalize.</l>
               <l>Nor like a Drunkard when he doth Expoſe</l>
               <l>In ſecret underneath the ſilent Roſe,</l>
               <l>To uſe his Freedom when the pot might bear,</l>
               <l>The ſaults which cloſely he commited there.</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:100279:47"/>
               <l>But, <hi>Shimei</hi> like, to all the Men he meets,</l>
               <l>He ſpews his Frantick Venom in the ſtreets:</l>
               <l>And tho' he ſayes the ſpirit moves him to it,</l>
               <l>The Devil is that Spirit made him do it.</l>
               <l>A Presbyter is he (els there is none,)</l>
               <l>That thinks the King will change Religion.</l>
               <l>His doubtful thought like to the Moon blind Eyes,</l>
               <l>Makes the Beaſt ſtart at every ſhape he Spyes.</l>
               <l>And what his fond miſtaken fancy Breed,</l>
               <l>He does believe as firmly as the Creed.</l>
               <l>From whence he doth proclaim a faſt to all,</l>
               <l>That he allows to be Canonicall,</l>
               <l>And then he Conſecrates a Secret Room,</l>
               <l>Where none but the Elected Siſters come.</l>
               <l>When being met doth Treaſon boldly Teach,</l>
               <l>And will not Faſt and Pray, but Faſt and Preach:</l>
               <l>Then ſtrains a Text whereon he may Relate,</l>
               <l>The Churches Danger, Diſcontent of State,</l>
               <l>And hold them there ſo long in fear &amp; doubt</l>
               <l>That ſome do think 'tis Danger to go out.</l>
               <l>Beleiving if they hear the Cieling Crack,</l>
               <l>The Biſhops are behind them at their Back.</l>
               <l>And ſo they ſit bewaling one another,</l>
               <l>Each groaning Siſter howling to her Brother.</l>
               <l>A Presbyter is he has womens Fears,</l>
               <l>And yet will ſet the whole world by th' Ears:</l>
               <l>Hee'l rail in publick if the King deny</l>
               <l>To let the Quarrell of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> die.</l>
               <l>He ſtorms to hear in <hi>France</hi> the VVars ſhou'd ceaſe</l>
               <l>And that by Treaty there ſhould be a peace.</l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:100279:48"/>
               <l>For ſure ſaith he the Church doth Honour want,</l>
               <l>VVhen 'tis not truly called Militant,</l>
               <l>And in plain truth as far as I can find,</l>
               <l>He bears the ſelf ſame Treaſonable Mind</l>
               <l>As does the Jeſuit, for tho' they be</l>
               <l>Tongue Enemies, in ſhew their Hearts agree.</l>
               <l>And both profeſſed foes alike conſent,</l>
               <l>Both to betray th' Anointed Innocent.</l>
               <l>For tho their Manners differ, yet they aim,</l>
               <l>That either may the King or Kingdom maim.</l>
               <l>The difference is this way underſtood,</l>
               <l>One in Sedition, 'tother deals in Blood.</l>
               <l>Their Characters abridg'd if you will have,</l>
               <l>Each ſeems a Saint, yet either proves a Knave.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:100279:48"/>
            <head>THE DISSENTER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat! ſhall a gorious Nation be o're thrown</l>
               <l>By Troops of ſneaking Raſcals of our own?</l>
               <l>Muſt Civil and Eccleſiaſtick Laws,</l>
               <l>Once truckle more under the Good old Cauſe?</l>
               <l>Shall theſe ungrateful Varlets think to Live,</l>
               <l>Only to clip Royal Prerogative?</l>
               <l>Shall all our Blood turn whey whilſt we do ſee,</l>
               <l>Men both affront, and ſtab the Manarchy?</l>
               <l>I'm all inflam'd with a poetick Rage,</l>
               <l>And will chaſtiſe the follies of the Age.</l>
               <l>Thoughts crow'd ſo faſt upon me I muſt Write,</l>
               <l>Till I've diſplay'd the gaudy Hypocrite.</l>
               <l>He's one that ſcarcely can be call'd a Man,</l>
               <l>And yet's a pious holy Chriſtian.</l>
               <l>He's big with ſaving Faith (he ſays) yet, He</l>
               <l>Has Not one ſpark of Common Charity.</l>
               <l>'Gainſt Reaſon he perpetually VVhines,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it contradicts his black Deſigns.</l>
               <l>He diſeſteems dull Morals, for a Saint,</l>
               <l>My well belov'd Brethren muſt not want</l>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:100279:49"/>
               <l>Soul warming thoughts; ſo warm that they did dwell,</l>
               <l>Firſt in the Womb, then in the Breaſts of Hell.</l>
               <l>He flouts the Common Prayer, yet the poor Fool,</l>
               <l>Himſelf, not them, does turn to ridicule,</l>
               <l>He hates a Form, yet loves his dear Nonſence;</l>
               <l>Nauſeats his God with his Impertinence.</l>
               <l>With Eyes turn'd up, Mouth ſcrew'd, and Monkey Face</l>
               <l>He loudly Bawls to God for ſaving Grace.</l>
               <l>With Meen ſo baſe and ſcurvy as if even</l>
               <l>His Apiſh poſtures only wou'd pleaſe Heaven.</l>
               <l>And then his ſnivelling tone to the moſt High,</l>
               <l>He does conclude his Curious Melody.</l>
               <l>If things ſucceed not as his Humour Wou'd,</l>
               <l>He ſtrai't grows angry, and he huffs his God:</l>
               <l>And this (as if God knew not what to do)</l>
               <l>And that wou'd have been for thy Glory too.</l>
               <l>Then muſled in his Cloak <hi>Roger</hi> begins</l>
               <l>In's Sermon to dawb forth Soul killing Sins.</l>
               <l>Murder, and theft, and pride, and Gluttony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which in their Lives none more Applauds then He,</l>
               <l>Yet if you do ſurvey the Liſt with Care,</l>
               <l>You'l quickly find Rebellon is hid there.</l>
               <l>And when hee's preſt to Dutys for ſome Hours,</l>
               <l>He ne're puts in? Obey the Higher Powers,</l>
               <l>At Surplice and Lawn ſleeves he takes offence,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they are the Types of Innocence,</l>
               <l>For that he hates, and with it Men of Senſe,</l>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:100279:49"/>
               <l>The Reverend Prelate he ſtill Villifies,</l>
               <l>'Cauſe they detect his curſed Villanies.</l>
               <l>Hand them they Bark, come let us pull them down</l>
               <l>For this ſame Mitre does ſupport the Crown.</l>
               <l>They'r the Kings trueſt friends, yet thought it good</l>
               <l>To drown his Kingdom in a Sea of Blood.</l>
               <l>They the Kings Perſon wou'd protect they ſaid,</l>
               <l>Yes, yes, forſooth, by Cutting off his Head.</l>
               <l>And this they did, inſpir'd by Zeal alone,</l>
               <l>To faſten Chriſt in his Triumphant Throne.</l>
               <l>As if Damn'd Lyes, falſe Oathes, and Baſe Deceit,</l>
               <l>Propt up his Throne and made him truly Great.</l>
               <l>As if the Devil himſelf that acted them,</l>
               <l>Did bring the Luſtre to his Diadem.</l>
               <l>Nay they go on yet with the ſame Intents,</l>
               <l>By Molding to their Minds new Parliaments,</l>
               <l>Some of the Great they by their whimſeys guide</l>
               <l>To like their Treaſon, and to 'ſteem their Pride.</l>
               <l>In other things like Methods they purſue,</l>
               <l>For ev'n the Sh'riffs muſt be Fanaticks too.</l>
               <l>The Judges too they'd to their Party gain,</l>
               <l>Did they want either Honeſty or Brain.</l>
               <l>And when their wheedling Tricks do fail on theſe</l>
               <l>They poiſon ſoon ſome Country Juſtices.</l>
               <l>Then had they once the dear Militia,</l>
               <l>They'd mount the Saddle, and make <hi>Charles</hi> obey.</l>
               <l>Thus firſt they'd make him but a very Straw,</l>
               <l>And then at laſt Controul and give him Law.</l>
               <l>In fine they are the foes of Royal State,</l>
               <l>Order is the great Object of their Hate.</l>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:100279:50"/>
               <l>Nor God nor Men theſe Furies ſeek to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>They'd bruiſe the Crown, and Tear our Surplices.</l>
               <l>They'd undermine the Churches Harmony,</l>
               <l>And ride a full Career to Popery.</l>
               <l>They all Mankind, except themſelves, Deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Chiefly the great for being Good and Wiſe.</l>
               <l>Some Subtile have, and ſome have Giddy Souls,</l>
               <l>Some Fools, ſome Knaves, and ſome are Knaves and Fools.</l>
               <l>Theſe Vermin wou'd ev'n the beſt things Command</l>
               <l>And ſuck up all the Sweetneſs of the Land.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>THE <hi>Sollicitous Citizen</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>COntinuall Hubbub, and the noiſe of <hi>PLOT,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Idle ſuſpicions of he knows not what,</l>
               <l>The Pope, the Devil, and the French three years,</l>
               <l>Have <hi>Citt</hi> enſlav'd to Jealouſies and Fears,</l>
               <l>Nor any proſpect yet of Peace appears.</l>
               <l>Bandy'd about 'twixt Credit and Deſpair,</l>
               <l>Who's ſafe (he crys) while ſuch Deſigns there are?</l>
               <l>And what is more peplexing can't tell where.</l>
               <l>No, tho' of late he to his ſide have got</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> that Devil at cold ſcent of <hi>PLOT.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:100279:50"/>
               <l>But the poor Cur at <hi>Oxford</hi> loſt his fame,</l>
               <l>Where he Ran Counter to's eternal ſhame;</l>
               <l>There the baſe Man Diſloyal and Unjuſt</l>
               <l>A Second time prov'd Traytor to his Truſt,</l>
               <l>In vain from him Diſcoveries you hope,</l>
               <l>Till he the whole confeſſes in a Rope.</l>
               <l>But this to <hi>Citt</hi> no ſatisfaction gives,</l>
               <l>He's ſtill uneaſie, and in Fear he lives,</l>
               <l>Cryes there are others who can find out Plots,</l>
               <l>(And make perhaps) as well as Dr. <hi>Oates;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Says wiſer Heads than his the City Rule</l>
               <l>(Or elſe I'd ſaid each <hi>Citt</hi> had been a Fool)</l>
               <l>Say what you will we will ſecure our Home,</l>
               <l>Be all in Readyneſs at Beat of Drum,</l>
               <l>Who knows how ſoon the K. of <hi>France</hi> may come?</l>
               <l>The Guards each night, you'd ſplit to ſee the Farce,</l>
               <l>(Like Rattle Snakes, with Bandaliers at A—</l>
               <l>Ty'd to long Swords, and dreſt in Greaſy Buff,</l>
               <l>Majeſtick Porters) through the City Huff;</l>
               <l>While Leader, Fore-horſe like, the Pageant makes</l>
               <l>With formal ſtrut, and gaudy Toſſell ſhakes.</l>
               <l>In this brave Pomp they walk to Rendezvouze,</l>
               <l>And there from Nine to Six ſecurely bouze,</l>
               <l>In damn'd <hi>Mundungus,</hi> and as naſty <hi>Nantz,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They Curſe the Pope and Huff the K. of <hi>France.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Does but poor VVhore about their Quarters budge,</l>
               <l>Whom unkind Stars do force till Ten to Trudge,</l>
               <l>Strait bruſtling <hi>Myrmidon</hi> cries, who comes there?</l>
               <l>Stand or I'le Fire; or ſtir a foot that dare.</l>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:100279:51"/>
               <l>Raiſes the Guards; (for ſuch Alarms are Common</l>
               <l>Two hundred Men to ſeize on one poor Woman)</l>
               <l>Why here ſo late (cryes Leader) on what ſcore,</l>
               <l>What are you, I'm a Woman, you're a Whore,</l>
               <l>And fellow Buff-Coats, a ſuſpicious one,</l>
               <l>For ought I know, the VVhore of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As you ſay, Captain it may be Pope <hi>Joan.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such Fears as theſe our Mighty Dons of War</l>
               <l>Perform to ſhew the VVorld how much they dare,</l>
               <l>But here dull <hi>Cit</hi> is out in's Policy</l>
               <l>VVhile he on VVoman doth his Manhood try,</l>
               <l>Credulous Aſs! there's no more groſs miſtake</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Citizens</hi> Wives Beaſts of their Husbands make,</l>
               <l>Believe me <hi>Cit</hi> thoud'ſt better far Neglect</l>
               <l>The Plots abroad, and thoſe at home Inſpect</l>
               <l>Thou need'ſt not fear the Jeſuits, but the Leagues</l>
               <l>Of VVife with Courtier, <hi>Iſlington</hi> Intreagues.</l>
               <l>VVas it well known to each contented Sot</l>
               <l>VVhat don at home, how <hi>Jacky</hi> was begot,</l>
               <l>Hee'd be more jealous of his VVife then th' Plot</l>
               <l>But of all Pates, <hi>Cit</hi> has the ſofteſt one,</l>
               <l>The better (crys the VVife) to graft upon,</l>
               <l>But he by ſuch dam'd dullneſs is undon.</l>
               <l>VVhile on him Every Raſcal puts a trick,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Care, Curtis, Baldwin,</hi> and Seditious <hi>Dick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such Rogues as theſe do ſtill ſuſpicions give,</l>
               <l>And make new Plots that no man can believe,</l>
               <l>One makes him hope, another makes him fear</l>
               <l>Juſt like four Maſty Dogs upon one Bear,</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:100279:51"/>
               <l>VVho knows not which the true or falſe to call,</l>
               <l>But honeſtly, dull Soul, believes them all,</l>
               <l>Theſe are the Knaves who make the <hi>Cits</hi> ſuſpect</l>
               <l>Their Prince that he their ſafety does neglect,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe only care, (Heaven knows) is to protect.</l>
               <l>Theſe are the Villains who our Jarrs encreaſe,</l>
               <l>Nor till they're hang'd can we e're hope for Peace,</l>
               <l>Each Cobler's Stateſman-grown, and the bold Rabble</l>
               <l>Convert each Ale-houſe-board to Council Table,</l>
               <l>One Cenſures this, another blames that faſhion,</l>
               <l>And thus they ſettle the Affairs oth' Nation,</l>
               <l>On Votes and Councils are their Judgments paſt,</l>
               <l>And in what form they pleaſe Affairs they caſt,</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Colledg</hi> did, but he was hang'd at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:100279:52"/>
            <head>Iter Boreale.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AFter long practis'd Malice in the South,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brutus</hi> (the Peoples Ear, the Peoples Mouth)</l>
               <l>At length moſt prudently has Sally'd forth,</l>
               <l>And cautiouſly retir'd to his <hi>North.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Poyſon he has left behind in <hi>London,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By whoſe Infection <hi>Whigland</hi>'s Chiefs are undon.</l>
               <l>Charter lies bleeding, Ecchoing Orphans crys</l>
               <l>Reach Heaven, whilſt the guilty Cauſer flies.</l>
               <l>Whole Corporation ſuffers for Believing</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sneaksby</hi> who but one Garret had to live in.</l>
               <l>Yet had he had his Arbitrary Swing</l>
               <l>Wou'd all our Nobles to his Nine-pence bring.</l>
               <l>Wou'd curtail Monarchs and by grand Debate</l>
               <l>Reduce Great <hi>Britain</hi> to an <hi>Hamburg-State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(For <hi>Eighty Two</hi> ſhou'd be as <hi>Forty Eight.</hi>)</l>
               <l>But ſince great Ends by Providence are croſs'd,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Jeſuit-Whig</hi> Deſigns in Blanket's toſs'd,</l>
               <l>Since Jurors muſt no longer be forſworn,</l>
               <l>Nor private Sence 'gainſt Solemn Oath Suborn,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Oats</hi> Depoſals are Immortaliz'd,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Elliot</hi> ſtill remains Uncircumcis'd;</l>
               <l>Since Loyalty muſt take and All are for't,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Pomfret</hi> Eloquence won't take at Court,</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:100279:52"/>
               <l>Since Ryots for the Publick-Weal can't be</l>
               <l>Secure without Invading Royalty;</l>
               <l>And Legal Bearings up againſt the Power,</l>
               <l>In Peoples Right, force <hi>Demagogues</hi> to th' Tower.</l>
               <l>Since all the Juice of <hi>Tony</hi>'s Tap's quite ſpent,</l>
               <l>Which ſuckled long both <hi>good old Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(For ſome who this way look are that way bent)</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Bacon</hi>'s Brazen Head fix'd on his Shoulders,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>TIME WAS—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can only ſay to Property Upholders.</l>
               <l>Since Legal Monarchy muſt rule the Roſt,</l>
               <l>And care determin'd is to keep his poſt,</l>
               <l>Since Envy, Hatred, Malice do ſmall feats,</l>
               <l>Party detected in all holy Cheats:</l>
               <l>Thouſands of Guineys can't have Influence</l>
               <l>On him who hath of Loyalty due ſence,</l>
               <l>Since neither <hi>Wapping</hi> Treats, nor VVhigshead Clubs</l>
               <l>Aſſert the Right of <hi>Perkin</hi> or the Tubs,</l>
               <l>Since truth, and only truth muſt now prevail,</l>
               <l>Maugre St. <hi>Tony's</hi> Tap or <hi>Stephens</hi> Flail,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Brutus</hi> lately <hi>Londons</hi> Demagogue</l>
               <l>No Office has but where Men Diſembogue,</l>
               <l>'Tis time, high time to quit that hated place</l>
               <l>VVhere nought but Loyal muſt, dare ſhew its face,</l>
               <l>So Fiends Aſſociate VVizards ſtill forſake,</l>
               <l>Cajoll'd with hopes untill they come to ſtake,</l>
               <l>Thus inmate Rats who firſt eſpy the flaw</l>
               <l>In Ruinous Buildings prudently widraw,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neſwells</hi> VVhig Babells ſall, &amp; parting ſeems to ſay,</l>
               <l>Periſh ye with your Cauſe ſo I be out oth'way.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:100279:53"/>
            <head>THE MAD-MENS HOSPITAL, OR <hi>Preſbyterian Itch.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>OH happy Soil, unhappily poſſeſs'd,</l>
               <l>Your Natives now invade your Sacred peace,</l>
               <l>And that Religion we all profeſs'd,</l>
               <l>Muſt now by Exterpation ſucceaſe:</l>
               <l>Our Laws are broken, Birthrights ta'en away,</l>
               <l>Baniſh'd or Murder'd Innocents betray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>This Hell bred Change hath Reformation brought,</l>
               <l>By bold Interpritation of Text:</l>
               <l>VVhat was believ'd, and our Forefathers taught.</l>
               <l>By new dark Lanthorn Lights is now perplext.</l>
               <l>New Government's ſet up, the Rabble ſee</l>
               <l>A way to Rule the Church and Monarchy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>Oh treble damn'd! Rebbles to God and King,</l>
               <l>Who firſt put Arms into the <hi>Round-Heads</hi> hands,</l>
               <l>Taught them to know their Brutiſh ſtrength, who bring</l>
               <l>A right of Levelling to all Mens Lands.</l>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:100279:53"/>
               <l>Like Hounds unhunted left to their own Chaſe,</l>
               <l>Seize all that croſs their way, Noble or Baſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>They love the King as School boys Maſters love,</l>
               <l>Let them do what they will; How good a Man;</l>
               <l>Correct them he's a Tyrant, none above,</l>
               <l>If they admit, then Govern them that can.</l>
               <l>Break up the School, A <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> their Cry's,</l>
               <l>Learning hath Foold the World, and taught us Lyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Thus in this wilfull, and preſuming Age,</l>
               <l>Where Reaſons Blinded with Opinion,</l>
               <l>For currant Truth upheld by th' Peoples Rage.</l>
               <l>They Spurn at Truth, and true Religion.</l>
               <l>Thoſe Beaſt like Rights, which greater Beaſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade,</l>
               <l>Are the falſe Opticks of their Cheating Trade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Poor Country Men! the whole worlds hate or ſcorn</l>
               <l>Led by a creeping <hi>Will ih' Wiſp's</hi> falſe Fire,</l>
               <l>Like him to Malice and to Miſchiefs born,</l>
               <l>Leads you to periſh in a poyſon'd Mire.</l>
               <l>Pride made a Devil, what is't made thee ſo?</l>
               <l>Malice: So coupled both together go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>But tell me yet Madmen have Intervalls,</l>
               <l>What end do you propoſe? ſuppoſe your Plot,</l>
               <l>Shou'd take effect that Pallaces and Halls,</l>
               <l>The King, the Duke, Lords, Papiſts and who not</l>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:100279:54"/>
               <l>Shou'd in one Ruin fall what wou'd Succeed?</l>
               <l>Cutting of Throats make one another Bleed!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>For the great King will not deſcend to reign,</l>
               <l>You (in his Members) Crucify him here,</l>
               <l>In time compleat when he will come again,</l>
               <l>'Twill be to your Confuſion, and Fear:</l>
               <l>Order Supports the World, nothing can ſtand</l>
               <l>VVithout it; Beaſts have Order and Command:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>Theſe very Sects who now together joyn,</l>
               <l>Will then divide, and each their Claim advance.</l>
               <l>This is the Truth I hold, that Lordſhip's Mine,</l>
               <l>'Tis falſe, 'tis not, 'tis for the K. of <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For when that one anothers Blood we draw,</l>
               <l>'Tis time a third ſhou'd come to give us Law.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:100279:54"/>
            <head>STATE CASES PUT TO <hi>Iack Presbyter.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>JAck</hi> if you have one Grain of Sence,</l>
               <l>That's free from pride and Impudence,</l>
               <l>Say ſomething in your own Defence.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But Lye not.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy doſt thou make our Blood recoil,</l>
               <l>VVith noiſe of Plots and Popiſh Guile,</l>
               <l>VVhile you're the Traytor all the while.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Bygot?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy doſt thou brood upon the Plot,</l>
               <l>To hatch the Miſchiefs <hi>Room</hi> cou'd not,</l>
               <l>And play th'old Game? but we have caught</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye Napping.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy did the little <hi>Dorſet</hi> Eel,</l>
               <l>To make the Brain ſick Crowd Rebel,</l>
               <l>Sad ſtorys in the <hi>City</hi> tell,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Wapping?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What did the weſtern progreſs mean,</l>
               <l>When a fine Duke did march between,</l>
               <l>L. <hi>Gray</hi> and <hi>Tommy</hi> to be ſeen.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oth' Women?</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:100279:55"/>
               <l>How Country Proteſtants did run,</l>
               <l>To Gaze upon a Royall Son</l>
               <l>God bleſs him or wee're quite undone</l>
               <l>For Freemen.</l>
               <l>What meant <hi>Ben: Harri's</hi> Appeal</l>
               <l>So full of Loyalty and Zeal,</l>
               <l>VVas it not written for to heal</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Breaches?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy did the Commons houſe Addreſs</l>
               <l>And move the King that hee'd Releaſe</l>
               <l>The Villain from the <hi>Marſhalſeas:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Gratis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And prethe <hi>Jack</hi> did'ſt never hear</l>
               <l>The famous Speech of Noble Peer</l>
               <l>Stuft with true proteſtants, and bare</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fac'd Treaſon?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy were ſo many Thouſands Spread</l>
               <l>That every poſt Town packets had,</l>
               <l>VVithout one penny for 'em paid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Reaſon?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why did the perjur'd Jury Save</l>
               <l>The little Elephantine Knave,</l>
               <l>And on the Bills back ſide Engrave,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ignoramus?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Jurys are now a Town Tropan,</l>
               <l>A Tory Trap they know their Man</l>
               <l>This <hi>Jack</hi> we plainly ſay, nor can</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You Blame us.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:100279:55"/>
               <l>Why did you ſtickle Tooth and Nayl</l>
               <l>The penall Statutes to repeal</l>
               <l>When you your ſelves wou'd never deal</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such Meaſure?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But did inhumanly impoſe</l>
               <l>On all you Judg'd Diſſenting Foes,</l>
               <l>Heavy Mulcts and heavier Blows,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At Pleaſure.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why did the Knights and Burgers Vote</l>
               <l>No Man ſhou'd lend the King a Groat</l>
               <l>Tho' good Security were brought</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Royal?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But oh! that <hi>Brittain</hi>'s Majeſty</l>
               <l>Is never to be truſted, why,</l>
               <l>Confounded <hi>Jack,</hi> was that ſaid? I</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Defyall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy do you ſuffer <hi>Janeway</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Curtis</hi> factious Lyes to ſay</l>
               <l>And Hireling <hi>Care</hi> the Devills <hi>Ama—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nuenſis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhy doth the Packet of Advice</l>
               <l>And proteſtant true Mercuries</l>
               <l>Scare Folks with weekly Forgeries</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Frenzies?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And yet you Eaſily can ſpy</l>
               <l>In <hi>Rogers</hi> works ſtate Hereſy</l>
               <l>And Popery and all in <hi>He—</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Raclitus</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:100279:56"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jack</hi> if you will theſe Scruples weigh,</l>
               <l>And any thing in anſwer ſay,</l>
               <l>To Query once again it may</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Invite us</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>THE <hi>Geneva Litany,</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom the Tap in the Guts of the Honourable Stump,</l>
               <l>From which runs Rebellion, that ſtinks like the Rump,</l>
               <l>On purpoſe to leaven the Factious Lump,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From him that aſpires as high as the Crown,</l>
               <l>And vows to pull Copes and Cathedrals down,</l>
               <l>Fit only to govern the World in the Moon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the Prick-ear'd <hi>Levite,</hi> that can without pain</l>
               <l>Swear black into white, then deny it again;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Name did deſign him a Villain in Grain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:100279:56"/>
               <l>From his Black-Bills, and Pilgrims with Sticks in their hands</l>
               <l>That came to make up a Religions Band,</l>
               <l>Then Raviſh our Wives, and Inhabit our Land,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the Mouth of the City, that never gives o'r</l>
               <l>To complain of Oppreſſions unheard-of before,</l>
               <l>And yet for his Letchery will not quit ſcore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the <hi>Cent per Cent</hi> Scriv'ner, and every Statetrick;</l>
               <l>That rails at Intemp'rance, who yet will not ſtick</l>
               <l>To clear a young Spend thrift's Eſtate at a lick,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the Force and the Fire of the Inſolent Rabble,</l>
               <l>That wou'd hurl the Government into a <hi>Babel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And from the nice Fare of the Mouſe-ſtarver's Table,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the Elder in <hi>New-ſtreet,</hi> that does Goggle and Cant,</l>
               <l>Then turns up his Whites, to noſe it, and pant,</l>
               <l>And at the ſame time plays Devil and Saint,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Jenkin's Homilies</hi> drawn through the Noſe,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Langley, Dick, Baldwin,</hi> and all ſuch as thoſe,</l>
               <l>And from Brawny <hi>Settles</hi> his <hi>Poem</hi> in <hi>Proſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:100279:57"/>
               <l>From a Surfeit occaſion'd by Proteſtant Feaſts,</l>
               <l>From Sedition for Sawce, and Republicks for Gueſts,</l>
               <l>With Treaſon for Grace-Cup, and Faction the reſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the Conſcience of Cits, reſembling their Dames,</l>
               <l>That in Publick are Nice, but in private ſo Tame,</l>
               <l>That they'l not ſtick out for a Touch of that Same,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the blind Zeal of all Democratical Tools,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Whigland,</hi> and all its Anarchical Rules,</l>
               <l>Deviſed by Knaves, and Impoſed on Fools,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the late Times Reviv'd, when Religion was gain,</l>
               <l>And Church-Plate was ſeiz'd for Reliques Prophane,</l>
               <l>Since practic'd by Searching Sir <hi>William</hi> again,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From ſuch Reformation where Zealots begun,</l>
               <l>To preach Heaven muſt by firm Bulwarks be won,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Te Deum</hi> ſung from the mouth of a Gun,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Parliamentarians,</hi> that out of their Love</l>
               <l>And Care for His Majeſty's Safety, wou'd prove</l>
               <l>The ſecureſt way were His Guards to remove,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From Sawcy PETITIONS, that ſerve to inflame us,</l>
               <l>From all who for ASSOCIATION are famous,</l>
               <l>From the Devil, the Doctor, and the Damn'd IGNORAMUS.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:100279:57"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Norwich Litany.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>DEfend us from all Popiſh Plots,</l>
               <l>That ſo the People Pray;</l>
               <l>And eke alſo from Treacherous <hi>Scots</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As bad or worſe then they.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From Parliaments long Rumps and Tails</l>
               <l>From Houſe of Commons Furies</l>
               <l>Defend us eke from Proteſtant Flayls</l>
               <l>And Ignoramus Jurys.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Protect us now and evermore</l>
               <l>From a white ſheet and Proctor.</l>
               <l>And from that noble Peer brought or'e</l>
               <l>The <hi>Salamanca</hi> Doctor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Doctor with a witneſs ſure</l>
               <l>Both in his riſe and fall,</l>
               <l>His Exit almoſt as Obſcure</l>
               <l>As his Original.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:100279:58"/>
               <l>Deſigns and Dangers far Remove</l>
               <l>From this Diſtreſſed Nation,</l>
               <l>And damn the Trayterous model of</l>
               <l>The new Aſſociation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And may the prick Ear'd party that</l>
               <l>Have coyn Enough to Cupboard,</l>
               <l>Forbear to ſhiver an Eſtate,</l>
               <l>And ſplinters mount for <hi>Hobart.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From Sixteen ſelf conceited Peers</l>
               <l>Protect our Soveraign ſtill,</l>
               <l>And from the damn'd Petitioners</l>
               <l>For the Excluſive Bill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Guard Heav'n great <hi>Charles</hi> and his Eſtate</l>
               <l>'Gainſt <hi>Tony</hi> upon <hi>Tony,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And from a Houſe of Commons that</l>
               <l>Will give the King no Money.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From thoſe that did Deſign and Laugh</l>
               <l>At <hi>Tangier</hi> in Diſtreſs</l>
               <l>And were <hi>Mahometans</hi> worſe by half</l>
               <l>Then all the <hi>Moors</hi> at <hi>Fez.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From ſuch as with Uſurping hand</l>
               <l>Drive Princes to Extreams;</l>
               <l>Confound all their Devices, and</l>
               <l>Deliver <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>James.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:100279:58"/>
               <l>But may the Beauteous youth come home,</l>
               <l>And do the thing that's fit,</l>
               <l>Or I muſt tell that <hi>Abſolom</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He has more Hair then Wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>May he be wiſe, and ſoon Expel</l>
               <l>Th' old Fox th' old fawning Elf;</l>
               <l>The time draws nigh <hi>Achitophel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will make away himſelf.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Jury I've impanell'd here</l>
               <l>Of honeſt Lines and true</l>
               <l>Whom you'l I doubt at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Find Ignoramus too.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:100279:59"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Loyall Litany.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom a new Modell'd Jeſuit in a <hi>Scotch</hi> Bonnet,</l>
               <l>With a Maſs underſleeve, and a Covenant on it,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Iriſh</hi> Sedition blown out of <hi>French</hi> Sonnet,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From conſpiring at <hi>Joes</hi> and Cabballing at <hi>Mews,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From Sir <hi>Guts</hi> holy Tub of uncircumcis'd <hi>Jews</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From Gibbet, and Halter which will be their Dues,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From a Parliament Man rak'd out of the Embers,</l>
               <l>From Knights that haunt Counters. and Lunatick Members,</l>
               <l>From Presbyters <hi>Januarys,</hi> and Papiſts <hi>Novembers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From hugging a Witch and conſulting the Devil,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Welch</hi> Repermates which are ſomthing uncivil,</l>
               <l>From the Touch of a <hi>Scot</hi> to cure the Kings Evil,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the Mutinous Clamours of ſuch as raiſe Fears,</l>
               <l>From thoſe that wou'd ſet us together by the Ears,</l>
               <l>Who ſtill for the ſhipwrack of Monarchy ſtears,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:100279:59"/>
               <l>From Rebellion wrapt up in an humble petition,</l>
               <l>From the crafty Intrigues of an old Politician,</l>
               <l>From a <hi>Geneva</hi> Divine, and a <hi>Staffords</hi> Phyſitian,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From ſerving great <hi>Charles</hi> as his Father before,</l>
               <l>Diſinheriting <hi>York</hi> without why or wherefore,</l>
               <l>And from ſuch as <hi>Abſaloms</hi> folly adore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From Denying the King that which is his Right,</l>
               <l>From Caſhiering of Members for faults very Light,</l>
               <l>From the Troubleſom Searches of a Monyleſs Knight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From Libelling the Government, and Actions of Kings,</l>
               <l>From Vindicating Sectaries in Illegal things,</l>
               <l>From encouraging Faction which Rebellion brings,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From murmuring for ſending the Parliament home,</l>
               <l>From chooſing Fanaticks to ſit in their Room,</l>
               <l>That the Actions of Forty may not be out-don,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Iriſh</hi> Maſſacres by Papiſts don,</l>
               <l>From Seditious Cut Throats which thing is all one,</l>
               <l>From murthering the Father, and baniſhing the ſon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From ſhrouding all Villanies under the Cauſe,</l>
               <l>From making us happy by giving Sword Laws,</l>
               <l>From trampling oth' Mitre &amp; Crown with applauſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:100279:60"/>
               <l>From Hunting the King and abjuring his Race,</l>
               <l>From Cleanſers of Bungholes uſurping his place,</l>
               <l>From preachers in Tubs that are void of all Grace,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From Vulcans Treaſons late forg'd by the Fan,</l>
               <l>From ſtarving of Mice to be Parliament Man,</l>
               <l>From his Copper face that out face all things can,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From voting Lords uſeleſs, and dangeroufly Ill,</l>
               <l>From hanging of Biſhops for dropping the Bill,</l>
               <l>From letting Fanaticks have too much their Will,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From purging the houſe to obſtruct our free Choice,</l>
               <l>From Reſolving the King to oppoſe with one voice,</l>
               <l>From ſuch that at Miſchief do daily Rejoyce</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From all the Seditious that love not the King,</l>
               <l>From ſuch as a Civil war once more wou'd bring,</l>
               <l>And Repenting with <hi>Colledge</hi> at laſt in a ſtring,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:100279:60"/>
            <head>THE Laſt Will and Teſtament OF ANTHONY <hi>King of Poland.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY Tap is run, then <hi>Baxter</hi> tell me why</l>
               <l>Shou'd not the good the great <hi>Potapski</hi> die?</l>
               <l>Grim death who lays us all upon our backs,</l>
               <l>Inſtead of Sythe doth now advance his Ax.</l>
               <l>And I who all my Life in Broyls have ſpent,</l>
               <l>Intend at laſt to make a fettlement.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Imprimis,</hi> for my Soul (tho' I had thought</l>
               <l>To've left that thing I never minded, out)</l>
               <l>Some do advi e for fear of doing wrong,</l>
               <l>To give it him to whom it doth belong.</l>
               <l>But I who all mankind have cheated, now</l>
               <l>Intend likewiſe to cheat the Devil too.</l>
               <l>Therefore I leave my Soul unto my Son,</l>
               <l>For he, as Wiſemen think, as yet hath none.</l>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:100279:61"/>
               <l>Then for my Poliſh Crown that pretty thing,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Mon</hi>—tak't, who longs to be a King.</l>
               <l>His empty Head ſoft nature did deſign,</l>
               <l>For ſuch a Light and Airy Crown as mine.</l>
               <l>With my Eſtate, I'le tell you how it ſtands,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jack Ketch</hi> muſt have my Cloathes; the K. my Lands,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Item.</hi> I leave the damn'd Aſſociation,</l>
               <l>To all the wiſe Diſturbers of the Nation.</l>
               <l>Not that I think they'l gain their Ends thereby,</l>
               <l>But that they may be hang'd as well as I.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Armeſtrong</hi> in Murders and in Whoring skill'd,</l>
               <l>Who twenty Baſtards gets, for one Man kill'd.</l>
               <l>To thee I do bequeath my Brace of Whores,</l>
               <l>Long kept to draw the Humours from my Sores.</l>
               <l>For you they'l ſerve as well as Silver Tap,</l>
               <l>For VVomen give, and ſometimes cure a Clap.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How—d</hi> my partner in Captivity,</l>
               <l>Falſe to thy God and King, but true to me,</l>
               <l>To thee ſome heinous Legacy I'de give,</l>
               <l>But that I think thou haſt not long to live.</l>
               <l>Beſides thou'ſt Wickedneſs enough in ſtore,</l>
               <l>To ſerve thy ſelf, and Twenty Thouſand more.</l>
               <l>To thee (young <hi>Gray</hi>) I'd ſome ſmall Toy preſent,</l>
               <l>For you with any thing can be Content.</l>
               <l>Then take the Knife with which I cut my Corns,</l>
               <l>T'will ſerve to pare and ſharp your Lordſhips Horns</l>
               <l>That you may Rampant <hi>Mon—</hi> puſh and gore,</l>
               <l>Till he ſhall leave your houſe and change his Whore.</l>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:100279:61"/>
               <l>On top of Monument let my Head ſtand,</l>
               <l>It ſelf a Monument, where firſt began</l>
               <l>The flame that has Endangered all the Land.</l>
               <l>But firſt to <hi>Titus</hi> let my Fars be thrown,</l>
               <l>For He 'tis thought will ſhortly loſe his own.</l>
               <l>I leave Old <hi>Baxter</hi> my Invenom'd Teeth,</l>
               <l>To Bite and Poyſon all the Biſhops with.</l>
               <l>My Squinting Eyes let Ignoramus wear,</l>
               <l>That they may this way look, and that way ſwear.</l>
               <l>Let the <hi>Citts</hi> take my Noſe becauſe 'tis ſaid,</l>
               <l>That by the Noſe I them have always led.</l>
               <l>But for their Wives I nothing now can ſpare,</l>
               <l>For all my Life time they have had their ſhare,</l>
               <l>Let not my Quarters ſtand on <hi>City</hi> Gate,</l>
               <l>Leaſt they new Sects and Factions do create.</l>
               <l>For certainly the Presbyterian VVenches,</l>
               <l>In dirt will fall to Idolize my Haunches.</l>
               <l>But, that I may to my old Friend be Civil,</l>
               <l>Let ſome Witch make them Mummy for the Devil.</l>
               <l>To good K. <hi>Charles</hi> I leave (tho faith, 'tis pity,)</l>
               <l>A Poy ſon'd Nation, and deluded City.</l>
               <l>Seditious Clamours, Murmurs, Jealouſies,</l>
               <l>Falſe Oathes, ſham ſtoryes, and Religious Lyes.</l>
               <l>Ther's one thing ſtill which I had quite forgot,</l>
               <l>To him I leave the Carcaſs of my Plot.</l>
               <l>In a Conſumption the poor thing doth Lie,</l>
               <l>And when I'm gon 'twill pine away, and die.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Jenkings</hi> in a Tub my worth declare,</l>
               <l>And let my Life be writ by <hi>Harry Care.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:100279:62"/>
               <l>And if my Bowels in the Earth find Room,</l>
               <l>Then let theſe Lines be writ upon my Tomb.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>ANEPITAPH upon his Bowels.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>YE Mortal</hi> Whigs <hi>for death prepare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For mighty</hi> Tapsky's <hi>Guts lie here:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will his great Name keep ſweet d'y' think!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For certainly his Entrals Stink.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas! 'tis but a Fooliſh pride</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To outſin all Mankind beſide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When ſuch Illuſtrious Garbage muſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be mingled with the Common duſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Palfe Nature! that cou'd thus delude</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Cheater of the Multitude.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That put his Thoughts upon the Wing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Egg'd 'em on to be a King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>See now to what an uſe ſhe puts</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Noble great and little Guts.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tapski <hi>who was a Man of Wit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had guts for other uſes fit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tho Fiddle ſtrings they might not be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Becauſe he hated Harmony)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet for Black Puddings they were good,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Maſter did delight in Blood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of this they ſhou'd have drank their fill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(<hi>King</hi> Cyrus <hi>did not fare ſo ill</hi>)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poor Guts cou'd this have been your hap,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sh'rif</hi> Bethel <hi>might have got a Shap.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But now at</hi> York <hi>his Guts muſt rumble,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Since you into a hole did Tumble.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:100279:62"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Codecil</hi> To the Former WILL Added in <hi>HOLLAND</hi> where he Dyed <hi>January,</hi> 20th. 1682.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MOurn! <hi>England</hi> Mourn! Let not thy griefs be feign'd,</l>
               <l>The Tap ſo long upon the Lees is Drain'd.</l>
               <l>The cringing Atlas of the State and Church</l>
               <l>Is faln, and left his proſelites ith' Lurch.</l>
               <l>Alas? what will become oth' Reformation?</l>
               <l>The Popiſh Plots, and Blank Aſſociation?</l>
               <l>Our Rights and Libertys and good old Cauſe,</l>
               <l>Patch'd Juryes, and th' Ignoramus Laws?</l>
               <l>What will become oth' Saints in Tribulation</l>
               <l>If <hi>Tory</hi> Loyalty comes into Faſhion?</l>
               <l>The <hi>Salamanca</hi> Doctor muſt take Poſt,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Tompſon</hi> and <hi>Leſtrange</hi> muſt rule the Roſt,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Monkey Care, Gotham,</hi> and Sniveling <hi>Dick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Muſt from the <hi>Hague</hi> e'en follow to old <hi>Nick.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In vain we ſtrive to ſhun th'appointed Fate</l>
               <l>That on the Knave as well as Fool does Wait.</l>
               <l>Tho I (ſaid he) have drawn Infectious Breath,</l>
               <l>And liv'd this Sixty years in ſpight of Death.</l>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:100279:63"/>
               <l>Had I been Hang'd but half thoſe years agon,</l>
               <l>Leſs Treaſon had Enſu'd, leſs Miſchief don.</l>
               <l>But as there is an Evil Genious Waits,</l>
               <l>On private Men, ſo there's on publick States,</l>
               <l>The univerſal Temper of Mankind,</l>
               <l>That always in the Ditch will lead the Blind,</l>
               <l>Of Sin and Faction the Alloted Bane,</l>
               <l>And for that very Cauſe has leave to Reign,</l>
               <l>Els <hi>Belzebub</hi> long ſince I'de been thy due,</l>
               <l>But that he fear'd I ſhou'd Supplant him too.</l>
               <l>Thus like the Devil I was made a Curſe</l>
               <l>To all Mankind: My Lord and Maſter worſe,</l>
               <l>Betray'd like <hi>Judas</hi> while I kept the Purſe.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill in every ſtate I walk'd ſecure,</l>
               <l>Grave with the King, and jocund with the VVhore.</l>
               <l>And never did one Lucky Miſcheif Vow,</l>
               <l>But Grateful Lawrells ſtill adorn'd my Brown.</l>
               <l>In every ſtate have ſo ſuccesfull been,</l>
               <l>As if Succeſs was the Reward of Sin.</l>
               <l>And all this while not the Severeſt Law</l>
               <l>Cou'd find me Guilty tho' they found a Flaw.</l>
               <l>Still by my Art or Ignoramus Friends,</l>
               <l>I Guiltleſs ſeem'd, and ſtill purſu'd my ends,</l>
               <l>For what was all the Specious pretence,</l>
               <l>Of Subjects right, and ſafety of the Prince?</l>
               <l>Religion, Liberty, Aſſociation?</l>
               <l>But to betray all and Enſlave the Nation?</l>
               <l>VVhich by ſo many VViles <hi>I</hi> did Inthrall,</l>
               <l>VVhilſt the blind Rabble worſhip'd me as <hi>Baal.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:100279:63"/>
               <l>But now the Miſt is Vaniſh'd from their Eyes,</l>
               <l>They ſee my Crimes throw all their thick Diſguiſe.</l>
               <l>(Tho' for the Saints and Brethren <hi>I</hi> dare ſay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> cou'd have kept in Ignorance to this day.)</l>
               <l>Once Sons of Light, but now the Saints are blind,</l>
               <l>VVhite Torys <hi>Janus</hi> like have Eyes behind.</l>
               <l>Thus all my ſhams diſcover'd <hi>I</hi> poor <hi>I</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVas forc'd altho' my wings were clipt to fly,</l>
               <l>Nay tho' no legs <hi>I</hi> had, my Gate was fleet,</l>
               <l>Oblig'd to Travel tho' <hi>I</hi> wanted Feet,</l>
               <l>From Juſtice (all my Crimes laid at my Door)</l>
               <l>Found Pow'r to run, who cou'd not crawl before.</l>
               <l>Old and Decrepid, gouty Toes, ſcar'd Shins,</l>
               <l>Turn <hi>Pilgrim</hi> in my Dotage for my Sins.</l>
               <l>My Strength and Action gon, <hi>I</hi> fly the Stage</l>
               <l>VVith all the Frailtyes that attends on Age.</l>
               <l>And nothing left me but the Conſtant VVill</l>
               <l>And Natural Inclination to do ill.</l>
               <l>Glad to ſham off with all my Vanquiſh'd hope</l>
               <l>To ſave that Neck that wou'd diſgrace a Rope.</l>
               <l>My Hopes are fled, let Death wind up the Charm</l>
               <l>Life's but a plague if <hi>I</hi> can do no harm.</l>
               <l>Our Canting words no longer will prevail,</l>
               <l>Our Liberty and Property's grown ſtale.</l>
               <l>The Rights and Priviledges of the Nation,</l>
               <l>The like Caſt Suits, when Loyalty's in faſhion,</l>
               <l>Our Plots and Perjurys will do no more,</l>
               <l>Our Slavery and Arbitrary Power</l>
               <l>Are with my Baniſh'd ſelf thrown out of Door.</l>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:100279:64"/>
               <l>What now Remains but that this Tap ſhou'd burſt,</l>
               <l>Who can do more that has e'en don his worſt?</l>
               <l>That the prov'd Foe Rejoyce not in my fall.</l>
               <l>Now Heart break Heart and bafle Catch and all,</l>
               <l>But ere I Fall a Victim tho' too late,</l>
               <l>In a vile Nation to a Viler Fate,</l>
               <l>I thus bequeath the Remnant of my Eſtate.</l>
               <l>My former Will as Fates Decretals ſtands,</l>
               <l>But ſomething's due unto the Netherlands</l>
               <l>For their Civiltyes Since here I Fled,</l>
               <l>Foul Napkins, Stinking Fiſh, and Mouldy Bread.</l>
               <l>To th' <hi>States</hi> becauſe they are a freeborn Nation</l>
               <l>I do bequeath my New Aſſociation.</l>
               <l>That perfect Model of true Anarchy,</l>
               <l>And Charm againſt all Monarch Tyranny.</l>
               <l>Tho' to live here had it ſo pleas'd the Fates,</l>
               <l>I had been King or th' Devil had had the States.</l>
               <l>My heart with Faction flam'd that ſource of Evil,</l>
               <l>I leave to my old Club that Haunts the Devil,</l>
               <l>As fickle and as falſe, as is their own</l>
               <l>Sworn Enemy to all that ſways the Throne.</l>
               <l>My Lungs my <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Frienps are yours,</l>
               <l>But for my Lights I leave 'em to the <hi>Bores</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To blow the Bellows of each new Sedition</l>
               <l>On any Change of Faction or Religion.</l>
               <l>I leave my Brains to that Inceſtuous Crew,</l>
               <l>The Lordly Tribe who lofty Treaſons Brew.</l>
               <l>Thoſe hot brain'd fiery <hi>Catalines</hi> of ſtate,</l>
               <l>Who their own and the Nations Ills create,</l>
               <l>And will I fear like me, Repent too late,</l>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:100279:64"/>
               <l>To <hi>Bethel</hi> and his Brethren I Reſign</l>
               <l>The Ax which Baffled Fate predeſtin'd mine,</l>
               <l>To do that Execution they would bring</l>
               <l>On Monarcy and an Indulgent King.</l>
               <l>To th' <hi>Salamanca</hi> Beagle of the Plot,</l>
               <l>I leave a Holter as his proper Lot</l>
               <l>For his ill management (whild Fools conniv'd)</l>
               <l>Of an ill Plot that was ſo well contriv'd.</l>
               <l>And laſtly to theſe Friends who were at ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Looſing themſelves to ſave a wretched Life,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> do Bequeath my Sledg as the juſt Fee</l>
               <l>Of their accumulated Perjury.</l>
               <l>You the Truſtees of this my Dying Will,</l>
               <l>If you in Villany wou'd proſper ſtill,</l>
               <l>Beſure you juſtly every point fulfil.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:100279:65"/>
            <head>SHAFTSBURYS FAREWELL OR <hi>The Aſſociation,</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>GReateſt of Men, yet Mans leaſt friend farewell,</l>
               <l>VVits mightieſt but moſt uſeleſs Miracle.</l>
               <l>VVhere Nature all her Richeſt Treaſures ſtor'd,</l>
               <l>To make one vaſt unprofitable Hoard.</l>
               <l>So high as thine no Orb of fire cou'd rowl,</l>
               <l>The Brighteſt, yet the moſt Excenticle Soul;</l>
               <l>VVhom midſt wealth, Honour, Fame, yet want of Eaſe,</l>
               <l>No power cou'd e're oblige, no ſtate cou'd pleaſe.</l>
               <l>Be in thy grave with peaceful ſlumbers bleſt,</l>
               <l>And find thy whole Life's only ſtranger, REST.</l>
               <l>Oh <hi>Sh—ry</hi> had thy prodigious Mind</l>
               <l>Been to thy ſelf and thy great Maſter kind.</l>
               <l>Glory had wanted Lungs thy Toomb to blow,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pyramids</hi> had been a Tomb too low.</l>
               <l>Oh that the VVorld (Great ſtatesmen) e're ſhou'd ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nebucadnezzars</hi> Dream fullfill'd in thee!</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſuch low Paths led thy great Soul away,</l>
               <l>Thy Head of Gold mov'd but on Feet of Clay.</l>
               <l>Yes, from Rebellions late Inhumane Rage,</l>
               <l>The Crimes and Chaos of that Monſtrous Age.</l>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:100279:65"/>
               <l>As the old <hi>Patriarch</hi> from <hi>Sodom</hi> Flew,</l>
               <l>So to great CHARLES his Sacred Boſom Thou;</l>
               <l>But oh? with more then <hi>Lots</hi> Wifes fatal Fault,</l>
               <l>For which ſhe ſtood in Monumental ſalt.</l>
               <l>Tho' the Black ſcene thy haſting Footſtep flyes,</l>
               <l>Thy Soul turns back and looks with longing eyes.</l>
               <l>Oh reſtleſs Peer! that the Records of ſame</l>
               <l>Shou'd give <hi>Erothratus</hi> and Thee one name.</l>
               <l>Great was his bold Atchievment, Greater Thine,</l>
               <l>Greater as Kings then Shrines are more Divine.</l>
               <l>Greater as Vaſter Toils it did Require</l>
               <l>To' inflame three Kingdoms, that one Temple fire.</l>
               <l>But where are all thoſe bluſtering ſtorms Retir'd,</l>
               <l>That roar'd ſo loud when <hi>Oliver</hi> Expir'd?</l>
               <l>Storms that rent Oaks, and Rocks aſunder broke,</l>
               <l>And at his Exequies in Thunder Spoke?</l>
               <l>Was there leſs Cauſe when thy laſt doom was given</l>
               <l>To waken all the Revellers of Heaven?</l>
               <l>Or did there want in <hi>Beligias</hi> humble Soil,</l>
               <l>A Cedar fit to fall thy Funerall pile?</l>
               <l>No: Die, and Heaven th' Expence of Thunder ſave,</l>
               <l>Husk'd as thy own deſigns down to Thy Grave.</l>
               <l>So husk'd may all the portents of the sky</l>
               <l>With thee our laſt great Comets Influence Die.</l>
               <l>May this one ſtroke our lowring Tempeſts Clear,</l>
               <l>And all the Fiery Trigon finiſh here.</l>
               <l>With thee Expire the <hi>Democratick</hi> Gall,</l>
               <l>Thy Sepulchre and <hi>Lethe</hi> ſwallow all.</l>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:100279:66"/>
               <l>Here ends the Poiſon of that Viperous Brood,</l>
               <l>And make thy Urn like <hi>Moſes</hi> wond'rous Rod,</l>
               <l>So may our Breaches cloſe in thy one Grave,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Sh—ry</hi>'s laſt breath three Nations ſave.</l>
               <l>And Dying thus t'avert his Countrys Doom,</l>
               <l>Go with more Fame then <hi>Curtius</hi> to his Tomb.</l>
               <l>But is he Dead! How! cruel <hi>Belgia</hi> ſay!</l>
               <l>Lodg'd in thy Arms, yet make ſo ſhort a ſtay!</l>
               <l>Ungrateful Country, Barbarous <hi>Holland</hi> ſhoar,</l>
               <l>Cou'd the <hi>Batavian</hi> Climat do no more!</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Sh—ry</hi>'s dear Life no longer ſave!</l>
               <l>What a Republick Air! And yet ſo quick a Grave!</l>
               <l>Oh! all ye ſcatter'd Sons of <hi>Titan</hi> Weep,</l>
               <l>This Diſmal day with ſolemn Mourning keep,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Iſraels</hi> Moulten Calf your Medall burn,</l>
               <l>And into Tears your great Laetemur Turn.</l>
               <l>Oh! wail in duſt to think how Fates dire frown,</l>
               <l>Has Thrown your dear <hi>Herculean</hi> Column down.</l>
               <l>Oh! <hi>Charon</hi> waft thy load of Miſchiefs o're,</l>
               <l>And land him ſaſly on the <hi>Stygian</hi> ſhore.</l>
               <l>At his Approach <hi>James</hi> loudeſt Trumpet call,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cromwell, Cook, Ireton, Bradſhaw, Hewſon,</hi> all,</l>
               <l>From all the Courts below, each well pleas'd Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>All the Republick Legions, Numerous Hoſt,</l>
               <l>Swarm thick to ſee your mighty <hi>Hero</hi> Land,</l>
               <l>Crow'd up the ſhoar and blacken all the <hi>Strand;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, what e're Chance on Earth, or Powers accurſt,</l>
               <l>Broke all your Bands, your holy Leagues all burſt,</l>
               <l>This union of the SAINTS no ſtorm ſhall ſever,</l>
               <l>This laſt ASSOCIATION holds for ever.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:100279:66"/>
            <head>THE RECOVERY.</head>
            <l>YET once more Peace turns back her head to ſmile,</l>
            <l>And take ſome pitty on our ſtubborn Iſle,</l>
            <l>She and her Siſter Truth, now hand in hand,</l>
            <l>Return to Viſit our forſaken Land,</l>
            <l>I ſee, I ſee! Oh <hi>Albion</hi> help the ſight,</l>
            <l>TRUTH long eclipſ'd, lift up her Sacred Light,</l>
            <l>And chaſe away thoſe obſcene Birds of Night.</l>
            <l>Th' ill-boding Scritch-owl we ſo long did fear,</l>
            <l>Hovering above in our thicken'd Air,</l>
            <l>Whoſe fatal note was never heard, but Death</l>
            <l>Follow'd th' Infernal Evidencing Breath.</l>
            <l>Hail Lovely Truth! Oh ſpred thy Rays Divine,</l>
            <l>And let thy dawning Beams more fully ſhine,</l>
            <l>Already thy glad Inference we find,</l>
            <l>And all now ſee, but they who will be blind,</l>
            <l>They ſee whilſt thou holds up thy guiding Light,</l>
            <l>The dangerous Errours of the former Night,</l>
            <l>A Night which all our Heaven did invade,</l>
            <l>By the Dire skill of State <hi>Magicians</hi> made.</l>
            <l>In a dark Cell the Wayward Brothers Met,</l>
            <l>Ith' midſt there was a Chair for Satan ſet,</l>
            <l>Which in his abſence—</l>
            <l>A little wither'd Conjurer ſupply'd,</l>
            <l>And all his Imps drank Venom from his ſide,</l>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:100279:67"/>
            <l>His word was (then he out his Tap did pluck.)</l>
            <l>Come my young Pugs of Treaſon, come and ſuck.</l>
            <l>This Helliſh Rite perform'd to work they go,</l>
            <l>To raiſe up Darkneſs from the ſhades below,</l>
            <l>Thick Miſts of popular fears, and Jealouſies,</l>
            <l>Did at the Necromantick Call ariſe,</l>
            <l>And in black Clouds hid all the Brittiſh Skies.</l>
            <l>Here firſt their unskil'd Sp'rits their Viſions play'd,</l>
            <l>And learn'd their Meſſage to the <hi>Hatfield</hi> Maid,</l>
            <l>Here firſt were rais'd the wondring World to ſcare</l>
            <l>The Armies <hi>Harris</hi> muſter'd in the Air.</l>
            <l>But now the Charms diſſolv'd, and <hi>England</hi> free</l>
            <l>From the Enchantment does its madneſs ſee,</l>
            <l>Sees its vain fears of that expected Day,</l>
            <l>No Royal Bloud, ſtain'd the Fifteenth of <hi>May,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Prevailing Truth has open'd Brittains Eyes,</l>
            <l>And Folly ſeen, begins to make her wiſe.</l>
            <l>Oh! Let us then unite, let Faction ceaſe,</l>
            <l>Nor think Confuſion is the way of Peace,</l>
            <l>That Schiſm muſt the Churches fall prevent.</l>
            <l>And breaking Laws, ſecure the Government,</l>
            <l>Let Traytors to expected Tryal come,</l>
            <l>And from the Mouth of Juſtice hear their Doom,</l>
            <l>Tis ſo, He's gon where Juſtice does maintain</l>
            <l>Her Seat in Peace, nor bears the Sword in vain,</l>
            <l>No Hackney ſpeakers there o're Law prevail,</l>
            <l>To Conquer thee by telling of a tale,</l>
            <l>Nor Factious, nor guilty Lords appear,</l>
            <l>To blunt that Sword whoſe Edge they juſtly fear.</l>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:100279:67"/>
            <l>No Garter blew nor Star that Court can awe,</l>
            <l>That Star which did long ſince its Beams with draw,</l>
            <l>Nor at the Tryal can its Light diſpence,</l>
            <l>To Cheriſh Treaſon with its Influence.</l>
            <l>Here all in vain ſtrives Councellor and Lord,</l>
            <l>Where the Revenging Goddeſs ſpeaks the word,</l>
            <l>Nor can Confeſſion turn aſide the Blow,</l>
            <l>From Criminals that own that they are ſo,</l>
            <l>Had this been done long ſince 't had ſav'd the guilt</l>
            <l>Of ſo much Bloud ſo prodigally ſpilt,</l>
            <l>VVhile certain Villany did hurry hence,</l>
            <l>To unjuſt Death ſuſpected Innocence.</l>
            <l>But Juſtice now is this Triumphant ſcene,</l>
            <l>Thy ſhame does end, and Triumph doth begin,</l>
            <l>All this to thy Defender <hi>Charles</hi> is due,</l>
            <l>Who now with the his Glorys does Renew,</l>
            <l>Already with freſh Beams the Crown does ſhine,</l>
            <l>Power Sacred grows, and Majeſty Divine,</l>
            <l>His mighty Scepters in his hand held faſt,</l>
            <l>Nor like a Deed is bent with every blaſt.</l>
            <l>Hold, hold Great <hi>Charles,</hi> this Reſolution hold,</l>
            <l>And in thy own, and Countrys Cauſe be bold,</l>
            <l>Whatever of this mighty Body thou,</l>
            <l>The Head, Reſolveſt, we thy hands will do,</l>
            <l>Dare to be happy, and to make us ſo.</l>
            <l>How great is Majeſty, and how Auguſt,</l>
            <l>How Godlike when 'tis Reſolutely juſt?</l>
            <l>Then 'tis that willing Subjects gladly meet,</l>
            <l>To throw their Lives before their Monarchs Feet,</l>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:100279:68"/>
            <l>There 'tis their Fortunes they before him lay,</l>
            <l>Sue to be Rul'd and Glory to Obey,</l>
            <l>Such <hi>Charles</hi> is now thy State, and ſuch the Train</l>
            <l>Of thoſe that now petition thee to Reign,</l>
            <l>See ev'n thy Prodigal Son does now deſtre,</l>
            <l>To leave his Husk, and Swine, and <hi>Wapping</hi> mire,</l>
            <l>In which ſo long he wallow'd up and down.</l>
            <l>Known to each dirty Kennel in the Town.</l>
            <l>And to his Injur'd Father and his Lord,</l>
            <l>Wou'd by his much wrong'd Uncle be reſtor'd.</l>
            <l>How well have <hi>W—ms, Jones,</hi> and <hi>W—ton,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>B—ch, G—rd, T—by,</hi> their great Duty don?</l>
            <l>How have they taught the People to Repent</l>
            <l>Their Zeal for their great Idol Parliament,</l>
            <l>How have they ſhewn the Arbitrary Way</l>
            <l>That Monſter took to make us all its Prey!</l>
            <l>They to looſe all, claim'd more then was their Right,</l>
            <l>And ſtretch'd their Pow'r only to break it quite,</l>
            <l>Theſe, theſe are they who have true Service done,</l>
            <l>Meriting their ſecret favours from the Crown,</l>
            <l>Theſe, theſe have made a Diſſolution be,</l>
            <l>Not VViſdom only, but Neceſſity.</l>
            <l>Theſe thus remov'd our Jealouſies and Fears,</l>
            <l>VVere ever ſuch deſerving Penſioners?</l>
            <l>Then <hi>Charles,</hi> ſince all things now conſpire to bleſs</l>
            <l>Thy graceful Age with Conqueſt and ſucceſs,</l>
            <l>Begin, Reſolve, and venture to be great,</l>
            <l>Nor over-throw thoſe vaſt deſigns of Fate.</l>
            <l>Begin at home, purge thine own houſe, and Free</l>
            <l>From Villains Tongues the Ears of Majeſty.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:100279:68"/>
            <head>ON THE <hi>Kings Deliverance</hi> AT NEW MARKET.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>SO Weapons proſper which are form'd 'gainſt Heaven,</l>
               <l>Or it is Vice grant Heavens peculiar Care,</l>
               <l>To whom are more then Vulgar Bleſſings given,</l>
               <l>And fire has ſav'd whom men more Cruel wou'd not ſpare.</l>
               <l>Some greater Genius him defends,</l>
               <l>By mighty means for mighty ends,</l>
               <l>And makes his Foes his Footſtool be,</l>
               <l>Or (what his Goodneſs more Delights to ſee)</l>
               <l>Makes them his Friends:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Nor do we more Congratulate,</l>
               <l>The preſent ſafety of the State,</l>
               <l>Then future peace which we anticipate.</l>
               <l>Now Treaſonous Arts are ſo Expos'd to view,</l>
               <l>The Plots as ſoon as hatch'd are blaſted too.</l>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:100279:69"/>
               <l>Popery's coming in they well might cry,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Methods wou'd fulfill the Propheſy.</l>
               <l>Nor did they cheat the World who took ſuch pain,</l>
               <l>The Jealoſyes they rais'd ſhou'd not be vain.</l>
               <l>Firſt Arbitrary power muſt down,</l>
               <l>Meaning the Crown.</l>
               <l>Then muſt ſome Miniſters be in Diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Becauſe a Rebel wants his place.</l>
               <l>More Liberty the People crave,</l>
               <l>Yet know not how to uſe that which they have.</l>
               <l>Next that Mens Propertyes ſecur'd muſt bee,</l>
               <l>They'f made the King a Property,</l>
               <l>What Monſtrous Bleſſings wou'd a Change create,</l>
               <l>Might Atheiſts mend the Church, and Knaves the State.</l>
               <l>But ſhall we twice be gull'd by one pretence?</l>
               <l>With one Allegiance have we loſt 'em ſince?</l>
               <l>Theſe very Tricks ruin'd us once before,</l>
               <l>Curſe of ſuch Arts which now are Arts no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>All that is envi'd ſtill attend the Throne,</l>
               <l>And him that ſits Theron.</l>
               <l>But when theſe Earthly Gods ſhall dye like Men,</l>
               <l>Let only Nature then</l>
               <l>(Nature the Rule of him by whom Kings Reign)</l>
               <l>Appoint who next ſhall grace and truth Maintain.</l>
               <l>May Names of Matchleſs <hi>Heroes</hi> of this Race,</l>
               <l>Diſtinguiſh happy times till time it ſelf ſhall ceaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100279:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
